--- Context for Data Collection ---
 the positive  relationship between horizontal coopetition and proactive search.  10990836, 2025, 4, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/bse.4230 by University College London UCL Library Services, Wiley Online Library on [29/05/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License 4901 3|Methodology 3.1|Samples and Data Collection This study employed a questionnaire survey to collect data, and  the content validity of the questionnaire was based on existing  literature. We chose the manufacturing industry as the research  sample because it plays a predominant role in driving China's  economic advancement and has the highest carbon dioxide  (CO2) emissions among industrial sectors (Zhao et al. 2017).  Hence, under China's climate crisis response policies, there  exists an urgent necessity for SPI within the manufacturin
--- Context for Measures ---
  errors in common sense content. The final sample included  companies from 18 cities in China, primarily concentrated  in provinces and cities such as Shaanxi, Jiangsu, Henan,  and Guangzhou. The industries mainly comprised manufac- turing sectors including construction materials, automotive  and parts, environmental protection and landscaping, as  well as clothing and textiles. It consisted of 67 state-owned  enterprises, 107 private enterprises, and 62 other types of  enterprises. 3.2|Measures A mature 7-point Likert scale was used for all the scale items  (Table1), with 17 indicating a range from Strongly disagree to  Strongly agree. 3.2.1|Horizontal Coopetition (HC) Based on Bouncken and Kraus (2013), we used three items  (Cronbach's =0.788) to measure horizontal coopetition. An  example item is Our company collaborates with direct compet- itors to achieve common goals. 3.2.2|Boundary-Spanning Search Drawing on the research of Katila and Chen (2008), as well 
--- Context for Correlations ---
sis to evaluate Harman's single-factor model.  Specifically, the model fit based on the single-factor model  (2=3803.225, df=464, 2/df=8.197, p<0.001, CFI=0.247,  TLI=0.195, NFI=0.229, RMSEA=0.175, and PGFI=0.381) was  inferior to that of the eight-factor model (2=822.118, df=436,  2/df=1.886, p<0.001, CFI=0.913, TLI=0.901, NFI=0.833,  RMSEA=0.061, and PGFI=0.680). Therefore, the CMV was  not an issue in this study. 3.5|Descriptive Statistics and Correlations Table 2 presented the results of mean, standard deviation,  and variable correlation results for the variables included in  this study. The correlation coefficients indicated that there  were significant relationships among the variables, and the  TABLE 2|Descriptive statistics, Pearson correlations, reliability, and validity. Constructs STD.  loading CR AVE ET EC HC PS RS CMS COS SPI ET 0.623 0.816 0.842 0.519 0.720 EC 0.638 0.892 0.870 0.630 0.413*** 0.794 HC 0.676 0.789 0.791 0.5
