ormance in horizon-tal alliances. The influences of ambiguity and conflict onperformance have been the focus of considerable research,yet the findings do not support a strong, direct relationship(see Table 1). Consequently, researchers have proposed non-linear (e.g., Schuler 1980) and interactive relationships(Fried et al. 1998) between stress and performance. Ourmodel examines the independent influenc
retail level. Table 2 summarizes research on the relationshipbetween effectiveness and stress and categorizes opera-tionalizations within the competing values framework. Mostrecent research acknowledges multiple facets 
re cognizant ofhigh conflict may view bargaining sessions as opportunitiesto reconcile disputes, and recognition of points of contentionmay lead them to stake out negotiation stances that are unac-ceptable to their trading partners. Conflict may also leadtrading partners to avoid interaction and interact less openlywhen bargaining commences (see Michaels, Day, andJoachimsthaler 1987). Consequently, amb
red by the simultaneous presence of ambi-guity and conflict. When responsibilities are poorly defined,consistent role obligations emanating from multiple partnersenable local retailers to attain acceptable sales levels. In con-trast, when retailers are confronted with inconsistentdemands from multiple trading partners, clearly delineatedresponsibilities enable retail managers to garner high contri-buti
14.504, p< .05). Table 3 provides correlations and descrip-
examination of both models (see Table 4).
learning on the Feeling of Knowing Is More Detectable inWithin-Subject Than Between-Subject Designs,ö American
