⌐Academy of Management Journat
1979, Vol. 22, No. 1, 104-117.
Influence and Information:
An Exploratory Investigation of
the Boundary Role Person ^s
Basis of Power
ROBERT E. SPEKMAN
University of Maryiand
This paper examines the boundary role person (BRP)
as an influence agent and investigates an aspect of his
potential ability to influence the decision outcomes of
other organizational members. It was found that as their
information requirements increase under conditions of
higher perceived environmental uncertainty, the constit-
uent members attribute to the BRP greater power in the
decision making process. The results further suggest
that, in light of the BRP's position in the transference of
information across the organization's boundary, the
reliance on expert power appears to be the most effec-
tive basis of social power for dealing with other
organizational members.
The boundary role person (BRP) occupies a unique position in a firm's
interaction with its environment (Adams, 1976). It has been hypothesized
that as a firm's external environment becomes more turbulent and
unstable the information processing function of the BRP becomes central
to a firm's ability to effectively gather, analyze and act on relevant infor-
mation (e.g., Aldrich & Herker, 1977; Leifer & Delbecq, 1978). The
potential dependency relationship, growing from the BRP's ability to
"cope with" (Thompson, 1967) or "absorb" (March & Simon, 1956)
uncertainty for those other organizational members, affords boundary
spanners an excellent opportunity to enhance their position of power
within the organization. Recent anecdotal evidence suggests, for example,
that much of the improved corporate status afforded to the purchasing
function is a direct result of the severe materials shortages of 1973-74.
Although eventual corporate recognition was inevitable, those turbulent
environmental conditions served to hasten management's acknowledg-
104
1979 Spekman 105
ment of purchasing's important role in the acquisition, importation and
processing of information crucial to the firm's survival.
Following in the tradition of Kahn, Wolfe, Quinn and Snoek (1964),
researchers (e.g., Keller & Holland, 1975; Miles, 1976; Organ & Green,
1972; Wall & Adams, 1974) have focused on the conflicting infiuences ex-
erted on BRPs by both their constituents (i.e., other members of the
organization) and persons outside of their organization. From these
studies has emerged a better understanding of affective factors which
might impair a BRP's ability to effectively execute his important boundary
spanning activities. Yet, a BRP is also a role senderùan infiuence
agentùattempting to infiuence the decisions and behaviors of those in-
dividuals with whom he interacts. Not only must the BRP negotiate with
BRPs from other firms who do not share the same goals and preference
orderings (e.g., Frey & Adams, 1972), the boundary spanner must also, at
times and to varying degrees, bargain with his own constituents. For ex-
ample, Strauss (1962) has described the various power tactics of
"bureaucratic gamesmanship" utilized by purchasing agents to enhance
their position of infiuence during the procurement decision making pro-
cess.
The purpose of this paper is to examine BRPs as infiuence agents by in-
vestigating aspects of their relationships with those constituents with
whom they regularly interact during the performance of their jobs.
Specifically, this paper focuses on the purchasing agent and his interac-
tions with members of the buying task group (BTG) (i.e., those constit-
uents responsible for purchasing related decisions). As it appears that the
importance of the BRP's boundary spanning activities increases as the
constituents require greater amounts of environmental information, one
objective of this research is to examine whether the degree of power at-
tributed to the purchasing agent by the other BTG members is associated
with their level of perceived environmental uncertainty. The second objec-
tive deals with a related issue and focuses on the individual power-related
behaviors of BRPs. Since BRPs, in general, have little if any formal
authority over their constituents, the goal here is to examine what base(s)
of social power purchasing agents utilize in their dealings with other BTG
members.
POWER IN BOUNDARY ROLES
Attributed Power as a Function of Dependency
Viewing power as the inverse of dependency, Emerson (1962, p. 32)
posited that "the dependence of actor P upon actor O is 1) directly pro-
portional to P's motivational investrhent in goals mediated by O; and
2) inversely proportional to the availability of those goals to P outside of
the O-P relationship." Incorporating Emerson's conceptualization in an
open systems framework, Thompson (1967) conceived of the organization
106 Academy of Management Journal March
as an interdependent, decision making system in which the primary goal
was to reduce the degree of uncertainty with which it had to contend. In
response to unmanageable levels of environmental uncertainty, Thomp-
son posited that organizations create specialized parts (i.e., boundary
spanning units) to cope with these contingencies. As a result of this struc-
tural adaptation, boundary spanning units presumably foster an im-
balanced dependency relationship among organizational subunits by
devoting more energy to monitoring crucial environmental contingencies
(see Aldrich & Herker, 1977; Thompson, 1967). Moreover, this increased
boundary spanning activity places the BRP (here the purchasing agent) in
the role of gatekeeper, thereby potentially increasing his or her ability to
control, channel and reformulate available environmental information
(Pettigrew, 1973; Rosen, 1976). Commenting on the important informa-
tion processing function served by the BRP, Aldrich and Herker (1977)
note that as constituents grow more dependent on the BRP's ability to
filter the fiow of information, the BRP's potential power position is fur-
ther enhanced.
Hickson, Hinings, Lee, Schneck and Pennings (1971) have more for-
mally presented the notion of intraorganizational power-dependency rela-
tions in a "strategic; contingencies" model. Building on earlier research
(e.g., Crozier, 1964; Emerson, 1962; Thompson, 1967), Hickson et al.
(1971) posit two structural properties as conceptual determinants of
power. They hypothesized that work fiow centrality (i.e., the degree to
which a subunit's activities are interlinked into the system) and non-
substitutability (i.e., the ability of an organization to obtain alternative
performance for the activities of a subunit) would contribute to the degree
of organizational power. On one level, one can see that a degree of
dependency (and, therefore, power) should accrue to purchasing by virtue
of its specialized function and centrality to the work fiow of the firm.
Traditionally, however, purchasing agents were viewed as order takers/ex-
peditors and, as a consequence, much of their boundary spanning activity
was preempted by other departments. In many cases, the filtering and
representative roles (see Adams, 1976; Miles, 1976) of the BRP were
under-utilized and the potential boundary relevance of purchasing was not
realized.
The need for purchasing agents, as Bi<Ps, to heighten their monitoring
activity was dramatically brought to the fore during the severe materials
shortages of the mid-1970s. As the purchasing environment grew more
turbulent, the purchasing agent's centrality became more salient,
presumably, as a result of the crucial role played by a BRP in the acquisi-
tion, importation and processing of purchasing-related information. One
can easily envision purchasing agents bolstering their unique gatekeeper
role through their contacts with outside sales personnel, knowledge of
potential and/or actual problems in the marketplace with respect to
material availability, information regarding alternative sources or sub-
stitute material, and so on.
1979 Spekman 107
It can be seen that as a BRP is able to reduce uncertainty for the constit-
uents responsible for purchasing-related decisions, they become depen-
dent upon him/her as a source of information. Purporting that this
dependency confers upon the BRP a position of power, both Crozier
(1964) and Perrow (1972) observed that power tends to be related to the
kind of uncertainty upon which depends the life of the firm. In the present
context, the BTG is devoted to purchasing-related decision making. It is
important to recognize, however, that it is not uncertainty per se that con-
fers power; rather, it is the ability to cope with uncertainty that determines
the degree of power achieved by the BRP. As the information demands of
the constituents diminishùunder conditions of lower environmental
uncertaintyùthe coping mechanism becomes less crucial, the need to ab-
sorb uncertainty abates, and the BRP's power dissipates.
Power, in this context, is defined as the ability to infiuence decision
making and is quite consistent with the definitions posited by Dahl (1957)
and other power theorists. Further, it should be noted that the present
conceptualization of power dependency parallels the Hickson et al. (1971)
"strategic contingencies" paradigm and, as a result, is also shaped by
structural constraints. In many respects, the preceding discussion suggests
a latent power which must be exercised if the true impact of the BRP's
power is to be realized. Similarly, Simon (1953) has suggested that the
magnitude of a power resource might be employed as a measure of power.
Thus, the actual power of a BRP is probably a function of the bases of
power available to him at any given time. This distinction is maintained by
Hickson et al. (1971, p. 218) who state "if the direction of the dependence
in a relationship is determined by an imbalance of power bases, power
itself must be defined separately from these bases."
Bases of Power and Constituent Compliance
Cyert and March (1964) were among the first to contradict the ra-
tionalistic approach to organizational decision making; they observed that
since organizational members often do not share the same preference
orderings, goals, et cetera, power is often exercised to affect decision out-
comes. Indeed, as Schein (1977, p. 64) noted, "power struggles ... may
be as endemic to organizational life as planning, organizing, directing and
controlling." Patchen (1974), building on the conceptual framework of
French and Raven (1959), examined the various bases of power by which
the various individuals participating in purchasing-related decisions exert
more or less infiuence on procurement decision outcomes. Despite the fact
that the research did not focus exclusively on the power bases exercised by
purchasing agents (as BRPs) to further their infiuence, Patchen's study
contributes to an understanding of the particular bases of power utilized
to affect organizational decisions.
The decision to employ either a reward, coercive, expert, referent or
legitimate base of power has certain consequences which may affect future
108 Academy of Management Joumal March
interactions and subsequent power attempts (Baldwin, 1971; Raven &
Kruglanski, 1970). Not only do BRPs (or any infiuence agent, for that
matter) have to weigh the costs associated with the exercise of power (see,
Harsanyi, 1962), they must also consider the impact of their infiuence at-
tempts on the long-run relationships with their constituents. For instance,
although coercive and reward power are both socially dependent, requir-
ing constant surveillance by the powerholder, the use of coercive power
tends to result in heightened conflict and hostility. The exercise of reward
power, on the other hand, appears to encourage continued interaction but
is also less likely to contribute to a long-term power-dependent relation-
ship, since the withdrawal of positive sanctions is apt to result in the less
powerful person's reversion to his previous behavior. Further, the effect
of the inducement, even if continued, is subject to diminishing utility.
The exercise of referent and/or expert power tends to foster a more
cooperative, prolonged relationship between individuals. Expert and
referent bases of power are seemingly more subtle in their impact, and
research suggests that a degree of shared values and goal congruence may
lie at the core of the emergent power dependent relationship (Raven &
Kruglanski, 1970; Raven, 1974). The point is that if BRPs are to infiuence
the decision outcomes of other constituent members, they need to devise
tactics (i.e., power strategies) for most effectively dealing with these
organizational members. In many cases, the decision can be quite prob-
lematic because BRPs do not have the traditional leverages of hierarchical
authority (i.e., a legitimate basis of power) at their disposal (Cleland &
King, 1968). Therefore, if BRPs are to successfully manifest their power,
they need to develop a power strategy which is, at the same time, consis-
tent with their base(s) of power and the consequence they desire (see,
Schein, 1977).
Interestingly, Patchen's (1974) results suggest that infiuence on specific
purchasing decisions often appears to be determined by those norms
which accord infiuence to those with greatest stake in the decision. Of the
five bases of power posited by French and Raven, expert power followed
by legitimate power seemed to be the next two most frequently mentioned
bases of infiuence. Patchen (1974, p. 216) also notes that reward, coercive
power and, to a lesser extent, referent power were "noticeable chiefiy by
their absence." It should be noted again that this study did not attempt to
isolate the bases of power exercised by a particular organizational member
and, therefore, while furnishing important behavioral insights may not be
directly transferable to an investigation of the specific power bases exer-
cised by BRPs.
In an attempt to contribute to an understanding of the BRP as an in-
fiuence agent, the present study examines two important research ques-
tions emerging from the literature cited above: (1) Is the level of power at-
tributed to purchasing agents (as BRPs) associated with the level of their
constituents' perceived environmental uncertainty, and (2) what bases of
1979 Spekman 109
social power are exercised by purchasing agents, as BRPs, to enhance their
power position?
METHOD
Tiie Sampie
The sample consisted of 20 firms from the greater Chicago area. These
firms represented 11 different industries of which 70 percent served mainly
industrial markets and the remainder served mainly consumer markets.
Using a sociometric technique (e.g., Patchen, 1974), BTG membership
was determined by asking the purchasing agent the names and titles of
those constituents with whom he interacted with respect to purchasing-
related decisions for the commodity for which he was responsible. Pur-
chasing agent centrality merely served to anchor a BTG's purchasing-
related responsibility to a particular commodity. While each decision
represented a commodity (21 different classes ranging from edible fats, to
steel, to metal fasteners) which was of considerable importance to each
firm in the sample, the study focused on rather repetitive purchasing deci-
sions. More specifically, each procurement decision typified a modified
rebuy situation in which the various BTG members "...have relevant
buying experiences, but the experience factor is not complete because new
alternative suppliers, items or marketing services are being considered"
(Robinson, Faris & Wind, 1967, p. 26).
Defined as an informal decision making unit (see, Spekman, 1977), the
BTG exemplifies a conceptualization of the lateral relationships (often
cutting across formal lines of authority) which emerge as a result of the
procurement process. The focus of the BTG is on the relationships which
develop between the purchasing agent and those other organizational
actors (i.e., production/manufacturing people, R&D engineers, quality
control personnel, sales managers and the like) with whom he/she in-
teracts during the purchasing decision making process. In this fashion, the
BTG defines a measurable communications network in which the objec-
tive is making purchasing-related decisions for a particular commodity or
class of commodities.
Each BTG members' questionnaire accentuated the interactive,
multiperson nature of the procurement process. (The reader can obtain
copies of the research instrument from the author.) Moreover, the
respondents were told that they were designated as members of a par-
ticular BTG "because part of your job entails interacting with a purchas-
ing agent with respect to the decision to purchase commodity X."
(Towards the end of the questionnaire, each respondent was asked to re-
spond to the question: "To what extent do you feel you are a part of the
buying task group?" All respondents retained in the final sample affirmed
their participation in the BTG.) During March-April 1976, 400
no Academy of Management Journal March
respondents were either personally administered or mailed questionnaires.
In total, there were 322 usable questionnaires (an 80.5 percent response
rate).
Measures
Environmental UncertaintyùWxih full recognition of the debate re-
garding the use of objective versus perceptual measures of environmental
uncertainty (see Downey & Slocum, 1975; Tosi, Aldag & Storey, 1973), an
11-item, perceptual measure of uncertainty (a = .68) was adopted from
Duncan (1972). In order to capture the relevant task environment, the
scale was modified to (1) focus exclusively on purchasing-related decisions
and (2) refiect the entire range of information inputs impinging on the
BTG. Specifically, attention was given to purchasing relevant factors ex-
ternal to the BTG but internal to the firm as well as factors external to
both the BTG and the firm. The following questions will illustrate the
distinction between the domains of the relevant task environment:
Relative to your role in the BTG, how often are you certain about what procedures
would be best for dealing with purchasing related problems that arise outside your com-
pany?
Relative to your role in the BTG, how often are you certain about what procedures
would be best for dealing with purchasing related problems that arise in other depart-
ments in your company?
It can be seen, therefore, that purchasing decisions can be affected by such
external factors as government regulations and economic conditions as
well as by internal considerations with respect to material tolerances, pro-
duction estimates, sales forecasts and so on.
Attributed Power-The power construct (a = .78) focused on the
degree to which the purchasing agent was perceived by his constituents to
influence the purchasing decision making process. Consistent with other
power theorists (e.g., March, 1955), attributed power was utilized to
measure the infiuence of the purchasing agent within the BTG. As the
scope of this study was limited to the procurement process, a specific item
measure (Patchen, 1963), adopted from the Robinson et al.'s (1967) "buy
phase," was employed to access the purchasing agent's infiuence in the se-
quence of decision making activities which are performed during the pur-
chasing process. Specifically, the power scale examined the purchasing
agent's infiuence in an eight-step succession of purchasing-related events
beginning with "problem recognition and/or anticipation" and ending
with the "evaluation and inspection of goods upon delivery."
The Bases of Social PowerùThe operationalization of the French and
Raven typology presented several difficulties, not the least of which was
the lack of a clear external criterion. A 15-item scale was constructed to
tap the bases of social power (i.e., three items for each power base).
Refiecting a high degree of face validity, these questions examined the
1979 Spekman 111
reasons other BTG members state they "follow suggestions or fulfill re-
quests made by the purchasing agent." The operationalization of the
power bases was depicted as:
(Reward) "He can give special help to those who cooperate with
him."
(Coercive) "He can penalize those who do not follow his sugges-
tions."
(Legitimate) "He has a legitimate right, considering his position, to ex-
pect that his suggestions will be carried out."
(Referent) "I respect him personally, and want to act in a way that
merits his respect and admiration."
(Expert) "I defer to his judgment in areas in which he is more
familiar than I."
A factor analysis, using VARIMAX rotation, was utilized to examine
whether the "bases of power" scale did, indeed, represent five distinct
constructs, each tapping a unique conceptual space. Such a "single com-
mon factor" approach has an implicit objective of construct validity. In
effect, an operational measure is a valid measure of a construct if it relates
in the way that a concept "should" to measures of other related con-
structs. As can be seen from Table 1, the factor analysis extracted four
factors with eigenvalues greater than 1.0. It is interesting to note that all
three of the expert power scale items (factor III) loaded heavily on One fac-
tor. Reward, referent and, to a lesser degree, legitimate power loaded
heavily on two factors (factors I and II), thus appearing to tap a concep-
tual property space which can be described as a more inclusive, noncoer-
cive base of power. This more complex construct seems to support the
notion that the bases of power are rarely used independently and, specifi-
cally, referent power is often exercised in combination with one or more of
the power bases (Raven, 1971). It can be seen that the ambiguous distinc-
tion between referent power and other power bases is accentuated further
by the high factor loading of a referent power scale item on factor III (ex-
pert power). Finally, factor IV is suggestive of a coercive base of power
but, due to the mixed loadings of the coercive power base items, must be
subject to guarded interpretation.
It should be noted that in an effort to avoid the operational difficulties
associated wtih the French and Raven typology, marketing researchers
(e.g.. Hunt & Nevin, 1974; Lusch, 1976) have abandoned the five bases
schema and have, instead, adopted a coercive/noncoercive power base
classification. While this consolidation achieves parsimony and solves
many empirical problems associated with differentiating the bases of
power, it is felt that this approach also loses valuable information. Since
an objective here is to more fully investigate the various power bases exer-
cised by BRPs in their attempts to infiuence constituent decision pro-
cesses, a compromise approach was utilized. Rather than retain the five
bases as independent constructs due to the high intercorrelations among
112 Academy of Management Journal March
TABLE 1
A Factor Analysis of the Bases of Social Power
Scale Items Denoting the Base of Social Power
I respect him personally, and want to act in a
way that merits his respect and admiration
I respect his competence about things he is
more experienced than I
He can give special help to those who
cooperate with him
He can apply pressure on those who do not
cooperate with him
He has a legitimate right, considering his
position, to expect that his suggestions will
be carried out
I defer to his judgment in areas in which he
is more familiar than I
He can make things difficult for me if I fail
to follow his advice
Because he is the purchasing agent I am
obligated to follow his suggestions
I can personally benefit by cooperating with
him
Following his advice results in better
decisions
I cooperate with him because I have high
regard for him as an individual
He can penalize those who do not follow his
suggestions
I feel I have to cooperate with him
I cooperate with him because I wish to be
identified with him
Cooperating with him can positively impact
on my performance
Eigenvalue
Percentage of Cumulative Variance
ExplainedFactor I
.711
.371
.771
.616
.115
.088
.434
.152
.672
.069
.282
.236
.001
.273
.065
5.06
33.7Factor II
.200
-.003
.094
-.038
.029
-.086
.087
.511
.349
.223
.406
.162
.457
.794
.762
2.03
47.2Factor III
.341
.642
.119
-.103
.102
.850
.011
-.023
.067
.547
.640
.050
-.008
-.050
.232
1.32
56.0Factor IV
-.035
-.232
.285
.564
.120
.207
.630
.268
.302
-.025
-.036
.751
.649
.117
.201
1.02
62.8
the power bases (see Table 2), the two highest factor scores on each ex-
tracted factor were combined to create four bases of power (i.e., noncoer-
cive I and II, expert and coercive.)' In this manner, problems associated
with multicollinearity were minimized and much of the descriptive infor-
mation of the five-base schema could be retained.
ANALYSIS AND DISCUSSION
While Allen (1966) discusses the flow of information across boundaries
as a technical problem, Pettigrew (1972) and others conceive of the BRP's
unique position in the information flow as a potential power resource.
'Although a legitimate power item had a higher factor loading on the coercive power factor (factor
IV) than the second coercive power item, it was not included in the final model. Exclusion of the
legitimate power item was based primarily on the greater difference between the mixed loading scores
on the second coercive power item.
1979 Spekman 113
TABLE 2
Zero-Order Correlation Matrix of the Bases of Social Power (n = 206)
Referent Power
(REFPOW)
Expert Power
(EXPOW)
Reward Power
(REWPOW)
Coercive Power
(COERPOW)
Legitimate Power
(LEGPOW)REFPOW
1.00EXPOW
.455***
1.00REWPOW
.605***
.317***
1.00COERPOW
.401***
.124*
.607***
1.00LEGPOW
.465***
.193**
.496***
.554***
1.00
*p < .05
**/? < .01
***p < .001
These findings support the positive relationship between the level of
perceived uncertainty and the power attributed to the purchasing agent
(/ò = .351, p < .01). It can be inferred that the power of the purchasing
agent emanates from a dependency built on the flow of material (Hickson
et al., 1971 refer to this as work flow centrality) and the flow of informa-
tion. Since the importance of purchasing to the continued flow of produc-
tion goods is felt to be relatively constant regardless of the level of uncer-
tainty, the positive correlation seems to suggest that coping with uncer-
tainty fosters a greater dependency as the perceived level of uncertainty in-
creases.
The notion of dependency is reinforced by further analysis suggesting
that BTG members operating under conditions of greater uncertainty
perceive purchasing to exercise greater influence in other than purchasing
related issues than those BTG members operating under conditions of
lesser perceived uncertainty {t = -4.80, p < .01). While the actual scope
of the purchasing agent's influence was not probed, the point is that BRPs
(in their gatekeeper role) sit at the juncture of many communication paths
and, therefore, collect and filter information that can potentially impact
upon the decision outcomes of many constituents, some of whom share no
regularized task related activities with the purchasing agent. It can easily
be envisioned that as long as the purchasing agent is perceived to effec-
tively filter and channel environmental information, and the information
is deemed crucial, the scope of his/her power can presumably extend to
such diverse areas as product design, long-range planning and other tradi-
tionally nonpurchasing areas.
Related to the notion of power dependency is the issue of the means by
which BRPs, as influence agents, exhibit their power. Table 3 summarizes
data examining the power-related behavior utilized by the purchasing
agent in his/her power attempts. In many respects, this model is felt to
depict the strategies by which the purchasing agent's power becomes
114 Academy of Management Journal March
TABLE 3
The Basis of Power as Predictors of Power: Multiple Regression Summary Tabie
Independent Variables Beta Weight Cumulative R' F (to add)
Expert Power J56 J39 25.80"
Coercive -.067 .42 0.73
Noncoercivel .079 .45 0.94
Noncoercive II -.043 .146 0.37
Overall Model 8.61*
*p < .01
**p < .001
manifest. It becomes readily apparent that the significance of the entire
model {F = 8.61, p < .01) and slightly over 90 percent of the explained
variance (13.9 percent) is directly attributable to the expert base of power.
This finding is consistent with the notion that the BRP's base of power is
primarily a result of his ability to gather and filter information deemed
crucial by his constituents. Whether as a result of the purchasing agent's
experience, access to information, or familiarity with purchasing-related
issues, the BTG members appear to rely on the BRP to improve their deci-
sion outcomes. Conceptually, and from the perspective of the BRP, the
utilization of expert power leads to greater cooperation and heightened
dependence (see Raven & Kruglanski, 1970). Interestingly, Strauss (1962)
observed that those purchasing agents concerned with improving their
status and expanding their influence tended to rely on "educational tac-
tics" which could easily be interpreted as the development of expert
power-based behavior. From the perspective of the BTG members,
however, other research indicates that a strong dependency can be prob-
lematic, since BRPs can conceal and misrepresent information, thereby
presenting to their constituents a distorted, self-serving view of the en-
vironment (Rosen & Adams, 1976).
A tendency to rely on expert power is mirrored in findings by Patchen
(1974), who reported that a person's knowledge, experience or access to
information were frequently mentioned as reasons an individual was in-
fluential in a decision. It is interesting to note that while Patchen (1974)
also observed the use of legitimate power (or authority) as a prevalent
basis of power, legitimate power was not included in the final model by
virtue of its poor and/or mixed factor loadings. Since the purchasing
agent has no formal authority over other BTG members, it is not surpris-
ing to find that legitimate power is not a viable power source in the present
context. Moreover, Strauss (1962) noted that "rule oriented" tactics were
not employed by the more influential purchasing agents who preferred to
operate informally so that they could more easily "bend the rules" to
achieve their own objectives.
The reader is cautioned, however, not to interpret these findings as sug-
gesting that BRPs rely solely on expert power in order to infiuence deci-
sion outcomes. From Table 4 it can be seen that one of the noncoercive
1979 Spekman 115
TABLE 4
Zero-Order Correlation Matrix Between Attributed Power
and tiie Bases of Social Power
Attributed Power
*p < .05
**p < .001Noncoercive
Power I
.1463*Noncoercive
Power II
-.0113Expert
Power
.3635**Coercive
Power
-.0095
power bases is also related to attributed power (r = .146, p < .05),
although there is a significantly stronger association between attributed
power and expert power (p < .05). (Hotellings' t was used to test for the
significance of the differences between the two correlation coefficients.)
This finding seems to accentuate the nebulous distinction between expert
power and the other noncoercive power bases. This correlation matrix
serves to temper the above discussion and tends to suggest that while ex-
pert power emerges as the dominant explanatory power base, its effective
utilization may be tied, to some extent, to the BRP's exercise of a com-
bination of power basesùin this case, other noncoercive power bases.
The weak support given to the BRP's utilization of referent power (as a
component of the noncoercive power-based factors) is consistent with
Patchen's findings (1974). Yet, both Adams (1976) and Organ (1971) rec-
ommend developing a referent power base as a viable strategy for BRPs to
compensate for their lack of formal authority when dealing across bound-
aries. These findings seem to indicate that reliance on referent power alone
may not be a successful tactic for the present sample of purchasing agents.
This discrepancy may be due, in part, to the present research context. That
is, since purchasing is perceived by many to be a low-status position, it
would follow presumably that the purchasing agent would not serve as a
basis for association and/or identification. While generalization beyond
this research setting may be tenuous, it is interesting to note that both
reward and referent power converge on the same factor. Perhaps this in-
dicates that purchasing agents, cognizant of their lower status, attempt to
gain and/or enhance personal loyalty and respect by "buying" (i.e.,
rewarding) their constituents.
The use of coercive power does not appear to be a suitable power base
for dealing with constituents. Patchen (1974, p. 216) interprets the absence
of sanctions (both rewards and punishments) as a result of demand
characteristics emanating from a "reluctance to talk about such models of
infiuence." A richer explanation, probing the interpersonal dynamics of
the procurement process, might refiect the costs associated with the exer-
cise of sanctions. That is, if a purchasing agent threatens another BTG
member with certain reprisals for nonperformance of a specified behavior
and the threat is not carried out, the purchasing agent has suffered a loss
of credibility. Further, the use of rewards, while more conducive to
116 Academy of Management Journal March
prolonged compliance, may lead to strained relationships because some
constituents may come to expect favors and the purchasing agent's reper-
toire of rewards is quite limited.
Finally, it should be noted that while these findings appear to substan-
tiate the conceptual relationship between environmental uncertainty and
the power attributed to the purchasing agent as well as the purchasing
agent's subsequent reliance on expert power, these results are subject to
guarded interpretation. Given that the purchasing agent has traditionally
been viewed as a low-status corporate member who often had no input
whatsoever into the purchasing decision making process, it is not surpris-
ing to find the_absolute mean score of the attributed power construct is
rather low (X = 2.282, range = 1.82). (The power construct was
measured on a five-point Likert scale with a score of 1 connoting "little,
or no influence.") Therefore, the low overall score may be viewed as
reflecting relative measures of high and low power, remembering that the
enduring "order-taker stereotype would probably mollify the opportunity
for the purchasing agent to achieve a great deal of absolute influence dur-
ing the purchasing process.
CONCLUSION
This exploratory field research has empirically investigated aspects of
the conceptual linkage between boundary spanning activity and the infor-
mation requirements of the BRP's constituent members. The BRP has
been examined as an influence agent and his base of power has been
shown to emerge from his potential ability to channel, if not control, the
flow of information into his firm. It can be inferred from these findings
that the purchasing agent's tendency to rely more heavily on expert power
supports the notion that the BRP's power resides primarily in his ability to
cope with uncertainty for his constituents. Moreover, these findings sug-
gest that the exercise of expert power is a means by which a BRP can better
sustain a continued dependency relationship thereby assuring himself an
influential voice in the decision making process. Despite the contextual
limitations of this study, this research has reaffirmed the importance of
the boundary role person in the acquisition, importation and processing of
environmental information.
REFERENCES
1. Adams, J. S. "The Structure and Dynamics of Behavior in Organizational Boundary Roles," in
M. Dunnette (Ed.) Handbook of Industrial and Organizational Psychology (Chicago: Rand
McNally, 1976), pp. 1175-1199.
2. Aldrich, H., and D. Herker. "Boundard Spanning Roles and Organizational Structure,"
Academy of Management Review, Vol. 2 (1977), 217-230.
3. Baldwin, D. A. "The Power of Positive Sanction," World Politics, Vol. 24 (1971), 19-38.
4. Cleland, D., and W. King. Systems Analysis and Project Management (New York: McGraw
Hill, 1968).
5. Crozier, M. The Bureaucratic Phenomenon (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1964).
1979 Spekman 117
6. Cyert, R., and J. March. A Behaviorat Theory of the Firm (Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice
Hall, 1964).
7. Downey, H. K., and J. Slocum. "Uncertainty: Measures, Research and Sources of Variation,"
Academy of Management Journal, Vol. 18 (1975), 562-578.
8. Duncan, R. B. "Characteristics of Organizational Environments and Perceived Environmental
Uncertainty," Administrative Science Quarterty, Vol. 17 (1972), 313-327.
9. Emerson, R. "Power Dependence Relations," American Sociological Review, Vol. 22 (1962),
31-41.
10. French, J., and B. Raven. "The Bases of Social Power," in D. Cartwright (Ed.) Studies in Social
Power (Ann Arbor, Mich.: Institute for Social Research, 1959), pp. 150-167.
11. Harsanyi, J. C. "Measurement of Social Power, Opportunity Costs, and the Theory of Two-
Person Bargaining Games," Behavioral Science, Vol. 7 (1962), 67-79.
12. Hickson, D., C. Hinings, C. Lee, and R. Schneck. "A Strategic Contingencies' Theory of In-
traorganizational Power," Administrative Science Quarterty, Vol. 16 (1971), 216-229.
13. Hunt, S., and J. Nevin. "Power in a Channel of Distribution: Sources and Consequences,"
Journal of Marketing Research, Vol. 11 (1974), 186-193.
14. Kahn, R., D. Wolfe, R. Quinn, and J. Snoek. Organizational Stress: Studies in Role Conflict
and Ambiguity (New York: Wiley, 1964).
15. Keller, R., and W. Holland. "Boundary Spanning Roles in Research and Development
Organizations," Academy of Management Journat, Vol. 18 (1975), 388-393.
16. Lawrence, P., and J. Lorsch. Organization and Environment (Homewood, 111.: Irwin, 1967).
17. Leifer, R., and A. Delbecq. "Organizational/Environmental Interchange: A Model of Bound-
ary Spanning Activity," Academy of Management Review, Vol. 3 (1978), 40-50.
18. Lusch, R. "Sources of Power: Their Impact on Intrachannel Conflict," Journal of Marketing
Research, Vol. 13 (1976), 382-390.
19. March, J. "An Introduction to the Theory and Measurement of Influence," American Political
Science Review, Vol. 49 (1955), 433-451.
20. Miles, R. "Role Requirements as Sources of Organizational Stress," Journat of Applied
Psychology, Vol. 61 (1976), 172-179.
21. Organ, D. "Linking Pins Between Organizations and Environment," Business Horizons, Vol.
14 (1971), 73-80.
22. Organ, D., and C. Greene. "The Boundary Relevance of the Project Manager's Job," R&D
Management, Vol. 3 (1972), 7-11.
23. Patchen, M. "Alternative Questionnaire Approaches to the Measurement of Influence in
Organizations," American Journat of Sociology, Vol. 69 (1963), 41-52.
24. Patchen, M. "The Locus and Basis of Influence on Organizational Decisions," Organizational
Behavior and Human Performance, Vol. 11 (1974), 195-211.
25. Pettigrew, A. "Information Control as a Source of Power," Sociology, Vol. 6 (1972), 187-204.
26. Raven, B. H. "The Comparative Analysis of Power and Power Preferences," in J. Tedeschi
(Ed.), Perspectives on Social Power (Chicago: Aldine, 1974).
27. Raven, B. H., and A. W. Kruglanski. "Conflict and Power," in P. Swingle (Ed.), The Structure
of Conflict (New York: Academic Press, 1970), pp. 69-109.
28. Robinson, P., C. Faris, and Y. Wind. Industrial Buying and Creative Marketing (Boston: Allyn
and Bacon, 1967).
29. Rosen, B. "Organization Boundary Roles: Information Gatekeeping and Transmission,"
(Presentation at the American Psychological Association, September 1976).
30. Rosen, B., and J. S. Adams. "Organizational Cover-Ups." Journat of Applied Social
Psychology, Vol. 4 (1974), 375-384.
31. Schein, V. "Individual Power and Political Behaviors in Organizations," Academy of Manage-
ment Review, Vol. 2 (1977), 64-72.
32. Spekman, R. "An Examination of Informal Decision-Making Units: Some Methodological Cau-
tions for Future Research," Proceedings of the Academy of Management (1977), pp. 213-218.
33. Strauss, G. "Tactics of Lateral Relationships," Administrative Science Quarterly, Vol. 9 (1962),
161-186.
34. Thompson, J. Organizations in Action (New York: McGraw Hill, 1967).
35. Tosi, H., R. Aldag, and R. Storey. "On the Measurement of the Environment: An Assessment
of the Lawrence and Lorsch Environmental Uncertainty Sub-Scale," Administrative Science
Quarterly, Vol. 18 (1973), 27-36.
36. Wall, J., and J. S. Adams. "Some Variables Affecting a Constituent's Evaluation of and
Behavior Toward a Boundary Role Occupant," Organizational Behavior and Human Perform-
ance, Vol. 11 (1974), 390-408.

