388 Academy of Management Journal June
Instrumentality were significantly correlated with P(I), whereas the varia-
bles of T and S were not. There is a need to test the model further in a real
world situation and to relate it to the actual degree of adoption of an
innovative strategy.
The semantic differential instrument used in this field study is both simple
and versatile to use. It provides a ready handle on the current status of
T, S, C, R, PN, and Ps in an organizational setting. A manager could use this
instrument to obtain feedback on how his group or department stands in
relation to a proposed innovation. Further, Model 1 of this study provides
clear conceptual guidance as to the interaction of the above variables and
their joint effect on the probability of adopting an innovative strategy. With
knowledge of the current status of the above key variables, the manager is
able to observe which variables are most unfavorable to the adoption of an
innovative strategy and to be able to consider changes accordingly.
REFERENCES
1. Fishbein, Martin and Bertram H. Raven. "The AB Scales: An Operational Definition
of Beliefs and Attitudes," Human Reiations, Vol. 15 (1962), 35-44.
2. March, James G., and Herbert A. Simon. Organizations (New York: Wiley, 1958).
3. Osgood, C. E., G. J. Suci, and P. C. Tannenbaum. The Measurement of Meaning (Ur-
bana: University of Illinois, 1957).
4. Pritchard, Robert D. 'The Influence of Valence, Instrumentality and Expectancy on
Effort and Performance," Journal of Applied Psychology, Vol. 57 (1973), 55-60.
5. Slevin, D. P. "The Innovation Boundary: A Specific Model and Some Empirical Re-
sults," Administrative Science Quarterly, Vol. 16 (1971), 515-531.
6. Slevin, D. P. "The Innovation Boundary: A Replication with Increased Costs," Admin-
istrative Science Quarterly, Vol. 18 (1973), 71-75.
BOUNDARY-SPANNING ROLES IN A RESEARCH AND
DEVELOPMENT ORGANIZATION: AN EMPIRICAL
INVESTIGATION i
ROBERT T. KELLER
WINFORD E. HOLLAND
University of Houston
Houston, Texas
The importance of boundary-spanning roles that serve to link organiza-
tions has been confirmed by research in a number of diverse organizations
(1, 2, 12, 16, 19, 20). These roles are vital to the effective monitoring of
the environment and to the transfer of technology and information across
boundaries.
1 This study was supported by a grant from the Office of Research and Sponsored Activi-
ties, University of Houston. Portions of this paper were presented at the 34th Academy of
Management Meeting, 1974.
Volume 18, Number 2 389
Considerable prior research (6, 9, 10, 13, 18), however, has found
boundary-spanning roles to have negative effects for their incumbents.
Since boundary spanners have role senders located in external organizations
as well as in their own organization, conflicting and misunderstood expecta-
tions for role performance often are sent to the boundary spanner. These
conditions have been found to result in strong and conflicting role pressures
and tensions for incumbents of boundary-spanning roles.
Marginality also has been found to be higher for those in boundary-span-
ning roles (7, 14, 23). Marginality is a self-orientation concerning two or
more groups of others: a person with high marginality would stand between
two or more groups with different value systems; a person with low margin-
ality would be associated v^dth a single group. Those high on marginality
have been found to be better able to deal objectively with two or more
groups and to be more satisfied and effective in boundary positions than
are nonmarginal individuals. Organ (8) has also hypothesized that effective
boundary spanners should have relatively high economic and political value
orientations, and relatively low aesthetic and religious value orientations.
The hypothesized value orientations are due to the pragmatism and
"hypocrisy" required of boundary spanners.
In the present study the Kahn et al. (6) theory of role dynamics was used
to generate the research hypotheses. It was hypothesized that boundary-
spanning activity (BSA) would be positively related to levels of role conflict
and ambiguity, and negatively related to levels of job satisfaction. It was
also hypothesized that BSA would be positively related to marginality and
to economic and political value orientations, and negatively related to
aesthetic and religious value orientations.
Method
The study was conducted in an applied science department of a large
government research and development organization. This department was
selected because of its external interfaces with more than 20 universities,
private contractors, and other governmental agencies, as well as its many
positions with primarily internal relationships. The sample of 51 profes-
sional employees (a 58 percent response rate) was similar to its population
in age, work experience, and education. All subjects had at least a bachelor's
degree, and most had a graduate degree. Anonymous questionnaires were
returned by mail directly to the researchers, and interviews were conducted
with many of the boundary spanners to corroborate the questionnaire data.
To measure the level of BSA, a four item scale was constructed based on
items successfully used in prior research (1, 2, 4). Each of the following
items had a five point scale of 0, 1-2, 3-4, 5-6, and more than 6:
(a) Indicate the total number of magazines, journals, and newspapers
which you regularly read, (b) During the last month, what was the
frequency with which you recommended specific information sources
390 Academy of Management Journal June
(e.g., journal article, knowledgeable colleague, report, magazine, etc.)
to a colleague? (c) During the last month, indicate the frequency with
which you have sought information/advice from members of other or-
ganizations outside (name of organization), (d) During the last month,
indicate the frequency with which members of organizations outside
(name of organization) have sought information/advice from you.
The BSA score was the sum of the four items. To validate the BSA scale,
top management of the department identified background characteristics of
personnel thought to be high on BSA. All those so identified scored in the
top third of the BSA scale distribution; moreover, a r-test between the BSA
scale means of those identified as boundary spanners and others was highly
significant (t = 4.07, p <.OO1). The reliability (Coefficient Alpha) of the
BSA scale was .73; the average score was 11.7, and the standard deviation
was 4.0.
Role conflict and ambiguity were measured by the two Rizzo et al. (15)
scales. The Job Description Index (17) was used to measure five dimensions
of job satisfaction: work itself, co-workers, supervision, pay, and opportun-
ities for promotion. The marginality measure was that used by ZiUer et al.
(23), and six personality related values were measured by the Study of
Values test (3).
Results
Tables 1 and 2 report the results of a correlational analysis. Contrary to
the hypotheses, BSA was negatively related to role ambiguity and positively
related to job satisfaction with co-workers, pay, and opportunities for pro-
motion. In addition, BSA was not related to marginality or any of the per-
sonality-related values; thus, these hypotheses were not supported either.
Partial correlations holding marginality constant also were computed to
eliminate effects introduced by both high and low marginality types being
attracted to boundary-spanning roles. These data, reported in Tables 3 and
4, do not provide support for. any of the research hjrpotheses.
TABLE 1
Correlations Between Boundary-Spanning Activity and Role and
Satisfaction Variables
Boundary-Spanning
ActivityRole
Conflict
.08Roie
Ambi-
guity
-.31*Work
.24Dimensions of Job
Co-
Workers
.41**Super-
vision
-.11Satisfaction
Pay
.28*Promo-
tions
.43**
* P < .05
*ò p < .01
1975 Volume 18. Number 2 391
TABLE 2
Correlations Between Boundary-Spanning Activity and
Marginality and Value Variables
Boundary-Spanning
ActivityMargin-
ality
.00Theo-
retical
.23Personality-Related Values
Eco- Aes- Politi-
nomic thetic Social cal
.09 .09 ù.01 ù.20
TABLE 3
Partial Correlations Between Boundary-Spanning Activity and
Role and Satisfaction Variables (Marginality Held Constant)
Boundary-Spanning
ActivityRole
Confiict
.25Role
Ambi-
guity
.20Dimensions of Job Satisfaction
Co- Super-
Work Workers vision Pay
.05 .65*** ù.36** .36**Reli-
gious
-.13
Promo-
tions
.38**
* P <.05
** p < .01
*** p < .001
TABLE 4
Partial Correlations Between Boundary-Spanning Activity and
Value Variables (Marginality Held Constant)
Boundary-Spanning
ActivityTheo-
retical
.34*Eco-
nomic
.15Personaiity-Related Values
Aes-
thetic Social
.06 .23Politi-
cal
-.28*Reli-
gious
-.32*
ò P < .05
Discussion and Implications
When compared with prior research (6, 9, 10, 13, 18, 23), the present
study indicates that boundary-spanning roles can differ substantially depend-
ing on the interorganizational relations and context. Where the organ-
izations which are spanned have goals that are in conflict, the boundary
spanner can experience strong role pressures and tensions due to the conflict-
ing expectations for perfonnance (e.g., a salesman or purchasing agent).
In the present study, however, the interorganizational goals are relatively
compatible. The research and development organization needs the tech-
392 Academy of Management Journal June
nology and information supplied by the universities and contractors to solve
its ambiguous problems. The universities and contractors, moreover, want
to publicize their research findings and applications. Boundary-spanning
roles here really serve to transfer technology and infonnation that are used
to solve problems and reduce ambiguities. And, as found by Pettigrew (11),
boundary spanners are able to use their access to information as a power
resource to obtain better pay, opportunities for promotion, and favorable
relations with co-workers.
With low degrees of role pressures and stress, it is understandable that
high marginality types or those with economic and political values are not
necessarily attracted to the boundary-spanning roles in the present study.
When marginality is held constant, the partial correlations between BSA
and role conflict and ambiguity are in the predicted direction. It thus ap-
pears that both the low degrees of role pressures and stress, and the attraction
of both high and low marginality types to these boundary-spanning roles
can explain the differences in results between this study and prior research.
The partial correlations also show BSA positively related to a theoretical
value orientation, and negatively related to political and religious values.
However, caution is urged in interpreting significance levels for the ipsatively
scored Study of Values test (5). In effect, with marginality held constant,
these boundary-spanning roles appear to attract those with a theoretical
value orientation who seek the discovery of "truth," rather than those with
a political value who are oriented toward power. These orientations are
consistent with the typical scientist in a research and development organi-
zation.
REFERENCES
1. Allen, T. J., and S. I. Cohen. "Information Flow in Research and Development Labora-
tories," Administrative Science Quarterly, Vol. 14 (1969), 12-19.
2. Allen, T. J., J. M. Piepmeier, and S. Cooney. "The International Technological Gate-
keeper," Technology Review, Vol. 75 (1971). 30-37.
3. Allport, G. W., P. E. Vemon, and G. Lindzey. Study of Values, 3rd ed., Test Booklet
and Manual (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1960).
4. Creighton, J. W., J. A. Jolly, and S. A. Denning. Enhancement of Research and Devel-
opment Output Utilization Efficiencies; Linker Control Methodology in the Technology
Transfer Process (Monterey, Calif.: Naval Postgraduate School, 1972).
5. Hicks, L. E. "Some Properties of Ipsative, Normative, and Force-Choice Normative
Measures," Psychological Bulletin, Vol. 74 (1970), 167-184.
6. Kahn, R. L., D. M. Wolfe, R. P. Quinn, J. D. Snoek, and R. A. Rosenthal. Organiza-
tional Stress: Studies in Role Confiict and Ambiguity (New York: Wiley, 1964).
7. Liddell, W. W. "Marginality and Integrative Decisions," Academy of Management
Journal, Vol. 16 (1973), 154-156.
8. Organ, D. W. "Linking Pins Between Organizations and Environment," Business Hori-
zons, Vol. 14 (1971), 73-80.
9. Organ, D. W. "Some Variables Affecting Boundary Role Behavior," Sociometry, Vol.
34 (1971), 524-537.
10. Organ, D. W., and C. N. Greene. "The Boundary Relevance of the Project Manager's
Job: Findings and Implications for R&D Management," R&D Management, Vol. 3
(1972), 7-11.
11. Pettigrew, A. M. "Information Control as a Power Resource," Sociology, Vol. 6 (1972),
187-204.
1975 Volume 18, Number 2393
12. Pruden, H. O. "Interorganizational Conflict, Linkage, and Exchange: A Study of Indus-
trial Salesmen," Academy of Management Journal, Vol. 12 (1969), 339-350.
13. Pruden, H. O., and R. M. Reese. "Interorganization Role-Set Relations and the Per-
formance and Satisfaction of Industrial Salesmen," Administrative Science Quarterly
Vol. 17 (1972), 601-609.
14. Pniden, H. O., and B. J. Stark. "Marginality Associated with Interorganizational Link-
T^^^^ ^'ò'^"'^''^'ty ^"^ Satisfaction," Academy of Management Journal, Vol.
15. Rizzo, J. R., R. J. House, and S. I. Lirtzman. "Role Conflict and Ambiguity in Complex
Organizations," Administrative Science Quarterly, Vol. 15 (1970), 150-163.
16. Rosenbloom, R. S., and F. W. Wolek. Technology and Information Transfer (Boston-
Harvard Business School Division of Research, 1970).
17. Smith, P. C, L. M. Kendall, and C. L. Hulin. The Measurement of Satisfaction in Work
and Retirement (Chicago: Rand McNally, 1969).
18. Wall, J. A., and J. S. Adams. "Some Variables Affecting a Constituent's Evaluation of
and Behavior Toward a Boundary Role Occupant," Organizational Behavior and Human
Performance, Vol. 11 (1974), 390-408.
19. Whitley, R., and P. Frost. 'Task Type and Information Transfer in a Government
Research Laboratory," Human Reiations. Vol. 25 (1973), 537-550.
20. Wren, D. A. "Interface and Interorganizational Coordination," Academy of Manage-ment Journal, Vol. 10 (1967), 69-Sl. I manage
21. Ziller, R. C. "Self-Other Orientation: Theory and Measures" (Unpublished paper
Universityof Oregon, 1968).
22. Ziller, R. C. The Social Self (Elmsford, N. Y.: Pergamon, 1973).
23. Ziller, R. C, B. J. Stark, and H. O. Pruden. "Marginality and Integrative Management
Positions, Academy of Management Journal. Vol. 12 (1969), 487-495.
STATISTICAL PROBLEMS OF CONTINGENCY MODELS
IN ORGANIZATIONAL BEHAVIORS
ABRAHAM K. KORMAN
ROBERT TANOESKY
Baruch CoUege
City University of New York
New York, New York
Interest in the conditions under which the relationship between supervisor
and subordinate results in effective work behavior has stimulated the de-
velopment of a number of leadership theories. Although a number of the
theories have achieved some success in accounting for these behaviors,
relatively few have dealt with the coordinate question concerning the
degree to which theoretical findings lend themselves to practical application
by management. In this paper some of the methodological and statistical
problems of contingency theories of leadership are examined from both
of these perspectives.
.^ ^iS7!lV!? PP*' ^^^ presented at the Midwestern Academy of Manage-
n I'h t. ^""l?^ ""* ^'ò^^^^"? '░ ░'"- "^"'^ P░░^y ░f *e University of Illinois and

