r Academy of Management Journal
2015, Vol. 58, No. 5, 1476û1494.
http://dx.doi.org/10.5465/amj.2013.0303
LEADERSHIP OVER-EMERGENCE IN SELF-MANAGING
TEAMS: THE ROLE OF GENDER AND COUNTERVAILING
BIASES
KLODIANA LANAJ
University of Florida
JOHN R. HOLLENBECK
Michigan State University
We examine leadership over-emergence, defined as instances when the level of oneÆs
leadership emergence is higher than the level of oneÆs leadership effectiveness, in
a sample of intact self-managing teams who worked together for a period of seven
months. We draw from Gender Role Theory and Expectancy Violation Theory to ex-
amine the role of gender in predicting leadership over-emergence. Building on argu-
ments from Gender Role Theory, we find that all else equal, men over-emerge as leaders.
However, Expectancy Violation Theory suggests that women are likely to benefit from
a countervailing bias. Specifically, women are attributed with higher levels of leader-
ship emergence than men when they engage in agentic leadership behaviorsùeven if the
level of the behaviors exhibited by men is exactly the same. Because the impact of these
behaviors on leadership effectiveness is not contingent on gender, however, women who
engage in more task behaviors and boundary spanning behaviors in self-managing
teams also over-emerge as leaders. We discuss the implications of this study for Gender
Role Theory and Expectancy Violation Theory, along with practical implications for
managing the problem of leadership over-emergence in work groups.
Self-managing teams are popular structures that
enable organizations to remain competitive and to
adapt to dynamic business environments (Druskat &
Wheeler, 2003; Ilgen, Hollenbeck, Johnson & Jundt,
2005; Roberson & Williamson, 2012; Stewart &
Manz, 1995). Typically, these teams have no orga-
nizationally assigned leaders, but instead, leaders
emerge informally (Neubert & Taggar, 2004; Taggar,
Hackett, & Saha, 1999). Because emergent leaders
play an important role in self-managing teams,
much attention has been devoted to identifying in-
dividual characteristics and behaviors associated
with leader emergence (Eagly & Karau, 1991; Ensari,
Riggio, Christian, & Carslaw, 2011; Judge, Bono,
Ilies, & Gerhardt, 2002).
As one might expect, much of the focus devoted to
leadership emergence has been toward leadership
development with the expressed intent of helping
individuals emerge as leaders (Yost & Plunkett,
2009). Indeed, the presumption characterizing al-
most all of this research is that if one could emerge as
a leader, he or she should emerge as a leader (e.g.,
Zhang, Waldman, & Wang, 2012). In some cases, this
presumption is valid, in the sense that certain traits
like intelligence and self-efficacy are associated at
roughly equal levels with leadership emergence and
leadership effectiveness (Foti & Hauenstein, 2007).
However, in other cases, factors predicting leader-
ship emergence differ from those predicting leader-
ship effectiveness, and a critical implication of this
empirical fact is that the person who emerges as
a leader may wind up being ineffective in that role.
For example, meta-analytic evidence suggests
that the correlation between extraversion and lead-
ership emergence is higher than the correlation be-
tween extraversion and leadership effectiveness
(Judge et al., 2002). This means that the likelihood
that a highly extraverted individual will emerge as
the leader is actually greater than the likelihood that
that person will be successful as a leader. Formally,
we define leadership over-emergence as cases when
an individualÆs leadership emergence (expressed in
descriptive terms), is actually higher than that
individualÆs leadership effectiveness (expressed in
We are thankful for our associate editor Ray Sparrowe
and three anonymous reviewers whose helpful comments
and suggestions improved this work. We are also grateful
to Joel Koopman and Mo Wang for their useful insights
during the development of this manuscript.
1476
Copyright of the Academy of Management, all rights reserved. Contents may not be copied, emailed, posted to a listserv, or otherwise transmitted without the copyright holderÆs express
written permission. Users may print, download, or email articles for individual use only.
normative terms). Recognition of this phenomenon
means that in some instances, the wrong person
might emerge as a leader of a group or the right
person may fail to emerge as a leader. Indeed, we
believe that inappropriate leadership emergence is
an important, but overlooked phenomenon in the
organizational literature.
One particularly important characteristic that
may be related to leadership over-emergence is
gender. EaglyÆs (1987) Gender Role Theory1 suggests
that due to gender-specific societal role and behav-
ioral expectations, men are expected to possess
agentic qualities (e.g., assertiveness, confidence,
and independence) and to engage in behaviors that
are congruent with a leader role. Women, on the
other hand, are expected to possess communal
qualities (helpfulness, nurturance, kindness) and to
engage in behaviors that are incongruent with
a leader role (Eagly & Karau, 2002). The impact of
gender on leadership emergence, however, tends to
be greater than the impact of gender on leadership
effectiveness (e.g., DeRue, Nahrgang, Wellman, &
Humphrey, 2011; Eagly, Karau, & Makhijani, 1995),
suggesting a bias against women that sets the stage
for over-emergence of male leaders.
Although early empirical evaluations of Gender
Role Theory posited that agentic behaviors may
help women overcome gender bias (Eagly & Karau,
1991; Rudman & Glick, 1999), later applications of
the theory downplayed this possibility and warned
that women who perform agentic behaviors may
experience backlash and be penalized in terms of
career prospects (Carli, 2010; Heilman, Wallen,
Fuchs, & Tamkins, 2004). The evidence for backlash
against agentic women, however, suggests that the
context wherein these behaviors are enacted matters
(e.g., Heilman, 2012), and that women who perform
agentic behaviors in self-managing teams may incur
little cost. Instead, Expectancy Violation Theory
(Jussim, Coleman, & Lerch, 1987) predicts that when
women engage in positive behaviors that are pro-
totypical leader behaviors, but atypical for the gen-
der stereotype, they are likely to be evaluated more
positively than men who engage in the exact same
behaviors. Thus, Expectancy Violation Theory pro-
poses a countervailing perceptual bias that works in
favor of women who perform agentic behaviors in
self-managing teams. However, since there is no
evidence that the relationship between engaging in
leader behaviors and leadership effectiveness is
contingent on gender, this sets up the potential for
leadership over-emergence for these women.
The purpose of this study is to draw from Gender
Role Theory (Eagly, 1987) and Expectancy Viola-
tion Theory (Jussim et al., 1987) to examine the
role of gender with respect to leadership emer-
gence, leadership effectiveness, and leadership
over-emergence. Both theories help generate prop-
ositions regarding how gender triggers biases when
it comes to perceptions of leadership emergence
and the potential for leadership over-emergence in
self-managing teams. Self-managing teams repre-
sent an important boundary condition with regards
to when either theory offers testable predictions for
leadership over-emergence. Specifically, Gender
Role Theory speaks more directly to why gender is
associated with bias and over-emergence in self-
managing teams, whereas Expectancy Violation
Theory speaks more directly to how behaviors per-
formed by both men and women in self-managing
teams carry individuating information likely to in-
fluence gender bias and over-emergence.
We propose that, all else equal, men will over-
emerge as leaders in self-managing teams due to the
effect of gender bias articulated by Gender Role
Theory. On the other hand, women who engage in
team-relevant agentic behaviors will over-emerge as
leaders relative to men enacting the exact same be-
haviors due to the alternative gender bias articu-
lated by Expectancy Violation Theory. The relative
impact of these countervailing biases will be em-
pirically documented and leveraged to help achieve
a more refined understanding of the role of gender
with respect to perceptions of leadership emer-
gence, leadership effectiveness, and leadership over-
emergence in self-managing teams.
THEORETICAL DEVELOPMENT AND
HYPOTHESES
We draw from Gender Role Theory (Eagly 1987;
Eagly & Karau, 1991) to posit that men over-emerge
as leaders in self-managing teams because this the-
ory predicts that men are viewed as more appro-
priate for leadership positions. Furthermore, we
draw from Expectancy Violation Theory (Jussim
et al., 1987) and recent developments in Gender
Role Theory to argue that women who perform
agentic behaviors (task and boundary spanning
1 Gender role theory (Eagly & Karau, 1991) is also
known as Social Role Theory in the literature (Eagly,
1987; Eagly & Karau, 2002). We refer to it as Gender Role
Theory in this manuscript to be consistent with work by
Eagly and Karau (1991) on gender and leadership emer-
gence in self-managing teams.
2015
1477
Lanaj and Hollenbeck
behaviors) and men who perform social behaviors
will trigger biases that work in their favor such that
they will over-emerge as leaders in self-managing
teams.
It is important to note that Gender Role Theory
and Expectancy Violation Theory have two key el-
ements in common. First, both theories describe
perceptual biases. The expectancy violation effect is
also a perceptual bias, in the sense that if a woman
engages in the same level of agentic behavior as
a man, the woman will get more perceptual credit
for it when it comes to emergence (e.g., Anderson,
Lievens, van Dam, & Born, 2006). Thus, although
the perceptual bias triggered by counter-stereotypical
behavior and described by Expectancy Violation
Theory works in a countervailing direction relative
to gender bias articulated by Gender Role Theoryùit
is still a bias.
Second, neither theory recognizes the potential
for leadership over-emergence due to gender bias
and the problem this poses for both genders. More
specifically, neither Gender Role Theory nor Ex-
pectancy Violation Theory assert that the effect of
any leader behavior (task, boundary, or social) on
team outcomes is contingent upon gender (and in-
deed there is no evidence to support this assertion).
Thus, any perceptual bias that promotes differential
leadership emergence but not differential leadership
effectiveness attributable to gender could promote
over-emergence. We examine these possibilities in
a sample of self-managing teams where team mem-
bers observed and rated each-otherÆs behaviors over
several months.
Gender and Leadership Over-Emergence:
Predictions by Gender Role Theory
Gender Role Theory (Eagly 1987; Eagly & Karau,
1991) proposes that gender creates shared social
role expectations of how men and women ought to
behave that affect peopleÆs perceptions in the
workplace. This is because gender roles represent
a collection of descriptive and injunctive expecta-
tions about women and men (Eagly & Karau, 2002).
For example, ômen are considered more leader-like,
intellectual, analytical, able to think abstractly, and
able to solve problems, whereas women are consid-
ered kinder, warmer, more expressive, more sup-
portive, and gentlerö (Carli, 2010: 343). According to
this theory, gender automatically activates stereo-
typical expectations that favor men over women for
leadership positions.
Since empirical evidence suggests that women
and men differ little in their leadership effectiveness
ratings (DeRue et al., 2011), this tendency for men to
be perceived as more appropriate for leadership
positions relative to women is a clear subjective
gender bias (Eagly & Carli, 2007; Koenig, Eagly,
Mitchell, & Ristikari, 2011). This bias may be over-
come when leaders are formally selected by the
organization via standardized, objective, and vali-
dated procedures that may be used in conjunction
with
diversity
initiatives.
However,
in
self-
managing teams, where leaders are not formally
selected via professionally validated processes, but
rather emerge informally based upon the subjective
perceptions of team members, the role of gender
bias becomes more salient (Eagly & Karau, 1991;
Hall, Workman, & Marchioro, 1998; Neubert &
Taggar, 2004).
Leadership emergence is defined as ôbeing per-
ceived as leaderlikeö (Kaiser, Hogan, & Craig, 2008:
97) and measures of emergence tend to focus on
descriptive terms related to a personÆs influence and
dominance in a group setting. Leadership effec-
tiveness, on the other hand, is defined as ôothersÆ
judgment of a personÆs performance as a leaderö
(Kaiser et al., 2008: 98) and measures of effective-
ness focus on normative terms related to whether
someoneÆs performance as a leader is good versus
bad. Leadership emergence and leadership effective-
ness are both ôperceptual categories of leadershipö
where emergence captures descriptive perceptions
that a team member ôstands outö in terms of influ-
ence, whereas effectiveness captures normative
perceptions of ôapprovalö for oneÆs performance as
a leader (Kaiser et al., 2008: 98). Research examining
the impact of gender on leadership emergence has
not examined its joint effects on leadership ef-
fectiveness. This oversight is puzzling given that
emergence and effectiveness are closely intertwined
socially constructed phenomena. Because leader-
ship emergence and effectiveness focus on charac-
teristics of the individual being rated, they are both
subject to perceptual biases (Kaiser et al., 2008);
however, gender ought to influence perceptions of
leader emergence more strongly than perceptions of
leader effectiveness.
A major reason why gender is likely to have a big-
ger impact on perceptions of leadership emergence
relative to perceptions of leadership effectiveness
can be traced to information processing differences
associated with the two inferences. For instance, in
a leadership context, socio-demographic gender auto-
matically triggers stereotypes and attributions that
1478
October
Academy of Management Journal
influence perceptions of leadership emergence (leaders
are men, Ayman & Korabik, 2010; Hall et al., 1998;
Scott & Brown, 2006). Perceptions of leadership
emergence are largely driven by recognition-based
priming that is heavily influenced by surface-level
individual differences such as gender that operate at
relatively low levels of awareness (e.g., Ayman &
Korabik, 2010; Carton & Rosette, 2011; Hall et al.,
1998).
Leader effectiveness, on the other hand, requires
more deliberate, conscious information processing
effort that relies at least partially on external feed-
back from the environment regarding the level of the
teamÆs success (or failure), as well as attributions for
that success (or failure). In most cases, information
about team performance is relatively unambiguous,
and most teams receive feedback about their per-
formance from external constituents on a regular
basis (e.g., external management, other units in the
organization, clients).
Indeed, the most common conceptualization and
measurement of leader effectiveness is the extent to
which ôthe leaderÆs organizational unit performs its
task successfully and attains its goalsö (Yukl, 2006:
10) and effectiveness is often rated in terms of the
leaderÆs contribution to ôprofit growth, market
share, and sales increaseö (Manz & Sims, 1987: 110).
Thus, to some degree, ratings of leader effectiveness
are influenced by objective indicators of perfor-
mance of the group or of the unit. Consequentially,
the impact of gender on perceptions of effectiveness
should be weaker than its corresponding influence
on emergence because stereotype-based perceptions
tend to be weaker in the presence of such diagnostic
information (Kunda & Thagard, 1996).
Illustrating this point, a comprehensive meta-
analysis on personality and leadership emergence
and leadership effectiveness conducted by Judge
and colleagues (2002) indicated that several per-
sonality traits are more strongly related to leader-
ship emergence perceptions than to leadership
effectiveness perceptions. Thus, whereas easily ob-
servable individual differences such as gender may
give rise to automatic and biased perceptions of
leader emergence, these same traits are likely to
have less impact on more controlled and evidence-
based perceptions of leadership effectiveness. Con-
sistent with these arguments, we predict that men
will over-emerge as leaders because the effect of
gender on leadership emergence perceptions is
stronger than the effect of gender on leadership ef-
fectiveness perceptions. Hence, we hypothesize the
following:
Hypothesis 1. Men over-emerge as leaders to
a larger extent relative to women in self-managing
teams.
Self-Managing Teams as Context for Leadership
Over-Emergence
From a behavioral perspective, as StogdillÆs (1948:
66) noted, ôLeadership implies activity, movement,
getting work doneö and Katz and Kahn (1978) iden-
tified three main categories of leader behavior that
contribute to group performance: task direction, psy-
chological supportiveness, and boundary spanning
behaviors. Building on this earlier work, Mumford
and his colleagues (Mumford, Campion, & Morgeson,
2006; Mumford, Van Iddekinge, Morgeson, &
Campion, 2008) developed a typology of team-
relevant behaviors that they collapsed into three
larger categories of task, boundary spanning, and
social behaviors.
Task behaviors refer to activities that contribute to
the teamÆs main responsibilities such as completing
team-relevant tasks. Boundary spanning behaviors
consist of coordination and consultation with out-
side constituents aiming to procure resources that
facilitate team performance. Social behaviors rep-
resent interpersonal behaviors that maintain the
social climate of the team, such as paying attention
to othersÆ feelings. All three types of leader behav-
iors contribute to team performance because they
facilitate goal accomplishment (Hawkins, 1995;
Galanes, 2003; Morgeson, DeRue, & Karam, 2010;
Morris & Hackman, 1969).
When viewed from the perspective of Gender
Role Theory, task and boundary spanning behaviors
have agentic qualities because of their assertive and
take-charge nature (e.g., Anderson et al., 2006;
Burke et al., 2006). Task behaviors are perceived as
masculine and agentic because they imply asser-
tiveness and ability to lead (Berdahl, 1996; Eagly &
Karau, 1991; Wood & Karten, 1986). Boundary
spanning behaviors are task-focused and agentic
because they are ômore highly related to the leaderÆs
role as a director than as a facilitatorö (Burke et al.,
2006: 292). Social behaviors, on the other hand,
have communal qualities because of their helpful
and sensitive nature (e.g., Scott & Brown, 2006).
Thus, whereas task and boundary behaviors are
agentic because they are task-focused and in-
strumental in nature, social behaviors are commu-
nal
because
they
facilitate
and
support
the
psychological context of the team. Based upon this
distinction, one might predict that women could
2015
1479
Lanaj and Hollenbeck
overcome gender bias by engaging in assertive and
take charge agentic behaviors.
Indeed, early applications of Gender Role Theory
seemed to suggest just that. For example, meta-
analytical examinations of gender and leadership
emergence suggested that compared to men, women
emerged as leaders to a lesser extent and performed
fewer agentic behaviors in leaderless groups (Eagly
& Karau, 1991). The authors stated that the findings
ômight be taken to imply that the best way for
women to achieve leadership is to emulate male
behaviorö (705). Similarly, Rudman and Glick
(1999: 1009) who studied agentic women concluded
that ômatching men on agency is necessary for
women to counteract perceptions that they are in-
sufficiently qualified for high status jobs.ö
Later developments of Gender Role Theory,
however, cautioned that agentic behaviors may re-
sult in backlash for women (Eagly & Carli, 2007). For
example, Eagly and Karau (2002) stated that: ôIn
general, the competent task contributions of women
are more likely to be ignored or to evoke negative
reactions than those of menö (p. 584). That is, on one
hand, women are perceived as more communal and
less agentic than men, and while this view is con-
sistent with their gender role as women, it is in-
congruent with a leader role. On the other hand,
when women display agentic behaviors that are
consistent with a leader role, they are perceived as
presumptuous
because
such
behaviors
are
in-
congruent with their gender role (Koenig et al.,
2011; Livingston, Rosette, & Washington, 2012).
Thus, women who try to assume a leadership role
by engaging in agentic behaviors may be penalized
because they are presumed to lack legitimacy for
leadership positions (Carli, 2010).
Empirical evidence on whether agentic behaviors
help or hurt women are mixed suggesting that the
context wherein these behaviors are enacted matters
(e.g., Heilman, 2012). For example, some studies show
that women who perform agentic behaviors experi-
ence backlash along communal dimensions and op-
portunities for organizational rewards (e.g., Heilman
et al., 2004; Rudman, 1998; Rudman & Glick, 1999).
Other studies show that women suffer backlash for
agentic behaviors only in the presence of ambiguity
about their contribution to group tasks (e.g., Heilman
& Haynes, 2005). Finally, a third set of studies show
that women actually benefit from agentic behaviors
(e.g., Anderson et al., 2006; Post, DiTomaso, Lowe,
Ferris, & Cordero, 2009; Rosette & Tost, 2010).
These findings underscore the importance of the
contextual factors associated with the nature of the
team that is being led. Although agentic behaviors
may result in backlash when enacted by women in
some settings, this is less likely to happen in the
context of self-managing teams. Specifically, self-
managing teams are interdependent groups where
members evaluate each otherÆs contributions to the
team frequently and carefully (Barker, 1993). Prior
research suggests that the presence of such di-
agnostic information about individual performance
reduces backlash against agentic women (Heilman
& Haynes, 2005; Rosette & Tost, 2010).
Furthermore, infrequent stereotype-inconsistent
information (e.g., women performing agentic behav-
iors) may be disregarded and dismissed as a fluke
in short term interactions where there is little at
stake. On the other hand, persistent stereotype
inconsistent behavior enacted by women in self-
managing teams, which typically interact over lon-
ger periods of time on consequential tasks, may
make expectancy violations more salient for other
team members (e.g., Fiske & Taylor, 2013). Thus,
whereas backlash against agentic women may occur
in more short-term teams working on tasks of mar-
ginal significance, this may be less likely to take
place in long-term self-managing teams where each
team member has a critical stake in the teamÆs
outcomes.
Indeed, Expectancy Violation Theory would suggest
that performance of task and boundary spanning be-
haviors may even benefit women in self-managing
teams. According to this theory, when individuals
engage in positive stereotype-defying behaviors, they
may often get more perceptual credit for those be-
haviors relative to individuals for whom these behav-
iors are stereotype confirming (e.g., Jussim et al., 1987).
Leadership Behaviors and Leadership Over-
Emergence: Predictions by Expectancy Violation
Theory
Expectancy Violation Theory suggests that indi-
vidual qualities and behaviors that run counter to
stereotype-based expectations are evaluated even
more extremely in the direction of the expectancy
violation (Jussim et al., 1987). A large body of re-
search has tested predictions of Expectancy Viola-
tion Theory with regards to race, ethnicity, and
gender stereotypes (Anderson et al., 2006; Avery,
McKay, Wilson, & Tonidandel, 2007; Bettencourt,
Dill, Greathouse, Charlton, & Mulholland, 1997;
Jackson, Sullivan, & Hodge, 1993; Jussim et al., 1987).
Overall, this work indicates that positive expectancy-
disconfirming behaviors attract perceptual attention
1480
October
Academy of Management Journal
from others (Stangor & McMillan, 1992) and con-
tribute disproportionately to evaluations of actors.
Thus, according to Expectancy Violation Theory,
individuals who perform positive behaviors not
expected of them based upon stereotypes will be
evaluated even more positively than others who
perform similar behaviors but who are expected to
do so (Jussim et al., 1987). Viewed from the per-
spective of Expectancy Violation Theory, women
who perform agentic behaviors ought to be rated
more positively than men who perform the exact
same behaviors. These expectations parallel find-
ings that continued exposure to female leaders re-
duces gender bias (Dasgupta & Asgari, 2004; Duehr
& Bono, 2006), and arguments that individuating
information counters category-based biases (Fiske,
Lin, & Neuberg, 1999; Fiske & Neuberg, 1990).
Consistent with arguments by Expectancy Viola-
tion theory, several studies suggest that women can
benefit from agentic behaviors in some instances.
For example, Heilman and Haynes (2005) found that
bias against women in leadership roles was miti-
gated when observers were provided with in-
formation that women contributed uniquely and
effectively to work team tasks. Similarly, Post and
coauthors (2008) found that women who were per-
ceived to be innovative were rated as more pro-
motable by their mangers than men who were
perceived to be innovative. The women in these
studies performed agentic behaviors that benefited
the group.
Recent developments in Gender Role Theory suggest
that women who perform other-advocating agentic
behavior do not experience backlash (Amanatullah &
Morris, 2010; Amanatullah & Tinsley, 2013). Thus,
women who engage in agentic behaviors that aim
to benefit the groupùsuch as task and boundary
behaviors enacted in self-managing teamsùought to
be evaluated even more positively than men who
perform these behaviors. This occurs because these
women experience little backlash from performance
of team-relevant agentic behaviors as per Gender
Role Theory, and because they are viewed as more
leaderlike than equivalent men as per Expectancy
Violation Theory.
Furthermore, agentic behaviors impact percep-
tions of emergence more strongly because agentic
behaviors are more important for leadership emer-
gence than communal behaviors (Carli, 2010; Eagly
& Karau, 1991). For example, Carli (2010) stated that
leadership emergence is ômore often associated
with agentic behavior, such as task contributions,
than with communal behaviorö (p.341). On the other
hand, theory and empirical evidence show that
agentic and communal behaviors are both important
for leadership effectiveness (DeRue et al., 2011).
Given that agency is important for leadership
emergence and that women receive more perceptual
credit for team-relevant agentic behaviors, women
who engage in these behaviors in self-managing
teams ought to over-emerge as leaders to a larger
extent than men who perform these same behaviors.
Consistent these arguments, we propose that
due to their agentic nature, task and boundary
spanning behaviors will lead to higher subjective
ratings of leadership emergence for women rela-
tive to men who engage in the same level of such
behaviors. In addition, we expect that the impact
of agentic behaviors will be stronger on womenÆs
ratings of leadership emergence than ratings of
effectiveness, thus triggering over-emergence in
self-managing teams. Consequentially, we hypothe-
size the following:
Hypothesis 2. Women who engage in task-related
behaviors over-emerge as leaders to a larger ex-
tent relative to men who engage in task-related
behaviors.
Hypothesis 3. Women who engage in boundary
spanning behaviors over-emerge as leaders to
a larger extent relative to men who engage in
boundary spanning behaviors.
In contrast to task-related and boundary spanning
behaviors which are agentic in nature, social be-
haviors are communal and expected of women
(Burke et al., 2006; Eagly & Karau, 1991). Hence,
women who engage in communal behaviors are not
violating gender expectations and should not ex-
perience any countervailing perceptual bias that
works in their favor. On the other hand, men who
perform a high frequency of social behaviors engage
in gender incongruent behaviors (Kulik & Olekalns,
2012). MenÆs emergence as leaders ought to be ac-
centuated when they engage in social behaviors
because these behaviors are not expected of them.
Lending support to this expectation, Heilman and
Chen (2005) found that altruistic citizenship be-
havior û a behavior stereotypically associated with
the female gender roleùresulted in more favorable
reactions when performed by men than women. For
these reasons, we predict that men who perform
more social behaviors will over-emerge as leaders to
a larger extent than women, thus testing the ôgen-
der- neutralö nature of this process. Hence:
2015
1481
Lanaj and Hollenbeck
Hypothesis 4. Men who engage in social behav-
iors over-emerge as leaders to a larger extent rel-
ative to women who engage in social behaviors.
METHODS
Participants
The sample for this study consisted of 181 students
enrolled in a full time MasterÆs of Business Admin-
istration (MBA) program at a large research university
in the United States. Students were assigned to 5-
person self-managing teams and they remained in
these teams for their entire first year in the MBA
program. Because team projects contributed consid-
erably to course grades, teams were composed to be
comparable across a number of demographic data
likely to contribute to team performance (e.g., age,
gender composition, MBA concentration, work ex-
perience, undergraduate major). Of the 181 students,
130 (71.8%) were men and 51 (28.2%) were women.
There was at least one woman per team (mean 5 1.4
women per team). This gender composition is repre-
sentative of MBA programs in the country (Kelan &
Jones, 2010).The average age of the sample was 27.6
(SD 5 3.7), and the average work experience was
51 months (SD 5 34.7).
Procedure
This was a longitudinal study where data were
collected at three different time periods. First, par-
ticipants completed a one-time survey approximately
two months before starting the MBA program and
before they met their team members. This sur-
vey measured personal data and individual traits
(extraversion, agreeableness, and conscientiousness).
Second, after approximately 6 weeks of frequent in-
teractions with their team members, participants
rated each of their team members on task, boundary
spanning, and social behaviors. Finally, approxi-
mately four months after the second wave, partici-
pants rated each of their team members on leadership
emergence and leadership effectiveness. Thus, with
the exception of personal data and traits, all partici-
pant behaviors were rated by an average of four team-
members. During the surveying period, all students
took the same classes, had the same instructors, and
participated in the same class-related team activities.
Measures: Independent Variables
Gender. Gender was a dummy variable such that
women were coded 1 and men were coded 0.
Task-related Behaviors. We used 20 items de-
veloped by Mumford and coauthors (2006, 2008) to
measure task-related behaviors. Items tapped on task-
relevant behaviors such as planning and organizing
team tasks and sharing task knowledge with the
team. Each team-member rated all other team mem-
bers on these items by indicating the extent to which
they performed these behaviors. Example items are:
ôorganizes the teamÆs work to get important work
done on time,ö ôcoordinates the work done by others
so that things are done in the right order,ö ôshares
with the team any knowledge he/she has about the
work to be done.ö The response anchor was a 5-point
Likert scale where ô15 not at allö and ô5 5 to a very
great extent.ö The average internal consistency for
task behaviors was a 5 0.93 (computed as the aver-
age coefficient a across the four raters). The ICC(1) for
the task-related behaviors scale across raters was 5 0.36,
and ICC(2) was 5 0.69. We also computed rwg fol-
lowing procedures by James, Demaree, and Wolf
(1984) for multiple-item scales. Task behaviors had
an average rwg(J) 5 0.97. These three statistics
indicate that there was interrater agreement for
task-related behaviors. Therefore, following recom-
mendations regarding aggregation of perceptual vari-
ables in group settings (Bliese, 2000; James, 1982;
James et al., 1984), we computed an overall score of
task behaviors by aggregating across raters.
Boundary Spanning Behaviors. Boundary span-
ning behaviors were measured with 8 items de-
veloped by Mumford and coauthors (2006; 2008).
These items assessed the extent to which team
members coordinated with people outside the team
to acquire resources that would help team perfor-
mance. Similar to task behaviors, boundary span-
ning behaviors for each team member were rated by
all other team members. Example items are: ôgoes
outside the team to bring in new resources that help
the team work effectively,ö ôinteracts with people
outside the team to get special knowledge about the
work, project, or task,ö ôinteracts with people out-
side the team to present the team and its accom-
plishments in a favorable light.ö The response scale
ranged from 1 to 5, where ô15 not at allö and ô5 5 to
a very great extent.ö The average internal consis-
tency for boundary spanning behaviors was a 5 0.90.
The ICC(1) for boundary spanning behaviors was
0.12, ICC(2) 5 0.35, and average rwg(J) was 0.88.
Because of agreement among raters, we collapsed
ratings of boundary spanning behaviors into one
overall score for each team member.
Social Behaviors. We measured social behaviors
with 12 items by Mumford and coauthors (2006;
1482
October
Academy of Management Journal
2008). These items asked team members to rate each
of the other team members on the extent to which
they listened to the thoughts and personal feelings
of other team members and supported the work of
others on the team. Example items are ôlistens
carefully to the thoughts and feelings of others,ö
ôhelps settle conflict between team members,ö
ôsupports team members in their work.ö The re-
sponse format was a five-point scale (1 5 not at all;
5 5 to a very great extent). Coefficient a for social
behaviors was 0.93. ICC(1) was 0.28, ICC(2) 5 0.61,
and average rwg(J) 5 0.93 justifying aggregation of
social behavior ratings across raters.
Measures: Dependent Variables
Leadership Emergence. We used seven items to
measure leadership emergence adapted from Lord,
Foti, and De Vader (1984), Kent and Moss (1994),
and Taggar, Hackett, and Saha (1999). Team mem-
bers were asked to indicate the degree to which each
team member emerged as the leader via items that
were descriptive of whether they led or did not lead,
but were not normative in terms of whether that
leadership was effective or ineffective. Example
items asked if the individual ôexhibits leadership in
the team,ö ôassumes leadership in the team,ö ôin-
fluences the team,ö æinfluences team decisions,ö
ôleads the conversation in team.ö The response
scale for these items ranged from 1 to 5, where ô1 5
Almost Neverö and ô5 5 Almost Always.ö Average
internal consistency for leadership emergence across
all raters was a 5 0.95. ICC(1) was 0.42, ICC(2) 5
0.74, and average rwg(J) 5 0.90, justifying aggregation
of leadership emergence ratings across raters for each
team member.
Leadership Effectiveness. We measured leader-
ship effectiveness with 11 items adapted from
Giessner
and
van
Knippenberg,
(2008).
Team
members were asked to indicate the degree to which
various team members were effective as leaders
using normative language. Team members were
asked to rate the leadership effectiveness of each
team member using a response scale from 1 to 5,
where ô1 5 Strongly Disagreeö and ô5 5 Strongly
Agree.ö Example items asked if the individual ôis
a very good leader,ö ôis very effective,ö ôhelps our
group achieve success,ö ômakes good decisions,ö
ôteaches people how to improve.ö Internal consis-
tency for leadership effectiveness across raters was
a 5 0. 94. ICC(1) was 0.29, ICC(2) 5 0.62, and average
rwg(J) 5 0.95; therefore we aggregated leadership ef-
fectiveness across raters.
We conducted a set of confirmatory factor ana-
lyses to examine the factor structure of our leader-
ship measures. Because there are 58 items across
our 5 leadership measures, we followed prior re-
search and created four parcels of items for each
measure to allow for a favorable item to sample size
ratio (e.g., Bagozzi & Edwards, 1998). The five-factor
theoretical model where task behaviors, boundary
spanning behaviors, social behaviors, leadership
emergence,
and
leadership
effectiveness
items
loaded on their respective factors fit the data rela-
tively well: CFI 5 0.96, TLI 5 0.96; RMSEA 5 0.07;
x2 5 680.67, df 5 160, p , .01.
We compared this five-factor model to several
alternative models using x2 difference tests. x2 dif-
ference tests showed that the five-factor model fit
the data significantly better than a four factor model
combining leadership emergence and effectiveness
items into one overall factor (Dx2 5 819.69; df 5 4,
p , .01). Fit of this four factor model was CFI 5 0.91,
TLI 5 0.89, RMSEA 5 0.11, x2 5 1500.36; df 5 164.
The five-factor model also fit better than a four
factor model collapsing task behaviors and leader-
ship emergence items on one factor: CFI 5 0.77,
RMSEA 5 0.17, x2 5 3560.30, df 5 164; x2 differ-
ence test results were Dx25 2879.63; df 5 4, p , .01.
Finally, the five-factor model was also a better fit
to the data than a four factor model, which collapsed
task behaviors and boundary spanning items on the
same factor. The fit of this four factor model was
CFI 5 0.86, RMSEA 5 0.13, x2 5 2253.08, df 5 164;
x2 difference tests results were Dx25 1572.41; df 5 4,
p , .01. In their entirety, these tests support the
construct distinctiveness of our five leadership
measures.
Leadership Over-Emergence. Leadership over-
emergence was conceptualized as the relative effect
size difference that the independent variables had
on leadership emergence vs. leadership effective-
ness in multilevel multivariate analyses. In order to
prevent ôapples versus orangesö comparisons that
would confound the results associated with either
component of over-emergence, it was critical to
keep the timing and source for each of the two dif-
ferent components constant.
Measures: Control Variables
Although the primary focus of this study was on
gender, we controlled for extraversion, conscien-
tiousness, and agreeableness because prior research
has shown that these relate to both leadership
emergence and effectiveness (DeRue et al., 2011;
2015
1483
Lanaj and Hollenbeck
Ensari et al., 2011; Grant, Gino, & Hofmann, 2011;
Judge et al., 2002; Marinova, Moon, & Kamdar,
2013). Thus, any effects detected in this study for
gender cannot be attributed to potential personality
differences between the men and women in this
sample.
Agreeableness. Agreeableness was measured with
10 items from the International Personality Item Pool
(IPIP) (Goldberg, 1999). Participants indicated whether
the items tended to describe their general pattern of
behavior on a scale of 1 to 5, where represented ô1 5
very inaccuratelyö and ô5 5 very accuratelyö (e.g., I
sympathize with othersÆ feelingsö). Internal consis-
tency for agreeableness was a 5 0.81.
Conscientiousness. We measured conscientious-
ness also with 10 items from IPIP (Goldberg, 1999:
e.g., ôI am always preparedö). The response format
was on a five-point scale, same as agreeableness. In-
ternal consistency for conscientiousness was a 5 0.86.
Extraversion. Extraversion was assessed with 10
items from IPIP (Goldberg, 1999: e.g., ôI start con-
versationsö). The response format was on the same
five-point scale as for agreeableness and conscien-
tiousness and internal consistency was a 5 0.86.
RESULTS
Descriptive statistics, including means, standard
deviations, and intercorrelations for the focal vari-
ables are presented in Table 1. Because of the nested
nature of the data (team members nested within
teams), we tested our hypotheses via multilevel
multivariate analyses in Mplus 7.11 by utilizing the
ôType 5 Complexö cluster approach (Muth┤en &
Muth┤en, 1998/2012). Multivariate regressions are
appropriate given our research questions because
they test the effects of the independent variables on
the dependent variables while taking into account
their linear association (Tabachnick & Fidell, 2007).
Furthermore, multivariate regressions decompose
the effects of each independent variable on leader-
ship emergence vs. leadership effectiveness allow-
ing us to reach statistical conclusions about the
phenomenon of leadership over-emergence.
In line with Gender Role Theory, Hypothesis 1
stated that men over-emerge as leaders in self-
managing teams. Controlling for agreeableness, con-
scientiousness, and extraversion, the effect of gender
on perceptions of leadership emergence was sig-
nificant (B 5 2 0.24, p , .05) but the effect of gender
on leadership effectiveness perceptions was not
(B 5 2 0.06, n.s.) (Table 2). To ascertain whether
men over-emerged as leaders, we further estimated
the effect difference of gender on leadership emer-
gence vs. effectiveness in Mplus. Gender had a sig-
nificantly larger effect on leadership emergence
than on leadership effectiveness (B 5 2 0.17, p , .05),
supporting Hypothesis 1 that men over-emerge as
leaders in self-managing teams.
In supplementary tests of Hypothesis 1, we
found that the effect of gender on leadership over-
emergence remained significant when controlling
for boundary and social behaviors (whether we
controlled for these separately or together), but that
it became non-significant when task behaviors were
added to that regression (see Table 3 for the full
regression). Thus, the effect of gender on leadership
over-emergence may be due to real differences
in task behaviors that stem from social stereotypes
and expectations, or it may be due to gender bias
that is triggered when these agentic behaviors are
perceived.
TABLE 1
Descriptive Statistics and Inter-Correlations Among Variables
Variable
Mean
SD
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
1
Gender (1 5 Female)
0.28
0.45
2
Agreeableness
4.19
0.50
0.17*
0.81
3
Conscientiousness
3.89
0.66
20.13
0.34**
0.86
4
Extraversion
3.63
0.64
0.12
0.36**
0.16*
0.86
5
Task Behaviors
3.53
0.44
20.25**
20.03
0.06
0.06
0.93
6
Boundary Behaviors
3.00
0.44
0.09
0.06
0.03
0.17*
0.58**
0.90
7
Social Behaviors
3.68
0.48
0.05
0.08
0.00
0.04
0.53**
0.52**
0.93
8
Leadership Emergence
3.40
0.68
20.17*
0.00
0.12
0.11
0.72**
0.46**
0.43**
0.95
9
Leadership Effectiveness
3.76
0.50
20.07
0.05
0.09
0.04
0.59**
0.43**
0.65**
0.77**
0.94
Note: n 5 177û181; Reliabilities are shown in the diagonal.
* p , .05
** p , .01
1484
October
Academy of Management Journal
Expectancy Violation Theory (Jussim et al., 1987)
suggests that when women perform agentic behav-
iors not expected of them (e.g., task and boundary
spanning behaviors), they will be evaluated even
more positively than men who engage in the same
behaviors. Similarly, Gender Role Theory suggests
that group-oriented agentic behaviors result in less
backlash and may even benefit women (Amana-
tullah & Tinsley, 2013; Eagly & Karau, 2002). These
arguments give rise to an expectancy violation bias
that ought to work in favor of women who perform
agentic behaviors. Consequentially, Hypothesis 2
posited that women who engage in task-related be-
haviors will over-emerge as leaders because (a) the
effect of these behaviors on leadership emergence
perceptions for women is stronger relative to the
effect of these same behaviors for men, but (b) the
effect of these behaviors on leadership effectiveness
perceptions for women is not stronger relative to the
effect of these same behaviors for men.
In support of Hypothesis 2, we found that women
who performed task-related behaviors emerged as
leaders to a larger extent than men (B 5 0.37, p , .05)
but that there were no differences in leadership
effectiveness between men and women who per-
formed task behaviors (B 5 0.10 n.s.) (Table 4).
Figure 1 illustrates the multilevel multivariate in-
teraction effects.
Over-emergence occurred if the effect of task be-
haviors was stronger on leadership emergence vs.
effectiveness, and if this effect was stronger for
women vs. men. To further decompose these effects,
we ran multilevel multivariate multigroup (men vs.
women) analyses in Mplus (Muth┤en & Muth┤en,
1998/2012), constraining the two groups to be equal
across the control variables to facilitate compari-
sons. These analyses revealed that the impact of task
behaviors on leadership emergence for women was
B 5 1.27 (p , .01), and for men it was B 5 0.91 (p , .01).
Thus, the relationship between engaging in task-
related behaviors and perceptions of leadership
emergence was stronger for women relative to men
who engaged in the exact same behaviors and the
effect difference was B 5 0.36 (p , .05). On the other
hand, the effect of task behaviors on leadership ef-
fectiveness for women was B 5 0.48 (p , .05) and
for men it was B 5 0.37 (p , .05), but these effects
did not differ by gender (B 5 0.11, n.s.).
Hence, the over-emergence effect for women
who engaged in task-related behaviors was B 5 0.80
(p , .01) and the over-emergence effect for men who
engaged in task-related behaviors was B 5 0.54
(p , .01). Compared to men who engaged in task-related
TABLE 2
Multivariate Regression Estimates for Hypothesis 1: Effects
of Gender on Leadership Emergence and
Effectiveness
Variable
Leadership
Emergence
Leadership
Effectiveness
B
t-value
B
t-value
Agreeableness
20.07
20.68
0.03
0.36
Conscientiousness
0.10
0.94
0.05
0.76
Extraversion
0.14
1.66
0.02
0.31
Gender (1 5 Women)
20.24
22.18*
20.06
20.76
Note: Level 1 n 5 177; no. of clusters 5 37; unstandardized
coefficients are reported.
* p , .05
TABLE 3
Supplementary Tests of Hypothesis 1
Variable
Leadership
Emergence
Leadership
Effectiveness
B
t-value
B
t-value
Agreeableness
20.04
20.42
0.00
0.00
Conscientiousness
0.09
1.60
0.06
1.50
Extraversion
0.05
1.01
20.01
20.29
Task Behaviors
1.02
6.92**
0.40
4.50**
Boundary Behaviors
0.07
0.55
20.02
20.22
Social Behaviors
0.09
0.98
0.49
5.80**
Gender (1 5 Women)
20.02
20.23
0.01
0.13
Note: Level 1 n 5 177; no. of clusters 5 37; unstandardized
coefficients are reported.
** p , .01
TABLE 4
Multivariate Regression Estimates for Hypothesis 2: The
Interactive Effects of Gender and Task Behaviors
Variable
Leadership
Emergence
Leadership
Effectiveness
B
t-value
B
t-value
Agreeableness
20.06
20.67
20.01
20.08
Conscientiousness
0.09
1.85
0.06
1.59
Extraversion
0.05
0.95
20.01
20.31
Gender (1 5 Women)
0.02
0.28
0.02
0.34
Task Behaviors
0.91
5.90**
0.37
4.27**
Boundary Behaviors
0.03
0.28
20.03
20.31
Social Behaviors
0.11
1.32
0.50
6.00**
Task X Gender
0.37
2.55*
0.10
0.84
Note: Level 1 n 5 177; no. of clusters 5 37; unstandardized
coefficients reported.
* p , .05
** p , .01
2015
1485
Lanaj and Hollenbeck
behaviors, women who engaged in task-related be-
haviors over-emerged as leaders to a larger extent:
B 5 0.26 (p , .05). Thus, when men and women
both performed the same level of task related be-
haviors, women tended to over-emerge as leaders
more than men.
Hypothesis 3 predicted that women who engage
in more boundary spanning behaviors over-emerge
as leaders. In support of Hypothesis 3, we found that
women who performed boundary spanning behav-
iors emerged as leaders to a larger extent than men
(B 5 0.32, p , .05), and that there were no differ-
ences in leadership effectiveness between men and
women who performed boundary spanning behav-
iors (B 5 0.07, n.s.) (Table 5). Figure 2 illustrates the
pattern of these associations.
We decomposed the multivariate effects of
boundary spanning behaviors on leadership emer-
gence vs. effectiveness for women vs. men in Mplus
using multilevel multigroup analyses. The effect of
boundary spanning behaviors on emergence was
stronger for women vs. men (B 5 0.31, p 5 0.05),
whereas the impact of boundary spanning behaviors
on leadership effectiveness was not significantly
different for women vs. men (B 5 0.08, n.s.). The
over-emergence effect for women who engaged in
boundary spanning behaviors was B 5 0.24 (p , .05)
and for men it was B 5 0.00 (n.s.). Supporting Hy-
pothesis 2, women who performed boundary span-
ning behaviors over-emerged as leaders to a larger
extent than men who performed the exact same
behaviors and that effect was 0.24 (p , .05).
FIGURE 1
Effects of Task Behaviors on Leadership Over-Emergence for Men vs. Women
2
2.5
3
3.5
4
4.5
Leadership Effectiveness
Men
2
2.5
3
3.5
4
4.5
Leadership Emergence
Men
2
2.5
3
3.5
4
4.5
Leadership Effectiveness
Women
2
2.5
3
3.5
4
4.5
Leadership Emergence
Women
Low Task Behaviors
Low Task Behaviors
High Task Behaviors
High Task Behaviors
Low Task Behaviors
High Task Behaviors
Low Task Behaviors
High Task Behaviors
TABLE 5
Multivariate Regression Estimates for Hypothesis 3: The
Interactive Effects of Gender and Boundary Behaviors
Variable
Leadership
Emergence
Leadership
Effectiveness
B
t-value
B
t-value
Agreeableness
20.07
20.71
20.01
20.08
Conscientiousness
0.08
1.54
0.06
1.48
Extraversion
0.06
1.04
20.01
20.27
Gender (1 5 Women)
20.03
20.39
0.00
0.07
Task Behaviors
1.00
6.56**
0.40
4.49**
Boundary Behaviors
20.05
20.36
20.05
20.43
Social Behaviors
0.11
1.25
0.50
5.93**
Boundary X Gender
0.32
1.97*
0.07
0.67
Note: Level 1 n 5 177; no. of clusters 5 37; unstandardized
coefficients reported.
* p , .05
** p , .01
1486
October
Academy of Management Journal
Finally, Hypothesis 4 stated that men who per-
formed more social behaviors would over-emerge as
leaders compared to women û a test of the gender
neutrality
proposition
of
Expectancy
