0000 
Steven Lysonski and Arch G. 
While researchers have probed predictors of 
product managersÆ pe@ormance in consumer 
goods firms, few have looked at the per$ormance 
of the industrial product manager. in this article, 
Steven Lysonski and Arch Woodside use path 
analysis to examine causal models of industrial 
product managersÆ per$ormance during periods 
of rapid technological change. Key variables are 
analyzed. including the effects of environmental 
uncertainty, boundary spanning behavior, role 
pressures, role outcomes and two performance 
measures. A total of69 itrdustriul product man- 
agers from New Zealand Telecom completed u 
questionnaire that included both operational 
measures of the key variables and their overall 
job performance. The results suggest that most of 
the hypothesized relationships are supportable 
empirically. Perfiormance was hindered by envi- 
ronmental uncertainty, role conflict, role ambigu- 
ity, tension and dissatisfaction. The authors dis- 
cuss their studyÆs implications for improving the 
t ffectiveness of product management practices. 
Address correspondence to Arch G. Woodside, A. B. Freeman 
School of Business, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA 70118. 
0 1989 Elsevier Science Publishing Co., Inc. 
655 Avenue of the Americas, New York. NY 10010 Using the telecommunications industry in a case 
study, JeEinek [373 describes how technology can 
radically change the basis for competition. For 
the telecommunir=ations industry and many oth- 
ers Jelinek emphasizes that the ônew technol- 
ogyö based on semiconductors, versus the old 
technology based on electromechanics, results in 
the following strategic imperatives: 
custom tailored and individualized produc :s 
are not only feasible but economical; 
proliferating products and flexible rcspo~~ 
to customers means more finely tuned mar- 
ket segmentation and product positioning 
strategies; and 
as more competitors push the state-of-the-art 
technology and product design, competition 
will favor those who provide quality, relia 
ity and responsiveness; price alone wonÆt do 
it, nor will the technology. 
JelinekÆs 1984 observations were based on ner 
analysis of American Telephone and Telegraph 
and other US telecommunications businesses. By 
the late 1980s the strategic imperatives outlined 
by Jelinek occurred worldwide in market-based 
nations. Th: product proliferation of high quality 
electronic t Secommunications products coupled 
with customers more frequently demanding many 
product features, more speed and higher reliabil- 
ity has resulted in major reorganizations of mar- 
keting and related business activities within large 
teiecommunications companies. 
The marketing effectiveness following the reor- 
ganization response to the new technology and BIOGRMWICAL SYETCHES 
Stc\cn L \wvbLi 14 .\~~wa1e Profrt4wr at Marqurtte LÆntxerut? . 
~\t~iu,~~bee. \+æl\cansm Hz I N 4 former member of the bl.ddmg 
Facuk!, at the University of Canterbury. Christchurch. New Zealand. 
& the lÆnwer$ of Rhode Island at Kingston. He has completed 
www-ch on evaluating the cumpetul\e attractiveness of altematibe 
fbretgn \ asattlotr destination\. 
Arch G. Wwd&ie I* the Malcolm S. Woldenberp Proft?wr of 
Marketing of rhe A. B. Freeman Sshool of Bwincsh at Tulane 
lÆwenlt) . He IS Serw Editor of Adwnc t*.\ IFI Businw .4furkring. 
an annual \ olume sews OI origrnal re>earch reports and es3a! 5 on 
busmew-to-hwines?, marktmg toplo. He i* PreGdenr of ARC Con- 
sultant* Ins.. a firm specializing in research on planning and imple- 
menttRe msrketmg and product 4frafegie\. 
strategic imperatives by a national telecommu- 
nications enterprise. New Zealand Telecom. is 
reported in the present article. In a major effort to 
successfully introduce many high technology 
products in a marketplace that included aggres- 
sive competitors with many new products of their 
own. New Zealand Telecom (NZ Telecom) began 
by creating a new marketing organization. The 
product manager position product manager was 
central in the new marketing organization: before 
the marketing reorganization. the product man- 
ager position did not exist. The new product 
manager job description included the responsibil- 
ity for learning customer acceptance to new prod- 
uct designs. quickly learning and reporting prod- 
uct market introductions by competitors and 
directing the implementation of marketing 
strategies by the operating divisions of the firm. 
The study reported here is based on an in-depth 
survey of the activities and performance of these 
product managers at NZ Telecom. 
Success for industrial products may hinge on 
the performance of the product manager in coor- 
dinating the activities of others and in effectively 
managing the assigned product lines. Yet little is 
known about the position or the characteristics of 
individual industrial product managers [ l?] de- 
spite the increasing pol;Aarity of the industrial 
product management concept. Even thoubÆl a 
growing literature has developed on the role of 
the product manager in consumer goods indus- 
tries [ 14,X 49-5 11. researchers have not probed 
the many dimensions of the industrial product 
manager. No attempts seem to have been made to 
develop and test models of the antecedents of 
performance of industrial product management. S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
The purpose of this study is to develop valid 
causal models of the performance of the indus- 
trial product manager. 
The product manager in either the industrial or 
consumer setting functions as a communicator 
both inside and outside the firm. This boundary 
spanning role links the organization with a net- 
work of other organizations such as suppliers and 
buyers. In addition, this role includes coordinat- 
ing the efforts of multiple corporate departments 
to achieve product success. This communication 
role, however, may create stress and conflict for 
product managers, which ultimately can impair 
their performances. 
Although some research has examined the con- 
sumer product manager in terms of boundary 
spanning behavior [50], no comparable studies 
have looked at the industrial product manager. 
This article builds on the foundation laid by 
previous research on boundary role theory [ I,%] 
and provides a theoretical and empirical synthe- 
sis of some key issues related to the industrial 
product manager. 
The article is divided into four sections. The 
first reviews the published studies on industrial 
product management. The second presents the 
research model and hypotheses tested, while the 
third develops a methodology for testing the 
model and hypotheses. The last section focuses 
on the empirical findings and presents the conclu- 
sions and implications. 
Literature on Industrial Product Managers 
Only a few major studies have examined the 
industrial product manager and none of these has 
addressed performance, particularly in terms of 
the effects of environmental and behavioral di- 
mensions on performance. Such studies have 
established some differences between industrial 
and consumer product managers. Kelly and Hise 
[421, for example, found that industrial product 
managers were generally older and had more 
years of experience with the same product com- 
pared to product managers in consumer goods. 
Moreover, they found that in terms of role con- 
flict, role clarity and tension. the only difference 
was that consumer product managers reporte BOUNDARY ROLE SPANNING BEHAVIOR J ttt 
c 
managers with industrial goods responsibilities 
had greater levels of contact with sales reps, 
customers and managers in distribution. In an- 
other study using the case study approach, 
Petrini and Grub [63] found t at industrial prod- 
uct managers at Borg Warner and Curtis Wright 
had no control over pricing and no profit and loss 
responsibility. 
Two more recent studies on industrial product 
management find even greater differences be- 
tween consumer and industrial product managers 
than earlier reports. Cummings et al. [ 191 found 
that consumer product managers were active 
decision makers, unlike their industrial counter- 
parts who have less decision-making influence 
and instead function more as coordinators. They 
concluded that the industrial product manager 
differs significantly from the consumer product 
manager in terms of background characteristics 
and decision-making authority. Industrial prod- 
uct managers were significantly older, had more 
work experience and reached their position pri- 
marily from sales and some from engineering, 
unlike their consumer counterparts who were more likely to start as assistant product rnz nagers 
after obtaining 54.B.A.s. 
The other study by Eckles and Novotny [X] 
found that industrial product 
sponsibility for six or more prod 
Their major responsibilities inc 
profitability, physical product ch 
ing the productsÆ progress, product reengineer- 
ing, market entry, product conceptualization and 
any product deletions. Given such differences, 
research findings on consumer product managers 
may not be as applicable to the industrial setting. 
Hence, there is a need to focus explicitly on the 
industrial product manager. 
Variables and Hypotheses 
The relationships of several key behavioral vari- 
ables related to the product managerÆs perfor- 
mance were examined in the present study. The 
mode1 developed in Figure 1 is a causal one in 
which perceived environmental uncertainty, 
boundary spanning and role pressures of conflict 
and ambiguity were predictors of the product 
Figure 1. A camal model of the variables in the study. Perceived envuonmental uncer- 
tainty, boundary spanning, role percepthns of conflict and ambiguity, role outcomes and 
perceived performance. 
Pal 
I- Pa3 _ 
I I P31 I _ Person-Role I x3 [\ 
__.J 
P102 Performance 172 MAN.4G S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
managerÆs job satisfaction and job-related ten- 
sion. In addition. these several variables were 
hypothesized to be related to two measures of 
performance. These variables were selected to 
encompass the unique characteristics c\f the in- 
dustrial product management role and to provide 
actionable implications for industrial product 
managers. Such variables have also been found to 
be important in other settings such as sales man- 
agement. consumer product management and 
project management [e.g.. 26. 391. Although the 
model does not provide a complete explanation of 
the forces operating on the product manager. it 
serves to summarize and integrate most of what is 
known about the reiationships featured. 
According to Kahn et al. [39. p. 891. ôrole 
conflict and ambiguity are independent sources of 
stress.ö Hence, the correlation between role am- 
biguity allu -A conflict is viewed as unrelated. In 
addition, satisfaction and job-related tension are 
not linked in the model. High- versus moderate- 
to low-level job-related tension may be hypothe- 
sized to have a negative influence on job satisfiac- 
tion: however. no significant linear or quadratic 
relationships between levels of job satisfaction 
and job-related tension have been reported in 
previous studies. 
Ttie cenrrai focus of this study is to expiore the 
hypotheses stemming from the relationships in 
the model. the rationaies for which have been 
developed in a number oftheoretical and empirical 
work. While the logic of some of these predic- 
tions is perhaps self-evident, the predictions are 
nevertheless important. A brief discussion of 
each set of linkages depicted in the model is 
developed. followed by the hypotheses tested. 
Uncertainty. which deals with thn perceived pre- 
dictability of the environment. is a key construct 
in the model. High perceived uncertainty imposes 
a difficult environment in which to make deci- 
sions. Galbraith 1271, for example, stresses that 
high levels of uncertainty require increased infor- 
mation processing by managers while Thompson 
[74] views uncertainty as the fundamental prob- 
lem in complex organizations. Boundary span- 
ning activities. therefore, become instrumental 
for gathering and integrating information to adapt 
to uncertain environments [I?. 13. 183. Industrial product managers operating in un- 
certain market settings may confront turbulences 
which can threaten the viability of their product 
turbulences likely include market in- 
troductions of high technology products by ag- 
gressive competitors, as well as the responsibility 
to gain customer acceptance of an enterpriseÆs 
own high technology product launches. Con- 
versely, rtabie environments are unlikely to 
create the same challenge in decision making, 
coordinating and information gathering. Hence, 
the frequeracy of the product managerÆs boundary 
spanning activities to collect information, opin- 
ions and i&as is likely to be greater in uncertain 
environments. Expressed as an hypothesis, the 
following prediction is made: 
HI: As industrial product managers perceive 
greater environmental uncertainty, their 
ary spanning activity is greater. 
Uncertainty may also impinge on the product 
managerÆs role conflict in terms of how others 
erate with the product manager and 
on the degree of role ambiguity the product 
manager experiences in wondering how s/he will 
be evaluated and compensated. Similarly, per- 
ceived environmental uncertainty is likely to af- 
fect the product managerÆs satisfaction and job 
tension. Finally, the product managerÆs perfor- 
mance is likely to be adversely affected if the 
environmental uncertainty s/he faces seems over- 
whelming. Qthers have documented the role dif- 
ficultles exaerienced in decision making in uncer- 
tain environ,ments [9, 39, 68, 50, 773. 
In view of these arguments, the following hy- 
potheses arc proposed: 
ustrial product managerÆs perceived 
uncertainty is related: 
H2a: Positively to role conflict dimensions 
H2b: Positively to role ambiguity 
H2c: Negatively to job satisfaction 
ositively to job-related tension 
egatively to performance. 
As product managers perform their functions, 
they may confront diverse and conflicting expec- 
tations about how their job should be performed. 
y may have to corn 
sing interpersonal sk 
ing. compromising or cajoling. Several researc BOUNDARY RN E SPANNING BEHAVIOR 
ers have found boundar) spanning to be associ- 
ated positively with role conflict 761 
and also !ikely to create a feeling igu- 
. According to this a&ground. the fol- 
lowing hypotheses are suggested: 
H3: The frequency of an industrial p 
agerÆs boundary spanning is related: 
H3a: Positively with role conflict dimensions 
H3b: Positively with role ambiguity. 
Boundary spanning activity is also postulated 
to be associated with the product managerÆs 
behavioral outcou~ such as job satisfaction and 
job-related tension. One study has found some 
association between boundary spanning and con- 
sumer product manager role outcomes [ZO]. In 
addition, because boundary spanning is an impor- 
tant activity for integrating and coordinating a 
product line, it seems plausible that increased 
frequency or boundary spanning will be associ- 
ated with performance. Given these rationales, 
the following hypotheses are proposed: 
H4: The frequency of an industrial product man- 
agerÆs boundary spanning is related: 
H4a: Positively to job satisfaction 
H4b: Positively to job-related tension 
H4c: Positively to performance. 
When role conflict and ambiguity reach certain 
levels. these forces are likely to impinge on the 
morale of product managers. Product managers 
may feel anxious about the pressures being faced 
and the lack of consensus on the functions or 
duties they must perform. The result may be 
disillusioned product managers susceptible to 
bunnout. Research by organizational theorists 
over the last two decades tends to confirm the 
relationship between role conflict, dissatisfac- 
tion, anxiety, propensity to quit and performance 
39. 53. 55-57, 733. Similarly, several marketing 
studies have found negative relationships be- 
tween salespersonsÆ role conflict and both job 
satisfaction and performance [5, 8, i 6, 32, 701. 
Researchers in both organizational behavior and 
marketing have also found a definite relationship 
between role ambiguity and feelings of tension, 
futility, dissatisfaction, employee turnover and 
negative attitudes toward role senders [3 1,40,53, 
6?]. 173 
ssures are also likely to hake an 
rmance. Several recent stud es in 
sales research have found negative relationships 
between both role conflict and ambiguity with 
petiormance [5, 15, 21, 25, 34, 751. Given this 
background the following ,y potheses are pre- 
sented: 
H5: 
H6: An industrial p uct manageræs role conflict 
(dimensions) is related: 
H5a: Negatively to job satrsfaction 
H5b: Positively to job-related tension 
H5c: Negatively to performance. 
An industrial product managerÆs role ambi- 
guity is related: 
H6a: Negatively to job satisfaction 
H6b: Positively to job-related tension 
H6c: Negatively to performance. 
One business adage is that a happy worker is a 
more productive one. Bateman and Organ [6], 
Motowildo [SS] and Smith et al. [71] have pro- 
vided empirical evidence showing a linkage be- 
tween job satisfaction and prosocial organiza- 
tlDna1 behaviors such as cooperating, listening, 
volunteering and helping others. According to 
CohenÆs [ 171 review of several key studies, stress 
creates conditions of information overload result- 
ing in cognitive fatigue; as a result, energy needed 
for task performance is sapped. Too much ten- 
sion can be an insidious force operating to frus- 
trate a product manager and ultimately leading to 
reduced performance from dramatic exhaustion 
and physical and mental fatigue 154, 591. 
This mode1 follows the thinking of Lazarus et 
al. [46], Janis and Leventhal [36] and Motowildo 
et al. [59], who view stress as an intervening 
variable with antecedent causes and behavioral 
consequences. The dysfunctional consequences 
to the firm may be grave in that a tense manager 
may be prone to more mistakes and may use 
adverse coping mechanisms. Moreover, the anxi- 
ety, hostility and depression which stress may 
generate are likely to affect job performance with 
respect to interpersonal sensitivity. tolerance for 
frustration and overall quality of work. It is 
therefore hypothesized that: 
H7: An industrial product managerÆs job satis- 
faction IS related positively to performance 
H8: An industrial product managerÆs job-related 
tension is related negatively to performance. One researcher [SO] has adliocated the use of a 
single-industry or one organization sample s&C- 
tion of product managers to control for confound- 
ing results because of structural differences 
between industries. In light of this recommenda- 
tion. the senior management of NZ Telecom was 
requested and agreed to participate in the study. 
The data used to test the research hypotheses 
were obtained from questionnaires administered 
in October 1987 to 95 managers employed by NZ 
T&corn. the former governcent telecommu- 
nications monopoly in New Zealand, which is 
being privatized. As the monopoly is being dere- 
gulated in the late 1980s. profit making is becom- 
ing a chief concern for the organization. The 
respondents were assured that their individual 
responses would be kept strictly confidential. 
The resulting sample size consisted of 69 indus- 
trial product managers, all of whom were men. 
The median age was 37. Approximately 80% had 
at least some college education. Median job ten- 
ure was 15 years as a manager in engineering 
and/or marketing. 
The full-time position of product manager was 
created at NZ Telecom about 14 months prior to 
the time of the study: the product managers 
included in the study had been in their positions 8 
to 14 months at the time of the study and most 
(58) of them reported being involved directly in 
planning and implementing new product market 
introductions during the past six months. All the 
product managers participating in the study re- 
ported that product introductions by new compe- 
titors. customer inquiry and demand for new 
products from NZ Telecom, and/or the dramatic 
increase in the rate of new product launches by 
NZ Telecom between 1985 to late 1987. were 
significant influences 3n the increase in commu- 
nications between line and planning divisions in 
the organization as Well as in the evaluations of 
their individual performance levels. 
The results of the study may be unique and 
limited ill two ways: they are industry-specific 
and they are related only to modeling and testing 
the performance of product managers working in 
an organization moving from a less competitive 
environment with few new product introductions S. LYSONSKl AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
to an intensely competitive environment with 
many new product introductions. 
The Variables 
Environmental uncertainty. Since many as- 
pects of uncertainty seem to work through an 
awareness and perception process 120, 33, 471, 
perceived environmental uncertainty was used to 
assess the product managerÆs evaluation of the 
environment. There are, as yet, no definitive 
answers to the appropriateness of a subjective 
measure versus objective measures of uncer- 
tainty. Anderson and Paine [4, p. 13211 maintain: 
ôIt is generally accepted that the perceptions of 
environmental and internal characteristics (rather 
than objective characteristics of the environment) 
are the important properties to consider.ö The 
instrument, using 15 interval scaled items, was 
adapted from a scale developed by Duncan 1231, 
who identified the main dimensions of uncer- 
tainty in decision making. In a study by Downey 
et al. [20], an alpha coefficient of .67 was re- 
ported; hence, the Duncan uncertainty scale ôap- 
pears to be methodologically adequate for basic 
researchö [20, p. 2021. 
Boundary spanning. Boundary spanning, de- 
fined as the frequency of verbal, written, formal 
and informal communication beyond the product 
managerÆs department, was measured using a 
modified instrument designed by Aiken and Hage 
[2] and used successfully by Leifer [48 
Lysonski [SO]. Respondents in this study re- 
ported the frequencies of various boundary ac- 
tivities excluding strictly social contact on conti- 
nuous scales; these were aggregated to develop a 
global measure. 
ale pressures. Role conflict is defined as the 
degree of incompatibility or incongruity of expec- 
tations associated with a role. Ten Likert scaled 
items were used to measure role conflict along 
various dimensions. The specific types of role 
conflict measured were: 
9 person role: incompatibility between the 
product managerÆs expectations and the ex- 
pectations otherwise associated with his 
role: 
patible expectatio 
another person; 0 intersender: expectations of one person in- 
compatible with those of anot erso d 
0 role overload: a product managerÆs .-esporG- 
bilities exceed the time and resources availa- 
ble for accomplishment. 
Role ambiguity, defined as a lack of clarity in 
terms of how one will be evaluated and what is 
expected, was measured with six-item Likert 
scale items. Both of these scales were developed 
and validated by Rizzo et al. [67] while others 1691 
have reported the psychometric soundness of the 
scales. 
ob tisfaction. Job satisfaction was mea- 
sured with five Likert type items. The questions 
assessed the product managerÆs evaluations 
about promotion opportunities. chances to dem- 
onstrate individual ability and initiative, satisfac- 
tion with the position compared to other posi- 
tions , whether the product manager would 
recom,mend the position to others and overall job 
satisfaction. A scale of this type was used suc- 
cessfully in several other studies [e.g., 7, 661. 
Job-related tension. Job-related tension was 
measured by 1 I items employing Likert scales 
which incorporated measures of work-related 
worry, relief when leaving work, items from the 
Manifest Anxiety Scale developed Roy Taylor [72] 
and dimensions from a study by House and Rizzo 
[31]. Job tension is the extent to which an individ- 
ual is psychologically bothered by work-related 
matters. 
Job performance. Two aspects of performance 
were measured using two self-rating items. The 
first item measured overall performance in terms 
of managing the assigned product line while the 
second item asked for the product managerÆs 
rating in terms of his interpersonal relations in 
gaining the cooperation of others who can assist 
in implementing product plans. A ten-point scale 
was used with endpoints of ôjust satisfactoryö 
and ôclear excellence.ö Because substantial dis- 
agreement surrounds what constitutes a valid 
objective measure of effective product manage- 
ment, the self-rating scale was ideally suited to 
this study. Mareover, self-rating measures of 
performance have been found to have less le- 
niency, less restriction of range and less error 
than the purportedly more objective measures of 
superior ratings [30]. Pym and Auld [65] have 
found self-ratings to correlate strongly with more Person rote 
Intersender 
Intrasender 
Role overload 
Role ambiguity 
Job satisfaction 
Job-related tension 
Performance 
Overall 
Coordina tine others 
objective measures of performance, while Pruden 
and Reese [64] found such measures to be related 
to actual job performance of industrial salesmen. 
A review of the literature on self-rated measures 
of performance by Busch and Bush [ 151 found 
strong support for their use. Michaels et al. [52] 
used this approach in the industrial setting for 
industrial buyers while Behrman and Perre:.ult [8] 
used it for industrial salespeople. 
Scale Reliabilities 
The instruments were used successfully by a 
number of other researchers. Scale reliabilities 
(Cronbach alpha coefficients) were derived to 
determine the internal consistency of the instru- 
ments. Table 1 presents these reuability measures 
while Table 2 presents other scale information for 
the sample. Because reliabilities exceeding SO 
are generaliy viewed as sufficient for research 
purposes [60], all scales used in this study can be 
considered reliable. 
Method of Analysis 
An appropriate methodology for analyzing the 
causal properties of the model is path analysis, 
also referred to as structural equation analysis 
143, 621. From a data analysis viewpoint, a path 
analysis is simply a series of regression analyses 
that allows quantification of each linkage in the 
model in terms of standardized (beta) coefficients 
that are called path coefficients [ 10, 221. Each s OQ INNO\Æ M.4%æ4ti S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOXXIDE 
I .b w-84 
Means and Standard Deviations of Research Vari&!es 
S, N: x1 X4 Xæ Xtl x- _- 
X, XY Xl,b x;.,, 
X: 
X, 
cotlfltc t 
x, 
fntnsender X< 
conflict 
Role overload Xp 
conflict 
Role ambiguit!~ x- 
Jab satisfaction X, 
hb-r&ted N, 
tension 
F-rformance X!, 
to\ CZI-all) 
Pu-fcrrmance X,,,@ 
icoordinating) 
Means 
Standara 
de\ iations -.I45 
- .072 256 
.355 .i79 -.I11 
.449 287 - .068 .486 
251 .419 ho2 .I01 .112 
.301 
-.I52 
.404 .372 .I95 
- ,268 - .087 - .474 
.344 .431 .120 -.017 .330 
.I45 
.I61 - .29s 
.x3 
-.034 .363 
-.213 
sq; ._. 
-.13! -.I42 -.1x - .449 276 -.!85 -344 .O% -.I 17 
-.321 -.I82 - .302 ,162 -.391 ,577 1.w - 276 .302 -201 
74 67.9 7.6 14.4 1.1 7.5 21.0 19.1 33.7 4.9 2.0 
13.8 47.2 2.4 3.7 2.4 2.7 5.4 4.8 8.6 6.0 1.8 
endoge~ous variable was regressed on other: [hat for testing the modei given the sample size and 
preceded it in the model in Figure 1. Table 3 sizable number of constructs. 
provides the structural equations ot the model. Figures 2 and 3 present estimates of computed 
This procedure assumes a general model in which path coefficients. Linkage assessments were not 
variables that precede particular variables in the based on the criterion of statistical significance 
causal sequence have direct causal effects on it. since this is not an accepted method of determin- 
The maximum likelihood approach (such as im- ing causal significance 1221. Researchers suggest 
plemented with LISliEL) was deemed unsuitable that a path coefficieut must show a magnitude of 
Table 3. Structw I equations 
X: = B:,X, - e: 
Y; = B;:X: - B:,>;, - tÆ; 
x; = B,:X: - B,,X, - eJ 
X< -5 Bc:X: - B,,X, - e.: 
X, = B,:X: - B,,X, - eh 
X- = B :X1 t B-,X, - e- 
Xi, = B,,X, - B,:X: - B,,X; - BNJXJ - Bh,Xc - Bw,,X, - B,-X- - eh 
X, - B,,X, - B,:X: - B,,X, - B,,X, - By,X, - B,IhX, 7 B,-X- - ev 
XW = B,,,,X, - Brn2X: - B,,,tX1 - B,,X, + B,,,<Xs t B,,X, + B,,7X7 A B,,,,X, -+ B,,,& + e 
Where: B, = Standardized partial rerression corfficient~ \s%ich reprecent path coefficients 
e, = error term 
P,, = path coefficients (i = dependent \~arable: j = independent \fariable) 
S : Peiceiied uncertamt! : X2: Boundary spanrung: S.: Person role conflict: X1: lntrasender conflict: Xi: Iqrersender conik~?: X: hir 
o\erlnad conflict: X-: Role ambiguity : X: Jo5 sali>faction: 74,: Job-related tension: XI,,;: 
perfmnmnce ~coordir._.:& d,!her\) Perceived perfomance (overallI: X,,,B: PerceikeJ @lx rdhntirqg &hers as the final dependent variable. 
Plot=-tt 
I x3 P103=-.os 
Person-Rote IA I 
I -. I 
I 
P 9Æ = sa 
L : 
P 102=.17 S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
.05 or greater to be considered causally signifi- 
cant I~_c]. of any path coefficient was found to be 
causally nonsignificant. the path was deleted and 
the system evaluated again. 
The basic test for the adequacy of a causal 
model is to compare the original correlation ma- 
trix with the reproduced correlation matrix 129. 
431. The reproduced correlation matrix is calcu- 
lated from the estimates of the computed path 
coefficients. In almost every case in which the 
reproduced correlation matrix was compared to 
the original one. the discrepancy was less than 
.06: this suggests that the original model is a 
meaningful description of the relationships 
among the variables. 
Each performance variable was treated as the 
final dependent variable in separate models. The 
models were trimmed by deleting paths with 
insignificant path coefficients. This produced re- 
stricted models in which the insignificant paths 
identified earlier were assumed to have path 
coefficients equal to zero. Given this assumptkn, 
the remaining path coefficients in the trimmed or 
restricted models were rcsalculated by regressing 
each endogenous variable on only those ante- 
cedent variables that were not presumed to have 
direct paths to it. 
in testing the hypothesized models. which 
specifies direct and indu-ect lmkages. with path 
analysis some standard assumptions were made. 
First. the relationships between the variables 
are assumed to be linear. Examinations of scat- 
ter plots of the residuals indicated the residuals 
were randomly dispersed and the relationships 
in the study were most likely linear. Moreover, 
the fact that the scatter plots indicated no seri- 
ous problem with ôouthersö suggested that the 
model had no misspecification problems. The 
results are limited to the extent that some vari- 
ables are omitted from the model specification 
in the study. Second. it is assumed that the 
residuals of a given endogenous variable are not 
correlated with other system variables nor other 
variables. Third. the causal system posited by 
the mode is viewed as recursive (i.e., there is 
no reciprocal causation) [78]. Lastly. the vari- 
ables are assumed to be measured on interval 
scales. To the extent that the scales are ordinal, 
results may be slightly biased. alt 
tiple regression is still t e recommended 
procedure [I I. 351. Results 
Figures 2 and 3 include the path coefficients for 
the two trimmed modeis using the two perfor- 
mance measures. Table 4 provides a listing of 
each path coefficient for the full and trimmed 
models and the association RÆs. The results do 
not uphold H 1 in that the perceived environment- 
al uncertainty link to boundary spanning is nega- 
tive (p = - .15). Hence, boundary spanning 
seems to decrease as uncertainty increases. 
Given the highly uncertain environment being 
experienced by NZ Telecom during the time of 
the study. some of the product managers may 
have ôgiven upö and retreated into their own 
organization. Æ 
H2a was supported in that perceived uncer- 
tainty was related to all measures of role conflict, 
particularly tc person role conflict (p = .25), 
intrasender conflict (p = .27) and role ambiguity 
(P = .29), supporting H2b. Uncertainty was 
Gnked slightly both to satisfaction (p = .05), 
leading to acceptance of H2c and to tension (p = 
.08), lending support to H2d. Although !rczer- 
tainty was related to performance in coordinating 
others (p = - .12), it was linked more strongly to 
overall performance (p = -.27), suggesting that 
greater uncertainty hampered performance (as 
hypothesized in H2e). 
Boundary spanning was not strongly associ- 
ated with the measures of role conflict, although 
the results indicate it was inversely related to all 
forms of conflict except role overload conflict; 
hence, H3a was not supported in the direction 
hypothesized. H3b is rejected for the same rea- 
son in that the relationship between boundary 
spanning and role ambiguity was negative (p = 
- .27). 
Boundary spanning was found to be weakly 
linked to satisfaction (p = .14), supporting H4a. 
but H4b was rejected since the relationship be- 
tween boundary spanning and tension was nega- 
tive and weak (p = - .04). Boundary spanning 
was associated negatively with overall perfor- 
mance (p = - .12) and positively with perfor- 
mance in coordinating others (p = .19), although 
these linkages are moderate; H4c was given some 
support as a result. 
Æ One of the journal reviewers of an earlier draft of this anick 
offered this observation on the observed nega*+e relationship. BOUNDARY ROLE SPANNING BEHAVlOR 
Table 4. Path Analysis for the Full and Trimmed Models 
Dependent Predictor H thesized Path 
variable variable sign IV IV 
X2 K t -.IS .03 Same 
xj x + 25 .07 SallIe 
X1 + -.08 
x.4 XI + 27 .Q9 Same 
X2 + -.09 
X5 XI + .I6 .06 Same 
X2 t -.I6 
xc, Xl + -11 .cE Same 
X2 + .09 
X: XP t .29 .!8 Same 
XZ - 27 
xx XI - .O5 .35 -.Q6 .33 
XZ .I4 .I1 
X3 - .O3 
x0 - -28 -.33 
: - .02 
- - .35 -35 
x7 - - .43 - .39 
XP i .Q7 .31 .os .30 
XZ f - .04 .I1 
XF + .I2 13 
x1 + .Q3 -:33 
& + .29 .30 
&I + .31 .32 
X? + -.I4 -.lI 
X IGa XI - -.27 .31 
& + -.I2 
2 - -.I5 
- -.09 
X_C - .05 
x, -.O6 
x7 -.37 
x8 + .17 
XtJ - -.I8 
X v -.12 .36 Iob 
iL; -.ll .34 
+ .17 .19 
ôx: - -.06 -.07 
- - .22 
XS - -.23 -.22 
x, -.12 -.I4 
X? - -.24 -.21 
x8 + .02 
X, -.24 -.28 
* X1: Perceived uncertainty: XL: Boundary spanning: X,: Person role connflict: X4. Intrasender conflict: X4: lntersender conflict: X,: Role 
overload conflict; X7: Role ambiguity; X8: Job satisfaction; X9. . Job-related tenslon: XIOA: Perceived performance (overall): XWI+: Perceived 
performance (coordinating others) Same 
H5a was upheld in that two dimensions of role 3 as a result given that their path coefficients were 
conflict (intrasender with p = -.33 and role less than AX. HSb was also given support in that 
overload with p = -.35) were strongly linked to three dimensions of role confiict (except intrasen- 
e paths for person role and der) were linked strongly to job-related tension. 
intersender conflict were deleted in Figures 2 and The two hypotheses positing a linkage of role MAN AG S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
ambiguity to job satisfaction (H6a) and job- 
related tension (H6b) are also given support with 
linkages of p = - ._ 39 for siitisfkiiun arki ii = - . i 1 
for tension. 
The final set of hypotheses examined the paths 
between role pressures and role outcomes on 
performance. The hypothesized negative impact 
of role conflict on performance (HSc) was sup- 
ported in that all the conflict measures were 
related inversely to both performance measures. 
Furthermore. role ambiguity was also negatively 
associated with performance in coordinating oth- 
ers (p = - 21) and with overall performance (p = 
-37). which supports H6c. 
Lastly. job satisfaction was linked to overall 
performance (p = .17) but not to performance 
involved with coordinating others (p = .02). 
which lends some support to H7. H8 was sup- 
ported in that tension was linked negatively to 
both overall performance (p = -. 18) and to 
performance involved in coordinating others (p = 
28). The RÆs for the model with overall perfor- 
mance as the final dependent variable was .31 and 
.36 for the coordinating performance measure. 
Discussion 
Although these results per-Cain to one organiza- 
tion which recently implemented a product man- 
agement organization. the findings may be rele- 
vant for large organizations studying the question 
of whether or not to adopt a product management 
design or tr those firms who plan to initiate the 
system. ThL .~sults from testing the models show 
that antecedent variables such as environmental 
uncertainty and role conflict among others can 
lead to impaired performance on the part of the 
industrial product manager. Because so little em- 
pirical research of this kind has been carried out 
on industrial product managers, a path analysis 
was developed with the assumption that the vari- 
ables are ordered in this causal sequence. 
The results support many of the important 
links implied by the causal order. However, the 
interpretations of these path analyses must be 
tempered with some caution. Among the possible 
limitations are inability to rule out other plausible 
causal configurations. incomplete specification of 
the mode1 may confound interpretation, errors of 
measurement, correlated method variance among 
the self-report measures and other potential Table 5. Comparisons Between Consumer and 
Industrial Product Managers 
Average number of 
Boundary spanning contacts ConsumeP 
Internal 57.7 
External 19.9 
Informal 43.6 
Formal 23.9 
r\ Source: Lysonski 1501. 
b Source: Present study. 
*t-test comparisons significant at .Ol level. IndustrialÆ 
21.4* 
11.2* 
20.7ö 
11.3* 
sources of bias. Despite these limitations, this 
study represents a step forward in developing 
causal models on industrial product management. 
Several managerial and research implications 
follow from the study. Firct, the results indicate 
that perceived environmental uncertainty may 
not stimulate greater levels of boundary span- 
ning. Indeed, product managers who did more 
boundary spanning perceived the environment to 
be more certain. This finding may be due to the 
newness of the product management position for 
most of the NZ Telecom product managers. Ta- 
ble 5 provides a CCXI parison between findings by 
Lysonski [50] on the boundary spanning activities 
of consumer produci managers and those in this 
study. On every dimension of boundary span- 
ning, consumer product managers had at least 
twice as many contacts. Because the consumer 
setting is different, we must be cautious in inter- 
preting this comparison. 
Many other reasons may accent for this result. 
Exhibit 1 lists some of the responses by product 
managers when asked, Are you satisfied with 
your level of contacts with the market? Many 
product managers lamented their lack of time to 
perform such activities. Our interviews with re- 
spondents also suggest that because NZ Telecom 
historical!y did not have to deal with compeiition, 
managers were unclear how to react to the uncer- 
tainty of a deregulated environment. 
In addition, some of the respondentsÆ informai 
comments after completing the questionnaire ex- 
pressed concern about their authority and re- 
sponsibilities as product managers. Several re- 
ported being tol by their senior agers not to 
engage in boundary spanning actions. One pro 
uct manager reported the following as a verbatim 
quote made by the manager he reported to: BOUNDARY ROLE SPANNING BEHAVIOR J PROD PNSOV !u19NAG i8i 
iw?.fi: ML%4 
Exhibit 1. Selected Candid Remarks by Respondents When Asked, Are You Satisfied with Your Levd of 
Contacts with the Market? 
I simply donÆt have the time to talk with outside clients as much as IÆd like to. 
Sure it would be nice to meet personally with the market. but IÆm busy with matters here [at the head off&j: 
besides, IÆm expected to be in my office. 
1 seldom ask sales reps for their views. We hear t problems when they happen. 
I feel overwhelmed at times. 1æ out 
how these can be used in our net the latest development in 5uitching technoIog:y and 
e enough trouble making sure the technology we have is on the go. 
I wish I had more time to absorb whatÆs happening. With deregulation. weÆre ail finding our way. 
The sales reps are supposed to let us know whatæs happening. 
My superior knows the market. 
ôYour job is to stay in your office and do product 
planning; operations does the implementing, you 
do the planning. Period.ö These directions did 
not fit the written job description given to each 
product manager at NZ Telecom. The written job 
description stated that the product manager is 
responsible for planning, ensuring that implemen- 
tation of the plan occurs and measuring results on 
sales and profits of the implemented plan. 
The newness of the job and confusion found 
among the product managers and their supervi- 
sors were factors likely to cause low confidence 
in performing the actions called for in the job 
description. Such conditions are likely to inter- 
vene and cause a negative relationship between 
environmental uncertainty and boundary span- 
ning activities. This finding may suggest better 
training and preparation of product managers 
before they formally begin their positions. Train- 
ing programs could be introduced to help product 
managers better deal with situations of high un- 
certainty. In addition, senior management may 
wish to emphasize the need for boundary 
spanning. 
As NZ Telecom experiences more turbulekicc 
from operating in a dcreg&ted gnyimnment. 
keeping in touch with the many forms of uncer- 
tainty is mandatory for product line viability. One 
product manager interviewed in the study ex- 
plained that the situation in his job was rather 
æ6cozyö when NZ Telecom was a government 
monopoly. Such product managers may not be 
accustomed to dealing with uncertainty and the 
concomitant need for boundary spanning. 
owever, industrial product managers likely 
need to be active boundary spanners !n the words of Aldrich and Herker f3. p. 2291 ôan 
organizationÆs ability to adapt to environmental 
contingencies depends in part on the expertise of 
the boundary role incumbent in selection, trans- 
mitting and interpreting information originating in 
the environment.ö Moreover, Jemison [38] 
argues that boundary spanners are important in 
strategic decision making because of their ability 
to recognize and deal with trends of changes in 
the environment. The implication, therefore, is 
clear. Industrial product managers are likely to 
need to span boundaries actively to understand 
external forces to be able to anticipate changes. 
The second implication deals with the impact 
of uncertainty on the product manager. Perceived 
uncertainty was related to role pressures of con- 
flict and ambiguity; these variables may lead to 
adverse outcomes such as dissatisfaction and 
tension. Uncertainty was also found to be associ- 
ated with lower performance, particularly overall 
performance. Hence, product managers, particu- 
larly those recently hired, may need better train- 
ing and skills to cope with and understand uncer- 
tainty. 
A third implication app lies to the benefits of 
bo;mdarv spanning. Unlike many other studies, 
this study did not find a positive association 
between role pressures of conflict and ambiguity 
with boundary spanning. Instead, the results indi- 
cated that as boundary spanning increased, these 
role pressures actually declined. Our interviews 
suggest that the product managersÆ efforts to 
communicate, despite the lack of encouragement. 
allowed them to understand the expectations of 
others, and possibly to shape the expectations of 
others, and, thus. lessening the likelihood of role 182 MANAG S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSiDE 
conflict. Such a result can also be explained in 
that boundary spanning activity would better 
assist the product managers in performing their 
j&s more effectively. Encouraging product man- 
agers to be better boundary spanners may actu- 
ally help to !essen role conflict and ambiguity. 
The product managerÆs boundary spanning was 
associated positively with performance in coordi- 
nating others but negatively with overall perfor- 
mance. Such a result may stem from the product 
manager using boundary spanning for coordi- 
nation but not for environmental scanning. which 
might help to improve overall product line perfor- 
mance. 
A fourth implication focuses on the potentially 
deleterious effects of role pressures. Most of the 
dimensions of role conflict were linked to tension 
and dissatisfaction. Role ambiguity also had a 
definite negative impact on satisfaction but less 
so on tension. It is likely that role ambiguity will 
increase for these product managers as the com- 
pany confronts competition from deregulation. 
Role ambiguity is likely to arise as the product 
managers adapt to the new environment and as 
senior management begins to redefine their job 
requirements. Indeed, they may not know what 
to do in such a changing environment, a type 
which they never had experienced before. This 
finding suggest that senior management may need 
to provide the information necessary for product 
managers to perform their tasks effectively. Such 
information may be particularly important for 
firms such as NZ Telecom that confront increas- 
ing competition and advancing tee hnologies. 
Performance was clearly seen to be related to 
various dimensions of role conflict. For example, 
the conflict experienced by the product manager 
from a single (intrasender) or from multiple (inter- 
sender) role senders was related to diminished 
performance. This may imply that product man- 
agers need to be given some help in their role in 
the expectations of others. Con- 
t managers often do not have au- 
ensurate with their responsibility. 
ty also was linked to diminished 
overall performance. Establishing clearer expec- 
tations in terms of how product managers will be 
evaluated and exactly what is expected might 
increase their performances. 
Methods to mitigate role pressures are many. 
Kahn et al. WI suggest several rqethods includ- ing changes in the organizational structure, devel- 
opment of new criteria for selection and place- 
ment of personnel, increasing the individualÆs 
tolerance and coping abilities and strengthening 
the interpersonal bonds among organizational 
members. 
A fifth implication deals with the effects of 
satisfaction and tension on performance. A prod- 
uct managerÆs satisfaction seemed to increase 
performance, which confirms some of the rela- 
tionships established in prior studies examining 
other organizational personnel. Moreover, ten- 
sion was also linked to reduced performance both 
in overall terms and in coordinating the actions of 
others. 
Since some forms of stress are to some degree 
inevitable, the key may be to reduce them to 
manageable levels 1441. In the present study 
perceived environmental uncertainty was related 
to forms of role conflict and ambiguity. It is, 
therefore, likely that as environmental uncer- 
tainty increases- these role pressures will in- 
crease. 
Because the components of the study are new 
to research on industrial product management, it 
is hoped that this study will stimulate further 
thinking and research on industrial product man- 
agement. If we are to better understand behavior 
and performance of product managers, more rc- 
search on existing product management organiza- 
tions is needed. Research is also needed to invts- 
tigate how product managers can be given the 
requisite skills to deal more with uncertainty, role 
pressures and an increasing need to commu- 
nicate. An examination of the moderating effects 
of a product managerÆs need for clarity, need for 
achievement and other personal characteristics 
on the relationships in the model would also 
contribute to our understanding. In particular. 
the development of more integrative models simi- 
lar to the one used in this study is needed for 
better understanding of the industrial product 
management system. Longitudinal studies would 
also help to better understand another dimension 
of the relationships in this study. 
The various insights and implications derived 
from this stud!, should be accepied as tentative BOUNDARY ROLE SPANNlNG BEHAVlOR 
volving a variety of industrial product manage- 20. 
ment settings. 
References 
æ) _. 
3. 
4. 
5. 
6. 
7. 
8. 
9. 
10. 
El 
12 
13 
I4 
I5 
lb slructure . 
sented at the American Sociologkal Association Conference. 
New Orleans, 1972. 
Aldrich. Howard and Herker, Diane. Boundary s ning roles 
and organizational structure. Academ_v o~~~a~ageme~t Rc~,iew 
2:217-230 (1977). 
Anderson, C. and Paine. F. Managerial perceptions of strategic 
behavior. Academy ~f&#arna~ernen? JnutrmaI 18:8l l-823 I 1975). 
Bagozzi, Richard P. Sslecrcrson performance and satisfaction 
as a function of individual differences. inte rsonal and situa- 
tional factors. JÆcxtr~ul of .&d-A-erin.e Research 155 17-53 I 
(1978). 
Bateman, T. S. and Organ. D. W. Job satisfaction and the good 
soldier: the relationship between effect and employee citizen- 
ship. Academy of ,UanaFemen? Jotrrnal26:587-595 ( 1983). 
Beehr, Terry A., Walsh. Jeffrey T. and Taber. Thomas D. 
Relationship of stress to individually and organizationally val- 
ued states: higher order needs as a moderator. Jow~aC of 
Applied Ps+wlogy 6 I :4 I-47 ( 19761. 
Behrman. Douglas N. and Perreault, William D., Jr. .4 role 
stress model of tl-.e performance and satisfaction of industrial 
salespersons. JownaI of Marketing 48:9-21 ( 19843). 
Benson. F The 
Morrow. 1975. Relaxation Response. New York: William 
Billings. R. S. and Wroten. S. P. Use of path analysis in 
industriallorganizationd psychology: criticisms and sugges- 
tions. Journal of Aophed Psyh~og~ 63:677-688 ( 1978). 
Bohrnsteda. G. W. and Carten. T. M. Robustness in regression 
analysis. In: SociologL.al Methodology. H. L. Coster fed.). San 
Francisco: Jossey Bass. 1971. pp. 118-146. 
Boulton, William R.. Lindsay. William M., Franklin, Stephen 
G. and Rue, Leslie. Strategic planning: determining the impact 
of environmental characteristics and uncertainty. Academy of 
Management Journal 25:500-509 ( 1982). 
Brown. W. B. Systems boundaries and information 
ernv of Management Journal 13:318-327 (1966). flow. Acad- 
Buell. V. P. The changing role of the product manager in 
consumer goods companies. Journal of Marketing 39:3-l I 
(1975). 
Busch. P. and Rush R. F. Women contrasted to men in the 
industrial salesforce: job satisfaction, values. role clarity, per- 
formance and propensity to lealIe. Jorrrnal of Marketing Re- 
search f 5:438-448 ( 1978). 
Churchill, GilberE A.. Ford. Neil M. and Walker, Orville C. 
Measuring the job satisfaction of industrial salesmen. Jowtal of 
Marketing Research I I :25-I-260 ( 19741, 
Cokwn, S. After effects of stress on human performance and 
social behaviour: a review of research and theory. Psychologi- 
cal Bulletin 88:82- 108 ( 1980). 
Conrath. David W. Organizing decision making behavior under 
varying conditions of uncertainty. Management Science 
13:B487-B500 (1967). 
mings, W. T.. Jackson D. W. and Ostrom, L. L. Differ- 
ences between industrial and consumer product managers. 
Industrial Marketing Management 13:171-180 (1984). 22. 
23. 
24. 
25. 
26. 
27. 
28. 
29. 
30. 
31. 
32. 
33. 
34. 
35. 
36. 
37. 
38. 
39. 
40. I83 
environmenti uncertaint) _ Proceedi 
FhE4 AcadempÆ u$ .Zfanagemenr. 1975. 
cal examp& In: 
Bkkck. Jr. red.). 
New York: Macmiftan. t97l. 115-138. 
DUnCan. Rokrt B. Characteristics of organi7atiorr;rt 63wm3n- 
~IMZWS and perceived envimnmzntal t~ncertaint~ . ,a&ninistrative 
Science @arter!y i7:313-327 4 1972). 
Eckl~s. R. W. and Novotny . T. J. lmius~rial product mmager: 
authority and responsibility. Indastriai Marketing Marrapemem 
l3:7I-75 t w?4). 
Franke. G. R.. Rehrman. D. N. and Perreault. W. D. Salesforce 
performance and satisfaction: contemporaneous relationships 
and selected antecedents. i!X AMA EducatorsÆ Conference 
Proceediws. Chicago: American Marketing Association. 1981,. 
233-237. 
Fry. Louis W.. Futrell, Charles. Parasuraman. A. and Chmie- 
lewski. Margaret. An analysis of alternative causal models of 
salesperson role perceptions and work-r&ted attitudes. Juur- 
naC of Marketing Research 23: 153- 163 (1986). 
Galbraith, J. Organizational Des@. Reading, AMA: Addison, 
1977. 
Gemmilf, G. R. and WiIemon, D. t . The product manager as an 
i&uence agent. Journal of Marketing 36:65-73 (1972). 
Heise. D. R. Problems in path analysis and causal infiuence. In: 
SociotogicaEl Methodology, E. F. Borgatta ted.). !!&=I Francisco: 
Jossey Bass. 1%9, 38-73. 
Heneman, G. Comparisons of self and superior ratings of 
managerial performance. Journal of Applied Psychology 
59:638-642 (1974). 
House, Robert and Rizzo, John. Role conflict and ambiguity as 
criticat variables in a model of organizational behavior. Organi- 
zational Behavior and Human Per$ormance 73467-505 (IY72). 
Howell, R. D., Bellenger. D. N. and Wilcox. J. B. Seif esteem. 
role stress and job satisfaction among marketing managers. 
Journal of Brtsiness Research 15:71-84 ( 1987). 
Huber, George P., OÆConnell, Michael J. and Cummings. 
Larry. Perceived environmental uncertainty: effects of informa- 
Eion and sEructure. Academy of Management Journal æ8:725- 
740 ( 1975). 
Ivancevich, J. M. and Donnelly, J. H., Jr. A study of role clarity 
and need for clarity in three occupational groups. Academy of 
Management Journal 17:28-36 (1974). 
James, L. R., Mulaik, S. A. and Brett, J. M. Caasal Analysis: 
Assumptions, Models and Data. Beverly Hills. CA: Sage Publi- 
cations, 1982. 
Janis. I. L. and Leventhal, H. Human reactions to stress. In: 
Handbook of Personality Theory and Research. E. F. Borgatta 
and W. W. Lambert (eds.). Chicago: Rand McNally. 1968. 
1041-1085. 
Jelinek, Mariann. Rethink strategy or perish. Journal off ro&ct 
innovation Management 1:36-42 (1984). 
Jemison, D. B. The importance of boundary spanning roles in 
strategic decision making. Journal of Management Studies 
2I(2):131-152 (19%4). 
Kahn, Robert L., Wolfe, D. M., Quinn, R. P., Snack, J. D. and 
xosenthal, R. A. Organkationa[ Stress. New York: Wiley. 
1964. 
Keller. Robert T. Role conflict and ambiguity: correlates with 
job satisfaction and values. personnel Psych010g~ 28:57--f+# 
( 1975). 41. Keller. Robert T. and Sziiagji. Andrew. Employee reactions to 
leader re\\ ard behavior. Acrrdetn.~~ qf Mmtu~ctntwt Jownul 
19:619-627 (1976). 
42 Ke?i!. J. P. and Hise. R. T. industrial and consumer goods 
prtduct manager3 are diRerent. Indmrrid Mcrrldtirt,k! Mc~tu~gt- 
frwfft 8:3Y-332 (199a). 
43. Kerlinger. F. N. and Pedhauzer. E. J. Multiple Regression in 
Buhattiorul Re.~u~h. New York: Holt Rinehart and Winston. 
1973. 
44. Kets de Vries. hlanfred. Organizational stress: a ~11 for man- 
agement action. SlcJun Muncr~entenr Recim, 2 I( I ):3- 14 ( 1979). 
45 C. Principles of path analysis. in: Sociohgicul Murk- 
San Francisco: Jossey Bass. i%9. 15-27. 
46. Lazarus. R. S.. Ikese. J. and Osier. J. F. The effects of 
psychological stress upon performance. Psychological Bulletin 
49:293-316 (1952). 
47. Lebiebicb. Husc! ;n ..tnd &,lancik. Gerald R. Effects of environ- 
mcnlal uncertainty on information and decision processes in 
banks. Adtninisrrurke Scienct~ Qzturtt~rIF 26(4):578-596 ( 1% I j 
4% Leifer. Richard Paul. An analysis of the charxteristics and 
functioning of interorganizational boundary spanning person- 
nel. Ph.D. dihbertation. Madison: LÆnivercit! of Wi5con:*in 
(19?_c). 
49. Luck. David. Interfaces of a product manager. Jam-nui c?f 
Markering 32:32-36 (1969). 
$0. 
Cl. Lvsonski Steven. . 
&duct managerÆs A boundary theory investigation 
role. Jmrnnl qf Markring 492630 of the 
(19SC). 
McDaniel. Carl and Graj 
rtin :lhnoeetnenr Reciert. D. A. The oroduct 
æ23: 143-150Æ11980). manager. Cu&r- 
5: &Iichaciq. R. E.. Day. R. L. and Joachimsthaler. E. E. Role 
stress among industrial bu>,ers: an integrative model. Joztrnul qf 
.!?ctrkerrng 5 I : 28-45 ( 1987). 
53. hllies. Robert H. A comparison cf the relative impxts of role 
I\+-rceptions of ambiguity and conflict by role. Acndcw~ of 
\I/ w,gcnte~,l Jorcrnul 19( I ):Y-35 t i976). 
54. \&de.,. I.,~bert H. Organizational boundarv roles. In: Cztrrctzl 
Cotzcctm itz 0~ cq-mj~~ttul S;rc~~ 1. G. L. Cooper and R. Payne 
feds.). Sew 1Æork: Wiley. 1976. 
55. Jliles. Robert H. Role conflict and ambiguity 13 boundary and 
internal ruleb: a field stud) usin p role set analysis and panel 
design. Ph.D. dissertation. Chaps! Hill: University of North 
Carolina ( 1974). 
56. Miles. Robert H. Role requirements as sources of stress in R&D 
organizations. Proceedings of rlw 3stir Meering of the Academ> 
of Management. 1975. 191-193. 
57. Miles. Robert H. and Perreault. Wt:!iam D.. Jr. Organizational 
role conflict: its antecedents and consequences. Orgnni:arional 
Belrnch und Hztttzun Pt~rfimncrtzcy 17: 19-44 ( 1976). 
58. Motouildo. S. J. Does job satisfaction lead to consideration and 
personal senzitiviiy? Acudemy c?f .Vunugcttzrtzr Jorcrtzul 27:9lO- 
915 (19841. 
59. Motowildo, S. J.. Packard. J. S. and Manning. M. R. Occupa- 
tional stress: its causes and consequences for job performance. 
Joztrtznr of Applied Psychohg~ 71(4):618-629 ( 1986). 
6@. Nunnally. Jim C. PcyclzotmJtric Tl~ot~. Ne\+ York: McGratb- 
Hlll. 1967. 61. Organ. Dtanis W. Sam: variables affecting boundary role 
behavior. Sctciotnet~ 34: 524-537 ( 197 I 1. 
62. Pedhauzer. E. J. Mzrltiplc Regression in Erl:u~h :I Resmrch. 
Zd ed. New York: Holt. Rinehart and Winston. 1982. 
63. Petrini. B. :. and Grub. P. D. Product management in high 
technology defense industrial marketing. CÆalifarnia Munage- 
tnent Review IS: 138-146 (1973). 
64. Pruden. Henry 0. and Reese. R. Interorganizational role-set 
relations and the performance and satisfaction of industrial 
salesmen. Adtninistrative Science Quarterly 17:601-609 ( 19721. 
65. Pym. D. L. A. and Auld. H. D. The self-rating as a measure of 
employee satisfactoriness. Occuparional Psyhology 39: 103- 
ii3 (i%C). 
66. Quinn. R. P. and Shepard. L. J. The 1972-1973 quality of 
employment survey: descriptive statistics with comparison data 
from the 1969-1970 survey of warking conditions. Ann Arbor. 
MI: The institute for Social Research, 1974. 
67. Rizzo. John, House. Robert and Lirtzman. Sidney. Role conflict 
and ambiguity in complex organization. Administrarive Science 
Qzumerly 15:1501-1563 (1970). 
68. Roos. Leslie. Jr. and Starke. Frederick. Organizational roles. 
in: HundbooX oj Organixrionul Design. P. C. Nystrom and 
W. H. Starbuck feds.). New York: Oxford Press, 1981. 
69. Schuler. Randall S., Aldag, Ramon J. and Brief, Arthur P. Role 
conflict and ambiguit! : a scale analysis. Organi,-ational Behav- 
ior and Hzcrmn Perfortmznce 16: Ill-128 (1977). 
70. Sheridan. J. E. and Slocum, J. The direction of the causal 
relationship between job satisfaction and work performance. 
Or~ani~ariorrul Bckarhr n& Human Pcrfnrtnnncr i 3: 159 - 172 
(1974). 
7 I. Smith. C. A.. Organ. D. W. and Near. J. P. Organizational 
citizenship behavior: its nature and antecedents. Jmrtta~ of 
Applied Psychology 68:653-663 ( 1983). 
72. Taylor. J. A. A personality scale of manifest anxiety. Jourtmlof 
Ahnartnul Social Ps_~lzolog_~ 48: 285-290 ( 1953 1. 
73. Teas. R. K. Supervisory behavior. role stress and the job 
satisfaction of industrial salespeople. Jozrrnal of Murkefirzg 
Researciz 20:84-91 (1983). 
74. Thompson. J. D. Organi:arinns in Acrion. New York: McGraw- 
Hill. 1967. 
75. Walker, 0. C.. Churchill, G. A. and Ford, N. M. Motivation 
and performance in industrial seiling: present knowledge and 
needed research . Journal of Markehg Research 14: 156- 168 
4 1977). 
76. Wall. James A. and Adams, J. Stacey. Some variables affecting 
constituentsÆ evaluations of and behavior toward a boundary 
role occupant. Or~atzi:arional Bekovior mad H~tmn Pet-for- 
tmznce I I :390-408 ( 1974). 
77. Weed. Stanley E. and Mitchell. Terence R. the role of environ- 
mental and behavioral uncertainty as a mediator of situation- 
performance relationshlps. Academy of Munugetnen~ JmcrtnuI 
33:36-60 (1980). 
78. Wright. Sewall. Path coefficients and path regr:s\ ion;: alterna- 
tive or complementary conceptsÆ? Biottzehcs 16: 189-202 t 1970). 
