0000 
Steven Lysonski and Arch G. 
While researchers 
have probed predictors 
of 
product 
managersÆ 
pe@ormance 
in consumer 
goods firms, few have looked at the per$ormance 
of the industrial product manager. in this article, 
Steven Lysonski and Arch Woodside use path 
analysis to examine causal models of industrial 
product managersÆ per$ormance during periods 
of rapid technological change. Key variables are 
analyzed. including the effects of environmental 
uncertainty, 
boundary spanning behavior, role 
pressures, 
role outcomes and two performance 
measures. A total of69 itrdustriul product man- 
agers from New Zealand Telecom completed u 
questionnaire 
that 
included 
both operational 
measures of the key variables and their overall 
job performance. The results suggest that most of 
the hypothesized 
relationships 
are supportable 
empirically. Perfiormance was hindered by envi- 
ronmental uncertainty, role conflict, role ambigu- 
ity, tension and dissatisfaction. 
The authors dis- 
cuss their studyÆs implications for improving the 
t ffectiveness 
of product management practices. 
Address correspondence 
to Arch G. Woodside, A. B. Freeman 
School of Business, Tulane University, New Orleans, LA 70118. 
0 1989 Elsevier Science Publishing Co., Inc. 
655 Avenue of the Americas, New York. NY 10010 
Using the telecommunications 
industry in a case 
study, JeEinek [373 describes how technology can 
radically change the basis for competition. 
For 
the telecommunir=ations 
industry and many oth- 
ers Jelinek emphasizes 
that the ônew technol- 
ogyö based on semiconductors, 
versus the old 
technology 
based on electromechanics, 
results in 
the following strategic imperatives: 
custom tailored and individualized 
produc :s 
are not only feasible but economical; 
proliferating 
products and flexible rcspo~~ 
to customers 
means more finely tuned mar- 
ket segmentation 
and product 
positioning 
strategies; and 
as more competitors push the state-of-the-art 
technology 
and product design, competition 
will favor those who provide quality, relia 
ity and responsiveness; 
price alone wonÆt do 
it, nor will the technology. 
JelinekÆs 1984 observations 
were based on ner 
analysis of American Telephone 
and Telegraph 
and other US telecommunications 
businesses. By 
the late 1980s the strategic imperatives 
outlined 
by Jelinek occurred 
worldwide in market-based 
nations. Th: product proliferation of high quality 
electronic 
t Secommunications 
products coupled 
with customers more frequently demanding many 
product features, more speed and higher reliabil- 
ity has resulted in major reorganizations 
of mar- 
keting and related business activities within large 
teiecommunications 
companies. 
The marketing effectiveness following the reor- 
ganization 
response 
to the new technology 
and 
BIOGRMWICAL 
SYETCHES 
Stc\cn L \wvbLi 
14 .\~~wa1e 
Profrt4wr at Marqurtte 
LÆntxerut? . 
~\t~iu,~~bee. 
\+æl\cansm 
Hz I N 4 former member of the bl.ddmg 
Facuk!, at the University of Canterbury. Christchurch. New Zealand. 
& 
the lÆnwer$ 
of Rhode Island at Kingston. He has completed 
www-ch on evaluating the cumpetul\e attractiveness of altematibe 
fbretgn \ asattlotr destination\. 
Arch G. Wwd&ie 
I* the Malcolm S. Woldenberp Proft?wr 
of 
Marketing of rhe A. B. Freeman Sshool of Bwincsh at Tulane 
lÆwenlt) 
. He IS Serw Editor of Adwnc t*.\ IFI Businw 
.4furkring. 
an annual \ olume sews OI origrnal re>earch reports and es3a! 5 on 
busmew-to-hwines?, marktmg toplo. He i* PreGdenr of ARC Con- 
sultant* Ins.. a firm specializing in research on planning and imple- 
menttRe msrketmg and product 4frafegie\. 
strategic imperatives 
by a national telecommu- 
nications 
enterprise. 
New Zealand Telecom. 
is 
reported in the present article. In a major effort to 
successfully 
introduce 
many 
high technology 
products 
in a marketplace 
that included aggres- 
sive competitors 
with many new products of their 
own. New Zealand Telecom (NZ Telecom) began 
by creating a new marketing 
organization. 
The 
product manager position product manager was 
central in the new marketing organization: before 
the marketing reorganization. 
the product man- 
ager position 
did not exist. The new product 
manager job description included the responsibil- 
ity for learning customer acceptance to new prod- 
uct designs. quickly learning and reporting prod- 
uct market 
introductions 
by competitors 
and 
directing 
the 
implementation 
of 
marketing 
strategies by the operating divisions of the firm. 
The study reported here is based on an in-depth 
survey of the activities and performance 
of these 
product managers at NZ Telecom. 
Success for industrial products 
may hinge on 
the performance 
of the product manager in coor- 
dinating the activities of others and in effectively 
managing the assigned product lines. Yet little is 
known about the position or the characteristics 
of 
individual 
industrial product 
managers 
[ l?] de- 
spite the increasing pol;Aarity 
of the industrial 
product 
management 
concept. 
Even thoubÆl a 
growing literature has developed 
on the role of 
the product 
manager in consumer 
goods indus- 
tries [ 14,X 
49-5 11. researchers 
have not probed 
the many dimensions 
of the industrial product 
manager. No attempts seem to have been made to 
develop and test models of the antecedents 
of 
performance 
of industrial product management. 
S. LYSONSKI 
AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
The purpose 
of this study is to develop 
valid 
causal models of the performance 
of the indus- 
trial product manager. 
The product manager in either the industrial or 
consumer 
setting functions 
as a communicator 
both inside and outside the firm. This boundary 
spanning role links the organization 
with a net- 
work of other organizations 
such as suppliers and 
buyers. In addition, 
this role includes coordinat- 
ing the efforts of multiple corporate 
departments 
to achieve product success. This communication 
role, however, 
may create stress and conflict for 
product 
managers, 
which ultimately 
can impair 
their performances. 
Although some research has examined the con- 
sumer product 
manager 
in terms of boundary 
spanning 
behavior 
[50], no comparable 
studies 
have looked at the industrial 
product 
manager. 
This article 
builds on the foundation 
laid by 
previous research on boundary role theory [ I,%] 
and provides a theoretical 
and empirical synthe- 
sis of some key issues related to the industrial 
product manager. 
The article is divided into four sections. 
The 
first reviews the published 
studies on industrial 
product 
management. 
The second 
presents 
the 
research model and hypotheses 
tested, while the 
third develops 
a methodology 
for testing the 
model and hypotheses. 
The last section focuses 
on the empirical findings and presents the conclu- 
sions and implications. 
Literature on Industrial Product Managers 
Only a few major studies 
have examined 
the 
industrial product manager and none of these has 
addressed 
performance, 
particularly 
in terms of 
the effects of environmental 
and behavioral 
di- 
mensions 
on performance. 
Such 
studies 
have 
established 
some differences 
between 
industrial 
and consumer 
product managers. 
Kelly and Hise 
[421, for example, 
found that industrial product 
managers 
were generally 
older and had more 
years of experience 
with the same product com- 
pared to product 
managers 
in consumer 
goods. 
Moreover, 
they found that in terms of role con- 
flict, role clarity and tension. the only difference 
was that consumer 
product 
managers 
reporte 
BOUNDARY ROLE SPANNING BEHAVIOR 
J 
ttt 
c 
managers 
with industrial 
goods responsibilities 
had greater 
levels of contact 
with sales reps, 
customers 
and managers 
in distribution. 
In an- 
other 
study 
using 
the case 
study 
approach, 
Petrini and Grub [63] found t at industrial prod- 
uct managers at Borg Warner and Curtis Wright 
had no control over pricing and no profit and loss 
responsibility. 
Two more recent studies on industrial product 
management 
find even greater differences 
be- 
tween consumer and industrial product managers 
than earlier reports. Cummings et al. [ 191 found 
that consumer 
product 
managers 
were active 
decision makers, unlike their industrial counter- 
parts who have less decision-making 
influence 
and instead function more as coordinators. 
They 
concluded 
that the industrial 
product 
manager 
differs significantly 
from the consumer 
product 
manager in terms of background 
characteristics 
and decision-making 
authority. 
Industrial 
prod- 
uct managers were significantly older, had more 
work experience 
and reached their position pri- 
marily from sales and some from engineering, 
unlike their consumer 
counterparts 
who were 
more likely to start as assistant product rnz nagers 
after obtaining 54.B.A.s. 
The other study by Eckles and Novotny [X] 
found that industrial product 
sponsibility for six or more prod 
Their major responsibilities inc 
profitability, physical product ch 
ing the productsÆ 
progress, 
product reengineer- 
ing, market entry, product conceptualization 
and 
any product 
deletions. 
Given such differences, 
research findings on consumer product managers 
may not be as applicable to the industrial setting. 
Hence, there is a need to focus explicitly on the 
industrial product manager. 
Variables and Hypotheses 
The relationships 
of several key behavioral vari- 
ables related to the product 
managerÆs perfor- 
mance were examined in the present study. The 
mode1 developed 
in Figure 
1 is a causal one in 
which 
perceived 
environmental 
uncertainty, 
boundary spanning and role pressures of conflict 
and ambiguity 
were predictors 
of the product 
Figure 1. A camal 
model of the variables in the study. Perceived envuonmental uncer- 
tainty, boundary spanning, role percepthns of conflict and ambiguity, role outcomes and 
perceived performance. 
Pal 
I- 
Pa3 
_ 
I 
I 
P31 
I 
_ 
Person-Role 
I 
x3 [\ 
__.J 
P102 
Performance 
172 
MAN.4G 
S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
managerÆs job satisfaction 
and job-related 
ten- 
sion. In addition. 
these several variables were 
hypothesized 
to be related to two measures 
of 
performance. 
These variables were selected to 
encompass 
the unique characteristics 
c\f the in- 
dustrial product management 
role and to provide 
actionable 
implications 
for industrial 
product 
managers. Such variables have also been found to 
be important in other settings such as sales man- 
agement. 
consumer 
product 
management 
and 
project management 
[e.g.. 26. 391. Although the 
model does not provide a complete explanation of 
the forces operating on the product manager. it 
serves to summarize and integrate most of what is 
known about the reiationships featured. 
According 
to Kahn et al. [39. p. 891. ôrole 
conflict and ambiguity are independent sources of 
stress.ö 
Hence, the correlation between role am- 
biguity allu 
-A conflict is viewed as unrelated. 
In 
addition, satisfaction and job-related 
tension are 
not linked in the model. High- versus moderate- 
to low-level job-related 
tension may be hypothe- 
sized to have a negative influence on job satisfiac- 
tion: however. 
no significant linear or quadratic 
relationships 
between 
levels of job satisfaction 
and job-related 
tension 
have been reported 
in 
previous studies. 
Ttie cenrrai focus of this study is to expiore the 
hypotheses 
stemming from the relationships 
in 
the model. the rationaies 
for which have been 
developed in a number oftheoretical 
and empirical 
work. While the logic of some of these predic- 
tions is perhaps self-evident, 
the predictions 
are 
nevertheless 
important. 
A brief discussion 
of 
each set of linkages depicted 
in the model is 
developed. 
followed by the hypotheses 
tested. 
Uncertainty. 
which deals with thn perceived pre- 
dictability of the environment. 
is a key construct 
in the model. High perceived uncertainty imposes 
a difficult environment 
in which to make deci- 
sions. Galbraith 1271, for example, stresses that 
high levels of uncertainty require increased infor- 
mation processing by managers while Thompson 
[74] views uncertainty 
as the fundamental 
prob- 
lem in complex organizations. 
Boundary 
span- 
ning activities. 
therefore, 
become 
instrumental 
for gathering and integrating information to adapt 
to uncertain environments 
[I?. 13. 183. 
Industrial 
product 
managers 
operating 
in un- 
certain market settings may confront turbulences 
which can threaten the viability of their product 
turbulences 
likely include market in- 
troductions 
of high technology 
products 
by ag- 
gressive competitors, 
as well as the responsibility 
to gain customer 
acceptance 
of an enterpriseÆs 
own high technology 
product 
launches. 
Con- 
versely, 
rtabie 
environments 
are unlikely 
to 
create the same challenge 
in decision 
making, 
coordinating 
and information 
gathering. 
Hence, 
the frequeracy of the product managerÆs boundary 
spanning activities 
to collect information, 
opin- 
ions and i&as is likely to be greater in uncertain 
environments. 
Expressed 
as an hypothesis, 
the 
following prediction 
is made: 
HI: As 
industrial 
product 
managers 
perceive 
greater 
environmental 
uncertainty, 
their 
ary spanning activity is greater. 
Uncertainty 
may also impinge on the product 
managerÆs 
role conflict in terms of how others 
erate with the product 
manager and 
on the degree 
of role ambiguity 
the product 
manager experiences 
in wondering 
how s/he will 
be evaluated 
and compensated. 
Similarly, 
per- 
ceived environmental 
uncertainty 
is likely to af- 
fect the product 
managerÆs 
satisfaction 
and job 
tension. 
Finally, 
the product 
managerÆs 
perfor- 
mance is likely to be adversely 
affected if the 
environmental 
uncertainty 
s/he faces seems over- 
whelming. Qthers have documented 
the role dif- 
ficultles exaerienced 
in decision making in uncer- 
tain environ,ments 
[9, 39, 68, 50, 773. 
In view of these arguments, 
the following hy- 
potheses arc proposed: 
ustrial product 
managerÆs 
perceived 
uncertainty 
is related: 
H2a: Positively to role conflict dimensions 
H2b: Positively to role ambiguity 
H2c: Negatively 
to job satisfaction 
ositively to job-related 
tension 
egatively to performance. 
As product managers perform their functions, 
they may confront diverse and conflicting expec- 
tations about how their job should be performed. 
y may have to corn 
sing interpersonal 
sk 
ing. compromising 
or cajoling. Several researc 
BOUNDARY 
RN E SPANNING 
BEHAVIOR 
ers have found boundar) spanning to be associ- 
ated positively with role conflict 
761 
and also !ikely to create a feeling 
igu- 
. According to this 
a&ground. the fol- 
lowing hypotheses are suggested: 
H3: The frequency of an industrial p 
agerÆs boundary spanning is related: 
H3a: Positively with role conflict dimensions 
H3b: Positively with role ambiguity. 
Boundary spanning activity is also postulated 
to be associated 
with the product managerÆs 
behavioral outcou~ 
such as job satisfaction and 
job-related tension. One study has found some 
association between boundary spanning and con- 
sumer product manager role outcomes [ZO]. In 
addition, because boundary spanning is an impor- 
tant activity for integrating and coordinating a 
product line, it seems plausible that increased 
frequency or boundary spanning will be associ- 
ated with performance. Given these rationales, 
the following hypotheses 
are proposed: 
H4: The frequency of an industrial product man- 
agerÆs boundary 
spanning is related: 
H4a: Positively to job satisfaction 
H4b: Positively to job-related 
tension 
H4c: Positively to performance. 
When role conflict and ambiguity reach certain 
levels. these forces are likely to impinge on the 
morale of product managers. 
Product managers 
may feel anxious about the pressures being faced 
and the lack of consensus 
on the functions 
or 
duties they must perform. 
The result may be 
disillusioned 
product 
managers 
susceptible 
to 
bunnout. 
Research 
by organizational 
theorists 
over the last two decades 
tends to confirm the 
relationship 
between 
role conflict, 
dissatisfac- 
tion, anxiety, propensity 
to quit and performance 
39. 53. 55-57, 733. Similarly, several marketing 
studies 
have found 
negative 
relationships 
be- 
tween salespersonsÆ 
role conflict and both job 
satisfaction 
and performance 
[5, 8, i 6, 32, 701. 
Researchers 
in both organizational 
behavior and 
marketing have also found a definite relationship 
between role ambiguity and feelings of tension, 
futility, 
dissatisfaction, 
employee 
turnover 
and 
negative attitudes toward role senders [3 1,40,53, 
6?]. 
173 
ssures are also likely to hake an 
rmance. Several recent stud es in 
sales research have found negative relationships 
between 
both role conflict and ambiguity with 
petiormance 
[5, 15, 21, 25, 34, 751. Given this 
background the following 
,y potheses are pre- 
sented: 
H5: 
H6: 
An industrial p 
uct manageræs role conflict 
(dimensions) is related: 
H5a: Negatively to job satrsfaction 
H5b: Positively to job-related 
tension 
H5c: Negatively to performance. 
An industrial product managerÆs role ambi- 
guity is related: 
H6a: Negatively to job satisfaction 
H6b: Positively to job-related 
tension 
H6c: Negatively to performance. 
One business adage is that a happy worker is a 
more productive 
one. Bateman and Organ [6], 
Motowildo 
[SS] and Smith et al. [71] have pro- 
vided empirical evidence showing a linkage be- 
tween job satisfaction 
and prosocial 
organiza- 
tlDna1 behaviors 
such as cooperating, 
listening, 
volunteering 
and helping others. 
According 
to 
CohenÆs [ 171 review of several key studies, stress 
creates conditions of information overload result- 
ing in cognitive fatigue; as a result, energy needed 
for task performance 
is sapped. Too much ten- 
sion can be an insidious force operating to frus- 
trate a product manager and ultimately leading to 
reduced performance 
from dramatic exhaustion 
and physical and mental fatigue 154, 591. 
This mode1 follows the thinking of Lazarus et 
al. [46], Janis and Leventhal [36] and Motowildo 
et al. [59], who view stress as an intervening 
variable with antecedent 
causes and behavioral 
consequences. 
The dysfunctional 
consequences 
to the firm may be grave in that a tense manager 
may be prone to more mistakes 
and may use 
adverse coping mechanisms. 
Moreover, the anxi- 
ety, hostility 
and depression 
which stress may 
generate are likely to affect job performance with 
respect to interpersonal 
sensitivity. tolerance for 
frustration 
and overall quality of work. It is 
therefore hypothesized 
that: 
H7: An industrial 
product managerÆs job satis- 
faction IS related positively to performance 
H8: An industrial product managerÆs job-related 
tension is related negatively to performance. 
One researcher 
[SO] has adliocated 
the use of a 
single-industry 
or one organization sample s&C- 
tion of product 
managers to control for confound- 
ing 
results 
because 
of structural 
differences 
between industries. 
In light of this recommenda- 
tion. the senior management 
of NZ Telecom was 
requested and agreed to participate in the study. 
The data used to test the research hypotheses 
were obtained from questionnaires 
administered 
in October 1987 to 95 managers employed by NZ 
T&corn. 
the former 
governcent 
telecommu- 
nications 
monopoly 
in New Zealand, which is 
being privatized. As the monopoly is being dere- 
gulated in the late 1980s. profit making is becom- 
ing a chief concern 
for the organization. 
The 
respondents 
were assured 
that their individual 
responses would be kept strictly confidential. 
The resulting sample size consisted of 69 indus- 
trial product managers, 
all of whom were men. 
The median age was 37. Approximately 
80% had 
at least some college education. 
Median job ten- 
ure was 15 years as a manager in engineering 
and/or marketing. 
The full-time position of product manager was 
created at NZ Telecom about 14 months prior to 
the time of the study: 
the product 
managers 
included in the study had been in their positions 8 
to 14 months at the time of the study and most 
(58) of them reported being involved directly in 
planning and implementing 
new product market 
introductions 
during the past six months. All the 
product 
managers participating 
in the study re- 
ported that product introductions 
by new compe- 
titors. 
customer 
inquiry 
and demand 
for new 
products from NZ Telecom, and/or the dramatic 
increase in the rate of new product launches by 
NZ Telecom 
between 
1985 to late 1987. were 
significant influences 3n the increase in commu- 
nications between line and planning divisions in 
the organization 
as Well as in the evaluations 
of 
their individual performance 
levels. 
The results of the study may be unique and 
limited ill two ways: they are industry-specific 
and they are related only to modeling and testing 
the performance of product managers working in 
an organization 
moving from a less competitive 
environment 
with few new product introductions 
S. LYSONSKl AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
to an intensely 
competitive 
environment 
with 
many new product introductions. 
The Variables 
Environmental 
uncertainty. Since many as- 
pects of uncertainty 
seem to work through an 
awareness 
and perception 
process 
120, 33, 471, 
perceived environmental 
uncertainty 
was used to 
assess the product 
managerÆs 
evaluation 
of the 
environment. 
There 
are, as yet, no definitive 
answers to the appropriateness 
of a subjective 
measure 
versus 
objective 
measures 
of uncer- 
tainty. Anderson 
and Paine [4, p. 13211 maintain: 
ôIt is generally accepted 
that the perceptions 
of 
environmental 
and internal characteristics 
(rather 
than objective characteristics 
of the environment) 
are the important 
properties 
to consider.ö 
The 
instrument, 
using 15 interval scaled items, was 
adapted from a scale developed 
by Duncan 1231, 
who identified 
the main dimensions 
of uncer- 
tainty in decision making. In a study by Downey 
et al. [20], an alpha coefficient 
of .67 was re- 
ported; hence, the Duncan uncertainty 
scale ôap- 
pears to be methodologically 
adequate for basic 
researchö 
[20, p. 2021. 
Boundary spanning. Boundary 
spanning, 
de- 
fined as the frequency 
of verbal, written, formal 
and informal communication 
beyond the product 
managerÆs 
department, 
was measured 
using a 
modified instrument 
designed by Aiken and Hage 
[2] and used 
successfully 
by Leifer 
[48 
Lysonski 
[SO]. Respondents 
in this study re- 
ported the frequencies 
of various boundary ac- 
tivities excluding strictly social contact on conti- 
nuous scales; these were aggregated to develop a 
global measure. 
ale pressures. Role conflict is defined as the 
degree of incompatibility 
or incongruity 
of expec- 
tations associated 
with a role. Ten Likert scaled 
items were used to measure 
role conflict along 
various dimensions. 
The specific types of role 
conflict measured 
were: 
9 person 
role: 
incompatibility 
between 
the 
product managerÆs expectations 
and the ex- 
pectations 
otherwise 
associated 
with his 
role: 
patible expectatio 
another person; 
0 intersender: expectations of one person in- 
compatible with those of anot 
erso 
d 
0 role overload: a product managerÆs .-esporG- 
bilities exceed the time and resources availa- 
ble for accomplishment. 
Role ambiguity, defined as a lack of clarity in 
terms of how one will be evaluated and what is 
expected, 
was measured with six-item Likert 
scale items. Both of these scales were developed 
and validated by Rizzo et al. [67] while others 1691 
have reported the psychometric soundness of the 
scales. 
ob 
tisfaction. Job satisfaction 
was mea- 
sured with five Likert type items. The questions 
assessed 
the product 
managerÆs evaluations 
about promotion opportunities. chances to dem- 
onstrate individual ability and initiative, satisfac- 
tion with the position compared to other posi- 
tions , whether 
the product 
manager would 
recom,mend the position to others and overall job 
satisfaction. A scale of this type was used suc- 
cessfully in several other studies [e.g., 7, 661. 
Job-related tension. Job-related tension was 
measured by 1 I items employing Likert scales 
which incorporated measures of work-related 
worry, relief when leaving work, items from the 
Manifest Anxiety Scale developed Roy Taylor [72] 
and dimensions from a study by House and Rizzo 
[31]. Job tension is the extent to which an individ- 
ual is psychologically 
bothered by work-related 
matters. 
Job performance. Two aspects of performance 
were measured 
using two self-rating items. The 
first item measured overall performance 
in terms 
of managing the assigned product line while the 
second 
item asked for the product 
managerÆs 
rating in terms of his interpersonal 
relations in 
gaining the cooperation 
of others who can assist 
in implementing 
product plans. A ten-point scale 
was used with endpoints 
of ôjust satisfactoryö 
and ôclear excellence.ö 
Because substantial dis- 
agreement 
surrounds 
what constitutes 
a valid 
objective 
measure of effective product manage- 
ment, the self-rating scale was ideally suited to 
this study. 
Mareover, 
self-rating 
measures 
of 
performance 
have been found to have less le- 
niency, 
less restriction 
of range and less error 
than the purportedly 
more objective measures of 
superior 
ratings [30]. Pym and Auld [65] have 
found self-ratings to correlate strongly with more 
Person rote 
Intersender 
Intrasender 
Role overload 
Role ambiguity 
Job satisfaction 
Job-related tension 
Performance 
Overall 
Coordina tine others 
objective measures of performance, 
while Pruden 
and Reese [64] found such measures to be related 
to actual job performance 
of industrial salesmen. 
A review of the literature on self-rated measures 
of performance 
by Busch and Bush [ 151 found 
strong support for their use. Michaels et al. [52] 
used this approach 
in the industrial setting for 
industrial buyers while Behrman and Perre:.ult [8] 
used it for industrial salespeople. 
Scale Reliabilities 
The instruments 
were used successfully 
by a 
number of other researchers. 
Scale reliabilities 
(Cronbach 
alpha coefficients) 
were derived 
to 
determine 
the internal consistency 
of the instru- 
ments. Table 1 presents these reuability measures 
while Table 2 presents other scale information for 
the sample. 
Because reliabilities exceeding 
SO 
are generaliy 
viewed as sufficient for research 
purposes [60], all scales used in this study can be 
considered 
reliable. 
Method of Analysis 
An appropriate 
methodology 
for analyzing the 
causal properties 
of the model is path analysis, 
also referred 
to as structural 
equation analysis 
143, 621. From a data analysis viewpoint, a path 
analysis is simply a series of regression analyses 
that allows quantification 
of each linkage in the 
model in terms of standardized 
(beta) coefficients 
that are called path coefficients 
[ 10, 221. Each 
s 
OQ INNO\Æ 
M.4%æ4ti 
S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOXXIDE 
I 
.b w-84 
Means and Standard Deviations of Research Vari&!es 
S, 
N: 
x1 
X4 
Xæ 
Xtl 
x- 
_- 
X, 
XY 
Xl,b 
x;.,, 
X: 
X, 
cotlfltc t 
x, 
fntnsender 
X< 
conflict 
Role overload 
Xp 
conflict 
Role ambiguit!~ 
x- 
Jab satisfaction 
X, 
hb-r&ted 
N, 
tension 
F-rformance 
X!, 
to\ CZI-all) 
Pu-fcrrmance 
X,,,@ 
icoordinating) 
Means 
Standara 
de\ iations 
-.I45 
- .072 
256 
.355 
.i79 
-.I11 
.449 
287 
- .068 
.486 
251 
.419 
ho2 
.I01 
.112 
.301 
-.I52 
.404 
.372 
.I95 
- ,268 
- .087 
- .474 
.344 
.431 
.120 
-.017 
.330 
.I45 
.I61 
- .29s 
.x3 
-.034 
.363 
-.213 
sq; 
._. 
-.13! 
-.I42 
-.1x 
- .449 
276 
-.!85 
-344 
.O% 
-.I 17 
-.321 
-.I82 
- .302 
,162 
-.391 
,577 
1.w 
- 276 
.302 
-201 
74 
67.9 
7.6 
14.4 
1.1 
7.5 
21.0 
19.1 
33.7 
4.9 
2.0 
13.8 
47.2 
2.4 
3.7 
2.4 
2.7 
5.4 
4.8 
8.6 
6.0 
1.8 
endoge~ous 
variable was regressed on other: [hat 
for testing the modei given the sample size and 
preceded 
it in the model in Figure 
1. Table 3 
sizable number of constructs. 
provides the structural equations 
ot the model. 
Figures 2 and 3 present estimates of computed 
This procedure assumes a general model in which 
path coefficients. 
Linkage assessments 
were not 
variables that precede particular variables in the 
based on the criterion 
of statistical 
significance 
causal sequence have direct causal effects on it. 
since this is not an accepted method of determin- 
The maximum likelihood approach (such as im- 
ing causal significance 
1221. Researchers 
suggest 
plemented with LISliEL) was deemed unsuitable 
that a path coefficieut 
must show a magnitude of 
Table 3. Structw I equations 
X: = B:,X, 
- e: 
Y; = B;:X: 
- B:,>;, - tÆ; 
x; = B,:X: 
- B,,X, 
- eJ 
X< -5 Bc:X: - B,,X, 
- e.: 
X, = B,:X: 
- B,,X, 
- eh 
X- = B :X1 t B-,X, - e- 
Xi, = B,,X, 
- B,:X: 
- B,,X; 
- BNJXJ - Bh,Xc - Bw,,X, - B,-X- - eh 
X, - B,,X, 
- B,:X: 
- B,,X, 
- B,,X, 
- By,X, - B,IhX, 7 B,-X- - ev 
XW = B,,,,X, - Brn2X: - B,,,tX1 - B,,X, 
+ B,,,<Xs t B,,X, 
+ B,,7X7 A B,,,,X, -+ B,,,& 
+ e 
Where: 
B, = Standardized 
partial 
rerression 
corfficient~ 
\s%ich reprecent 
path coefficients 
e, 
= error term 
P,, = path coefficients 
(i = dependent 
\~arable: 
j = independent 
\fariable) 
S : Peiceiied 
uncertamt! 
: X2: Boundary 
spanrung: 
S.: Person 
role conflict: 
X1: lntrasender 
conflict: 
Xi: Iqrersender 
conik~?: 
X: 
hir 
o\erlnad 
conflict: X-: Role ambiguity : X: Jo5 sali>faction: 
74,: Job-related 
tension: 
XI,,;: 
perfmnmnce 
~coordir._.:& 
d,!her\) 
Perceived 
perfomance 
(overallI: 
X,,,B: PerceikeJ 
@lx 
rdhntirqg &hers as the final dependent variable. 
Plot=-tt 
I 
x3 
P103=-.os 
Person-Rote 
IA 
I 
I 
-. 
I 
I 
P 9Æ = sa 
L 
: 
P 102=.17 
S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
.05 or greater to be considered 
causally signifi- 
cant I~_c]. of any path coefficient was found to be 
causally nonsignificant. the path was deleted and 
the system evaluated again. 
The basic test for the adequacy 
of a causal 
model is to compare the original correlation 
ma- 
trix with the reproduced 
correlation 
matrix 129. 
431. The reproduced 
correlation 
matrix is calcu- 
lated from the estimates 
of the computed 
path 
coefficients. 
In almost every case in which the 
reproduced 
correlation 
matrix was compared 
to 
the original one. the discrepancy 
was less than 
.06: this suggests that the original model is a 
meaningful 
description 
of 
the 
relationships 
among the variables. 
Each performance 
variable was treated as the 
final dependent 
variable in separate models. The 
models 
were trimmed 
by deleting 
paths 
with 
insignificant path coefficients. 
This produced 
re- 
stricted models in which the insignificant paths 
identified 
earlier were assumed 
to have path 
coefficients equal to zero. Given this assumptkn, 
the remaining path coefficients in the trimmed or 
restricted models were rcsalculated by regressing 
each endogenous 
variable on only those ante- 
cedent variables that were not presumed to have 
direct paths to it. 
in testing 
the hypothesized 
models. 
which 
specifies direct and indu-ect lmkages. with path 
analysis some standard assumptions 
were made. 
First. 
the relationships 
between 
the variables 
are assumed to be linear. Examinations 
of scat- 
ter plots of the residuals indicated the residuals 
were randomly dispersed 
and the relationships 
in the study were most likely linear. Moreover, 
the fact that the scatter plots indicated no seri- 
ous problem with ôouthersö 
suggested that the 
model had no misspecification 
problems. 
The 
results are limited to the extent that some vari- 
ables are omitted from the model specification 
in the study. 
Second. 
it is assumed 
that the 
residuals of a given endogenous 
variable are not 
correlated 
with other system variables nor other 
variables. 
Third. the causal system posited 
by 
the mode is viewed as recursive 
(i.e., there is 
no reciprocal 
causation) 
[78]. Lastly. the vari- 
ables are assumed to be measured 
on interval 
scales. To the extent that the scales are ordinal, 
results 
may be slightly 
biased. 
alt 
tiple regression 
is still t e recommended 
procedure 
[I I. 351. 
Results 
Figures 2 and 3 include the path coefficients 
for 
the two trimmed 
modeis using the two perfor- 
mance measures. 
Table 4 provides 
a listing of 
each path coefficient 
for the full and trimmed 
models and the association 
RÆs. The results do 
not uphold H 1 in that the perceived environment- 
al uncertainty 
link to boundary 
spanning is nega- 
tive (p 
= - .15). Hence, 
boundary 
spanning 
seems 
to decrease 
as uncertainty 
increases. 
Given the highly uncertain 
environment 
being 
experienced 
by NZ Telecom 
during the time of 
the study. 
some of the product 
managers 
may 
have ôgiven 
upö and retreated 
into their own 
organization. 
Æ 
H2a was supported 
in that perceived 
uncer- 
tainty was related to all measures of role conflict, 
particularly 
tc person 
role conflict 
(p = .25), 
intrasender 
conflict (p = .27) and role ambiguity 
(P = .29), supporting 
H2b. 
Uncertainty 
was 
Gnked slightly 
both to satisfaction 
(p = .05), 
leading to acceptance 
of H2c and to tension (p = 
.08), lending support 
to H2d. Although 
!rczer- 
tainty was related to performance 
in coordinating 
others (p = - .12), 
it was linked more strongly to 
overall performance 
(p = -.27), suggesting that 
greater 
uncertainty 
hampered 
performance 
(as 
hypothesized 
in H2e). 
Boundary 
spanning 
was not strongly associ- 
ated with the measures of role conflict, although 
the results indicate it was inversely related to all 
forms of conflict except role overload 
conflict; 
hence, H3a was not supported 
in the direction 
hypothesized. 
H3b is rejected for the same rea- 
son in that the relationship 
between 
boundary 
spanning and role ambiguity 
was negative 
(p 
= 
- .27). 
Boundary 
spanning 
was found to be weakly 
linked to satisfaction 
(p = .14), 
supporting 
H4a. 
but H4b was rejected since the relationship 
be- 
tween boundary 
spanning and tension was nega- 
tive and weak (p = - .04). Boundary 
spanning 
was associated 
negatively 
with overall perfor- 
mance (p = - .12) and positively 
with perfor- 
mance in coordinating 
others (p = .19), although 
these linkages are moderate; H4c was given some 
support as a result. 
Æ One of the journal reviewers 
of an earlier draft of this anick 
offered this observation 
on the observed nega*+e relationship. 
BOUNDARY 
ROLE SPANNING 
BEHAVlOR 
Table 4. Path Analysis for the Full and Trimmed Models 
Dependent 
Predictor 
H 
thesized 
Path 
variable 
variable 
sign 
IV 
IV 
X2 
K 
t 
-.IS 
.03 
Same 
xj 
x 
+ 
25 
.07 
SallIe 
X1 
+ 
-.08 
x.4 
XI 
+ 
27 
.Q9 
Same 
X2 
+ 
-.09 
X5 
XI 
+ 
.I6 
.06 
Same 
X2 
t 
-.I6 
xc, 
Xl 
+ 
-11 
.cE 
Same 
X2 
+ 
.09 
X: 
XP 
t 
.29 
.!8 
Same 
XZ 
- 27 
xx 
XI 
- .O5 
.35 
-.Q6 
.33 
XZ 
.I4 
.I1 
X3 
- 
.O3 
x0 
- -28 
-.33 
: 
- 
.02 
- 
- .35 
-35 
x7 
- 
- .43 
- .39 
XP 
i 
.Q7 
.31 
.os 
.30 
XZ 
f 
- .04 
.I1 
XF 
+ 
.I2 
13 
x1 
+ 
.Q3 
-:33 
& 
+ 
.29 
.30 
&I 
+ 
.31 
.32 
X? 
+ 
-.I4 
-.lI 
X IGa 
XI 
- 
-.27 
.31 
& 
+ 
-.I2 
2 
- 
-.I5 
- 
-.09 
X_C 
- .05 
x, 
-.O6 
x7 
-.37 
x8 
+ 
.17 
XtJ 
- 
-.I8 
X 
v 
-.12 
.36 
Iob 
iL; 
-.ll 
.34 
+ 
.17 
.19 
ôx: 
- 
-.06 
-.07 
- 
- .22 
XS 
- 
-.23 
-.22 
x, 
-.12 
-.I4 
X? 
- 
-.24 
-.21 
x8 
+ 
.02 
X, 
-.24 
-.28 
* 
X1: Perceived uncertainty: 
XL: Boundary spanning: X,: Person role connflict: X4. Intrasender conflict: X4: lntersender conflict: X,: Role 
overload conflict; X7: Role ambiguity; X8: Job satisfaction; X9. . Job-related tenslon: XIOA: Perceived performance (overall): XWI+: Perceived 
performance 
(coordinating 
others) 
Same 
H5a was upheld in that two dimensions of role 
3 as a result given that their path coefficients were 
conflict 
(intrasender 
with p = -.33 
and role 
less than AX. HSb was also given support in that 
overload with p = -.35) were strongly linked to 
three dimensions of role confiict (except intrasen- 
e paths for person role and 
der) were linked strongly to job-related tension. 
intersender 
conflict were deleted in Figures 2 and 
The two hypotheses 
positing a linkage of role 
MAN AG 
S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSIDE 
ambiguity 
to job satisfaction 
(H6a) and job- 
related tension (H6b) are also given support with 
linkages of p = - ._ 39 for siitisfkiiun 
arki ii = - . i 1 
for tension. 
The final set of hypotheses 
examined the paths 
between 
role pressures 
and role outcomes 
on 
performance. 
The hypothesized 
negative impact 
of role conflict on performance 
(HSc) was sup- 
ported 
in that all the conflict 
measures 
were 
related inversely to both performance 
measures. 
Furthermore. 
role ambiguity was also negatively 
associated with performance 
in coordinating 
oth- 
ers (p = - 21) and with overall performance 
(p = 
-37). 
which supports H6c. 
Lastly. job satisfaction 
was linked to overall 
performance 
(p = .17) but not to performance 
involved 
with coordinating 
others 
(p = .02). 
which lends some support to H7. H8 was sup- 
ported in that tension was linked negatively 
to 
both overall performance 
(p = -. 18) and to 
performance 
involved in coordinating others (p = 
28). The RÆs for the model with overall perfor- 
mance as the final dependent 
variable was .31 and 
.36 for the coordinating 
performance 
measure. 
Discussion 
Although these results per-Cain to one organiza- 
tion which recently implemented 
a product man- 
agement organization. 
the findings may be rele- 
vant for large organizations 
studying the question 
of whether or not to adopt a product management 
design or tr those firms who plan to initiate the 
system. ThL .~sults from testing the models show 
that antecedent 
variables such as environmental 
uncertainty 
and role conflict among others can 
lead to impaired performance 
on the part of the 
industrial product manager. Because so little em- 
pirical research of this kind has been carried out 
on industrial product managers, 
a path analysis 
was developed with the assumption that the vari- 
ables are ordered in this causal sequence. 
The results 
support 
many of the important 
links implied by the causal order. However, the 
interpretations 
of these path analyses must be 
tempered with some caution. Among the possible 
limitations are inability to rule out other plausible 
causal configurations. 
incomplete specification of 
the mode1 may confound interpretation, 
errors of 
measurement, 
correlated method variance among 
the self-report 
measures 
and other 
potential 
Table 5. Comparisons Between Consumer and 
Industrial Product Managers 
Average number of 
Boundary spanning contacts 
ConsumeP 
Internal 
57.7 
External 
19.9 
Informal 
43.6 
Formal 
23.9 
r\ Source: Lysonski 1501. 
b Source: Present study. 
*t-test comparisons 
significant at .Ol level. 
IndustrialÆ 
21.4* 
11.2* 
20.7ö 
11.3* 
sources of bias. Despite these limitations, 
this 
study represents 
a step forward 
in developing 
causal models on industrial product management. 
Several managerial 
and research 
implications 
follow from the study. Firct, the results indicate 
that perceived 
environmental 
uncertainty 
may 
not stimulate 
greater 
levels of boundary 
span- 
ning. Indeed, 
product 
managers 
who did more 
boundary spanning perceived the environment 
to 
be more certain. This finding may be due to the 
newness of the product management 
position for 
most of the NZ Telecom product managers. Ta- 
ble 5 provides a CCXI parison between findings by 
Lysonski [50] on the boundary spanning activities 
of consumer 
produci managers and those in this 
study. On every dimension 
of boundary 
span- 
ning, consumer 
product 
managers 
had at least 
twice as many contacts. 
Because the consumer 
setting is different, 
we must be cautious in inter- 
preting this comparison. 
Many other reasons may accent for this result. 
Exhibit 1 lists some of the responses 
by product 
managers 
when asked, 
Are you satisfied with 
your level of contacts 
with the market? 
Many 
product managers 
lamented their lack of time to 
perform such activities. 
Our interviews 
with re- 
spondents also suggest that because NZ Telecom 
historical!y did not have to deal with compeiition, 
managers were unclear how to react to the uncer- 
tainty of a deregulated 
environment. 
In addition, some of the respondentsÆ 
informai 
comments after completing 
the questionnaire 
ex- 
pressed 
concern 
about their authority 
and re- 
sponsibilities 
as product 
managers. 
Several re- 
ported being tol 
by their senior 
agers not to 
engage in boundary 
spanning actions. One pro 
uct manager reported the following as a verbatim 
quote made 
by the manager 
he reported 
to: 
BOUNDARY ROLE SPANNING BEHAVIOR 
J PROD PNSOV !u19NAG 
i8i 
iw?.fi: ML%4 
Exhibit 1. Selected Candid Remarks by Respondents 
When Asked, Are You Satisfied with Your 
Levd 
of 
Contacts with the Market? 
I simply donÆt have the time to talk with outside clients as much as IÆd like to. 
Sure it would be nice to meet personally with the market. but IÆm busy with matters here [at the head off&j: 
besides, IÆm expected to be in my office. 
1 seldom ask sales reps for their views. We hear 
t problems when they happen. 
I feel overwhelmed at times. 1æ 
out 
how 
these can be used in our net 
the 
latest 
development 
in 
5uitching 
technoIog:y 
and 
e enough trouble making sure the technology we have is on the go. 
I wish I had more time to absorb whatÆs happening. With deregulation. weÆre ail finding our way. 
The sales reps are supposed to let us know whatæs happening. 
My superior knows the market. 
ôYour job is to stay in your office and do product 
planning; operations does the implementing, you 
do the planning. Period.ö These directions did 
not fit the written job description given to each 
product manager at NZ Telecom. The written job 
description stated that the product manager is 
responsible for planning, ensuring that implemen- 
tation of the plan occurs and measuring results on 
sales and profits of the implemented plan. 
The newness of the job and confusion found 
among the product managers and their supervi- 
sors were factors likely to cause low confidence 
in performing the actions called for in the job 
description. Such conditions are likely to inter- 
vene and cause a negative relationship between 
environmental uncertainty and boundary span- 
ning activities. This finding may suggest better 
training and preparation of product managers 
before they formally begin their positions. Train- 
ing programs could be introduced to help product 
managers better deal with situations of high un- 
certainty. 
In addition, 
senior management 
may 
wish 
to emphasize 
the 
need 
for 
boundary 
spanning. 
As NZ Telecom experiences 
more turbulekicc 
from operating 
in a dcreg&ted 
gnyimnment. 
keeping in touch with the many forms of uncer- 
tainty is mandatory for product line viability. One 
product manager interviewed in the study ex- 
plained that the situation in his job was rather 
æ6cozyö when NZ Telecom 
was a government 
monopoly. 
Such product 
managers may not be 
accustomed 
to dealing with uncertainty 
and the 
concomitant 
need 
for 
boundary 
spanning. 
owever, 
industrial 
product 
managers 
likely 
need to be active 
boundary 
spanners 
!n the 
words of Aldrich and Herker f3. p. 2291 ôan 
organizationÆs 
ability to adapt to environmental 
contingencies depends in part on the expertise of 
the boundary role incumbent in selection, trans- 
mitting and interpreting information originating in 
the 
environment.ö 
Moreover, 
Jemison 
[38] 
argues that boundary 
spanners are important in 
strategic decision making because of their ability 
to recognize and deal with trends of changes in 
the environment. 
The implication, 
therefore, 
is 
clear. Industrial 
product managers are likely to 
need to span boundaries 
actively to understand 
external forces to be able to anticipate changes. 
The second implication deals with the impact 
of uncertainty 
on the product manager. Perceived 
uncertainty 
was related to role pressures of con- 
flict and ambiguity; 
these variables may lead to 
adverse 
outcomes 
such as dissatisfaction 
and 
tension. Uncertainty 
was also found to be associ- 
ated with lower performance, 
particularly overall 
performance. 
Hence, product managers, particu- 
larly those recently hired, may need better train- 
ing and skills to cope with and understand uncer- 
tainty. 
A third implication 
app lies to the benefits of 
bo;mdarv 
spanning. 
Unlike many other studies, 
this study did not find a positive 
association 
between role pressures of conflict and ambiguity 
with boundary spanning. Instead, the results indi- 
cated that as boundary spanning increased, these 
role pressures 
actually declined. Our interviews 
suggest that the product 
managersÆ 
efforts to 
communicate, 
despite the lack of encouragement. 
allowed them to understand 
the expectations 
of 
others, and possibly to shape the expectations of 
others, and, thus. lessening the likelihood of role 
182 
MANAG 
S. LYSONSKI AND A. G. WOODSiDE 
conflict. Such a result can also be explained 
in 
that boundary 
spanning 
activity 
would better 
assist the product managers in performing their 
j&s more effectively. 
Encouraging product man- 
agers to be better boundary 
spanners may actu- 
ally help to !essen role conflict and ambiguity. 
The product managerÆs boundary spanning was 
associated positively with performance 
in coordi- 
nating others but negatively with overall perfor- 
mance. Such a result may stem from the product 
manager 
using boundary 
spanning 
for coordi- 
nation but not for environmental 
scanning. which 
might help to improve overall product line perfor- 
mance. 
A fourth implication focuses on the potentially 
deleterious 
effects of role pressures. 
Most of the 
dimensions of role conflict were linked to tension 
and dissatisfaction. 
Role ambiguity also had a 
definite negative impact on satisfaction but less 
so on tension. It is likely that role ambiguity will 
increase for these product managers as the com- 
pany confronts 
competition 
from deregulation. 
Role ambiguity is likely to arise as the product 
managers adapt to the new environment 
and as 
senior management 
begins to redefine their job 
requirements. 
Indeed, they may not know what 
to do in such a changing environment, 
a type 
which they never had experienced 
before. This 
finding suggest that senior management may need 
to provide the information necessary for product 
managers to perform their tasks effectively. Such 
information 
may be particularly 
important 
for 
firms such as NZ Telecom that confront increas- 
ing competition 
and advancing tee hnologies. 
Performance 
was clearly seen to be related to 
various dimensions of role conflict. For example, 
the conflict experienced 
by the product manager 
from a single (intrasender) or from multiple (inter- 
sender) role senders was related to diminished 
performance. 
This may imply that product man- 
agers need to be given some help in their role in 
the expectations 
of others. 
Con- 
t managers often do not have au- 
ensurate 
with their responsibility. 
ty also was linked to diminished 
overall performance. 
Establishing clearer expec- 
tations in terms of how product managers will be 
evaluated 
and exactly what is expected 
might 
increase their performances. 
Methods to mitigate role pressures are many. 
Kahn et al. WI suggest several rqethods includ- 
ing changes in the organizational 
structure, devel- 
opment of new criteria for selection 
and place- 
ment of personnel, 
increasing 
the individualÆs 
tolerance and coping abilities and strengthening 
the interpersonal 
bonds 
among 
organizational 
members. 
A fifth implication 
deals with the effects of 
satisfaction and tension on performance. 
A prod- 
uct managerÆs 
satisfaction 
seemed 
to increase 
performance, 
which confirms 
some of the rela- 
tionships established 
in prior studies examining 
other organizational 
personnel. 
Moreover, 
ten- 
sion was also linked to reduced performance 
both 
in overall terms and in coordinating 
the actions of 
others. 
Since some forms of stress are to some degree 
inevitable, 
the key may be to reduce 
them to 
manageable 
levels 
1441. In the present 
study 
perceived environmental 
uncertainty 
was related 
to forms of role conflict and ambiguity. 
It is, 
therefore, 
likely that as environmental 
uncer- 
tainty increases- 
these role pressures 
will in- 
crease. 
Because the components 
of the study are new 
to research on industrial product management, 
it 
is hoped that this study will stimulate 
further 
thinking and research on industrial product man- 
agement. If we are to better understand 
behavior 
and performance 
of product managers, 
more rc- 
search on existing product management 
organiza- 
tions is needed. Research is also needed to invts- 
tigate how product 
managers 
can be given the 
requisite skills to deal more with uncertainty, 
role 
pressures 
and an increasing 
need to commu- 
nicate. An examination 
of the moderating effects 
of a product managerÆs need for clarity, need for 
achievement 
and other personal 
characteristics 
on the relationships 
in the model 
would also 
contribute 
to our understanding. 
In particular. 
the development 
of more integrative models simi- 
lar to the one used in this study is needed for 
better understanding 
of the industrial 
product 
management 
system. Longitudinal 
studies would 
also help to better understand 
another dimension 
of the relationships 
in this study. 
The various insights and implications 
derived 
from this stud!, should be accepied 
as tentative 
BOUNDARY ROLE SPANNlNG BEHAVlOR 
volving a variety of industrial product manage- 
20. 
ment settings. 
References 
æ) 
_. 
3. 
4. 
5. 
6. 
7. 
8. 
9. 
10. 
El 
12 
13 
I4 
I5 
lb 
slructure . 
sented at the American Sociologkal Association Conference. 
New Orleans, 1972. 
Aldrich. Howard and Herker, Diane. Boundary s 
ning roles 
and organizational structure. Academ_v o~~~a~ageme~t 
Rc~,iew 
2:217-230 
(1977). 
Anderson, C. and Paine. F. Managerial perceptions of strategic 
behavior. Academy ~f&#arna~ernen? JnutrmaI 18:8l l-823 I 1975). 
Bagozzi, Richard P. Sslecrcrson performance and satisfaction 
as a function of individual differences. inte 
rsonal and situa- 
tional factors. JÆcxtr~ul of .&d-A-erin.e Research 155 17-53 I 
(1978). 
Bateman, T. S. and Organ. D. W. Job satisfaction and the good 
soldier: the relationship between effect and employee citizen- 
ship. Academy 
of ,UanaFemen? 
Jotrrnal26:587-595 
( 1983). 
Beehr, Terry A., Walsh. Jeffrey T. and Taber. Thomas D. 
Relationship of stress to individually and organizationally val- 
ued states: higher order needs as a moderator. Jow~aC 
of 
Applied 
Ps+wlogy 
6 I :4 I-47 
( 19761. 
Behrman. Douglas N. and Perreault, William D., Jr. .4 role 
stress model of tl-.e performance and satisfaction of industrial 
salespersons. JownaI of Marketing 48:9-21 
( 19843). 
Benson. F 
The 
Morrow. 1975. 
Relaxation 
Response. 
New York: William 
Billings. R. S. and Wroten. S. P. Use of path analysis in 
industriallorganizationd 
psychology: criticisms and sugges- 
tions. Journal of Aophed Psyh~og~ 
63:677-688 
( 1978). 
Bohrnsteda. G. W. and Carten. T. M. Robustness in regression 
analysis. In: SociologL.al 
Methodology. 
H. L. Coster fed.). San 
Francisco: Jossey Bass. 1971. pp. 118-146. 
Boulton, William R.. Lindsay. William M., Franklin, Stephen 
G. and Rue, Leslie. Strategic planning: determining the impact 
of environmental characteristics and uncertainty. Academy 
of 
Management 
Journal 
25:500-509 
( 1982). 
Brown. W. B. Systems boundaries and information 
ernv of Management 
Journal 
13:318-327 
(1966). 
flow. Acad- 
Buell. V. P. The changing role of the product manager in 
consumer 
goods companies. 
Journal 
of Marketing 
39:3-l I 
(1975). 
Busch. P. and Rush R. F. Women contrasted to men in the 
industrial salesforce: job satisfaction, values. role clarity, per- 
formance and propensity to lealIe. Jorrrnal of Marketing 
Re- 
search f 5:438-448 
( 1978). 
Churchill, GilberE A.. Ford. Neil M. and Walker, Orville C. 
Measuring the job satisfaction of industrial salesmen. Jowtal 
of 
Marketing 
Research 
I I :25-I-260 ( 19741, 
Cokwn, S. After effects of stress on human performance and 
social behaviour: a review of research and theory. Psychologi- 
cal Bulletin 
88:82- 108 ( 1980). 
Conrath. David W. Organizing decision making behavior under 
varying 
conditions 
of 
uncertainty. 
Management 
Science 
13:B487-B500 (1967). 
mings, W. T.. Jackson D. W. and Ostrom, L. L. Differ- 
ences 
between 
industrial 
and consumer 
product 
managers. 
Industrial 
Marketing 
Management 
13:171-180 (1984). 
22. 
23. 
24. 
25. 
26. 
27. 
28. 
29. 
30. 
31. 
32. 
33. 
34. 
35. 
36. 
37. 
38. 
39. 
40. 
I83 
environmenti 
uncertaint) _ Proceedi 
FhE4 AcadempÆ u$ .Zfanagemenr. 
1975. 
cal examp& 
In: 
Bkkck. Jr. red.). 
New York: Macmiftan. t97l. 115-138. 
DUnCan. Rokrt 
B. Characteristics of organi7atiorr;rt 63wm3n- 
~IMZWS 
and perceived envimnmzntal 
t~ncertaint~ . ,a&ninistrative 
Science 
@arter!y 
i7:313-327 4 1972). 
Eckl~s. R. W. and Novotny . T. J. lmius~rial product mmager: 
authority and responsibility. Indastriai 
Marketing Marrapemem 
l3:7I-75 
t w?4). 
Franke. G. R.. Rehrman. D. N. and Perreault. W. D. Salesforce 
performance and satisfaction: 
contemporaneous 
relationships 
and selected antecedents. i!X 
AMA 
EducatorsÆ 
Conference 
Proceediws. 
Chicago: American Marketing Association. 1981,. 
233-237. 
Fry. Louis W.. Futrell, Charles. Parasuraman. A. and Chmie- 
lewski. Margaret. An analysis of alternative causal models of 
salesperson 
role perceptions and work-r&ted 
attitudes. Juur- 
naC of Marketing 
Research 
23: 153- 163 (1986). 
Galbraith, J. Organizational 
Des@. 
Reading, AMA: Addison, 
1977. 
Gemmilf, G. R. and WiIemon, D. t . The product manager as an 
i&uence agent. Journal of Marketing 
36:65-73 (1972). 
Heise. D. R. Problems in path analysis and causal infiuence. In: 
SociotogicaEl Methodology, 
E. F. Borgatta ted.). !!&=I Francisco: 
Jossey Bass. 1%9, 38-73. 
Heneman, 
G. Comparisons 
of self and superior ratings of 
managerial performance. 
Journal 
of 
Applied 
Psychology 
59:638-642 
(1974). 
House, Robert and Rizzo, John. Role conflict and ambiguity as 
criticat variables in a model of organizational behavior. Organi- 
zational 
Behavior 
and Human Per$ormance 
73467-505 (IY72). 
Howell, R. D., Bellenger. D. N. and Wilcox. J. B. Seif esteem. 
role stress and job satisfaction 
among marketing managers. 
Journal 
of Brtsiness 
Research 
15:71-84 ( 1987). 
Huber, 
George P., OÆConnell, 
Michael J. and Cummings. 
Larry. Perceived environmental uncertainty: effects of informa- 
Eion and sEructure. Academy 
of Management 
Journal 
æ8:725- 
740 ( 1975). 
Ivancevich, J. M. and Donnelly, J. H., Jr. A study of role clarity 
and need for clarity in three occupational groups. Academy 
of 
Management 
Journal 
17:28-36 (1974). 
James, L. R., Mulaik, S. A. and Brett, J. M. Caasal Analysis: 
Assumptions, 
Models and Data. Beverly Hills. CA: Sage Publi- 
cations, 1982. 
Janis. I. L. and Leventhal, H. Human reactions to stress. In: 
Handbook 
of Personality 
Theory and Research. 
E. F. Borgatta 
and W. W. Lambert (eds.). Chicago: Rand McNally. 1968. 
1041-1085. 
Jelinek, Mariann. Rethink strategy or perish. Journal off ro&ct 
innovation 
Management 
1:36-42 (1984). 
Jemison, D. B. The importance of boundary spanning roles in 
strategic 
decision 
making. Journal 
of Management 
Studies 
2I(2):131-152 
(19%4). 
Kahn, Robert L., Wolfe, D. M., Quinn, R. P., Snack, J. D. and 
xosenthal, R. A. Organkationa[ 
Stress. 
New York: Wiley. 
1964. 
Keller. Robert T. Role conflict and ambiguity: correlates with 
job satisfaction 
and values. personnel 
Psych010g~ 28:57--f+# 
( 1975). 
41. Keller. Robert T. and Sziiagji. Andrew. Employee reactions to 
leader re\\ ard behavior. 
Acrrdetn.~~ 
qf Mmtu~ctntwt 
Jownul 
19:619-627 
(1976). 
42 Ke?i!. J. P. and Hise. R. T. industrial and consumer goods 
prtduct manager3 are diRerent. Indmrrid 
Mcrrldtirt,k! 
Mc~tu~gt- 
frwfft 
8:3Y-332 
(199a). 
43. Kerlinger. F. N. and Pedhauzer. 
E. J. Multiple Regression in 
Buhattiorul Re.~u~h. 
New York: Holt Rinehart and Winston. 
1973. 
44. Kets de Vries. hlanfred. Organizational stress: a ~11 for man- 
agement action. SlcJun Muncr~entenr Recim, 2 I( I ):3- 14 ( 1979). 
45 
C. Principles of path analysis. in: Sociohgicul 
Murk- 
San Francisco: Jossey Bass. i%9. 15-27. 
46. Lazarus. R. S.. Ikese. 
J. and Osier. J. F. The effects of 
psychological stress upon performance. Psychological Bulletin 
49:293-316 (1952). 
47. Lebiebicb. Husc! ;n ..tnd &,lancik. Gerald R. Effects of environ- 
mcnlal uncertainty on information and decision processes in 
banks. Adtninisrrurke Scienct~ Qzturtt~rIF 26(4):578-596 ( 1% I j 
4% Leifer. Richard Paul. An analysis of the charxteristics 
and 
functioning of interorganizational boundary spanning person- 
nel. Ph.D. dihbertation. Madison: 
LÆnivercit! 
of Wi5con:*in 
(19?_c). 
49. Luck. David. Interfaces of a product manager. Jam-nui c?f 
Markering 32:32-36 (1969). 
$0. 
Cl. 
Lvsonski 
Steven. 
. 
&duct 
managerÆs 
A boundary theory investigation 
role. Jmrnnl qf Markring 492630 
of the 
(19SC). 
McDaniel. Carl and Graj 
rtin :lhnoeetnenr Reciert. 
D. A. The oroduct 
æ23: 143-150Æ11980). 
manager. Cu&r- 
5: 
&Iichaciq. R. E.. Day. R. L. and Joachimsthaler. E. E. Role 
stress among industrial bu>,ers: an integrative model. Joztrnul qf 
.!?ctrkerrng 5 I : 28-45 ( 1987). 
53. hllies. Robert H. A comparison cf the relative impxts of role 
I\+-rceptions of ambiguity and conflict by role. Acndcw~ 
of 
\I/ w,gcnte~,l Jorcrnul 19( I ):Y-35 t i976). 
54. \&de.,. I.,~bert H. Organizational boundarv roles. In: Cztrrctzl 
Cotzcctm itz 0~ cq-mj~~ttul S;rc~~ 1. G. L. Cooper and R. Payne 
feds.). Sew 1Æork: Wiley. 1976. 
55. Jliles. Robert H. Role conflict and ambiguity 13 boundary and 
internal ruleb: a field stud) usin p role set analysis and panel 
design. Ph.D. dissertation. Chaps! Hill: University of North 
Carolina ( 1974). 
56. Miles. Robert H. Role requirements as sources of stress in R&D 
organizations. Proceedings of rlw 3stir Meering of the Academ> 
of Management. 1975. 191-193. 
57. Miles. Robert H. and Perreault. Wt:!iam D.. Jr. Organizational 
role conflict: its antecedents and consequences. Orgnni:arional 
Belrnch 
und Hztttzun Pt~rfimncrtzcy 17: 19-44 ( 1976). 
58. Motouildo. S. J. Does job satisfaction lead to consideration and 
personal senzitiviiy? Acudemy c?f .Vunugcttzrtzr Jorcrtzul 27:9lO- 
915 (19841. 
59. Motowildo, S. J.. Packard. J. S. and Manning. M. R. Occupa- 
tional stress: its causes and consequences for job performance. 
Joztrtznr of Applied Psychohg~ 
71(4):618-629 ( 1986). 
6@. Nunnally. Jim C. PcyclzotmJtric Tl~ot~. Ne\+ York: McGratb- 
Hlll. 
1967. 
61. Organ. Dtanis 
W. Sam: 
variables 
affecting 
boundary 
role 
behavior. Sctciotnet~ 
34: 524-537 ( 197 I 1. 
62. Pedhauzer. E. J. Mzrltiplc Regression in Erl:u~h 
:I Resmrch. 
Zd ed. New York: Holt. Rinehart and Winston. 1982. 
63. Petrini. B. 
:. and Grub. P. D. Product management in high 
technology defense industrial marketing. 
CÆalifarnia Munage- 
tnent Review IS: 138-146 (1973). 
64. Pruden. Henry 0. and Reese. R. Interorganizational 
role-set 
relations and the performance 
and satisfaction 
of industrial 
salesmen. Adtninistrative Science Quarterly 17:601-609 ( 19721. 
65. Pym. D. L. A. and Auld. H. D. The self-rating as a measure of 
employee 
satisfactoriness. 
Occuparional Psyhology 
39: 103- 
ii3 (i%C). 
66. Quinn. R. P. and Shepard. 
L. J. The 1972-1973 quality of 
employment survey: descriptive statistics with comparison data 
from the 1969-1970 survey of warking conditions. Ann Arbor. 
MI: The institute for Social Research, 
1974. 
67. Rizzo. John, House. Robert and Lirtzman. Sidney. Role conflict 
and ambiguity in complex organization. 
Administrarive Science 
Qzumerly 15:1501-1563 (1970). 
68. Roos. Leslie. Jr. and Starke. Frederick. Organizational roles. 
in: HundbooX oj Organixrionul 
Design. P. C. Nystrom and 
W. H. Starbuck feds.). New York: Oxford Press, 1981. 
69. Schuler. Randall S., Aldag, Ramon J. and Brief, Arthur P. Role 
conflict and ambiguit! : a scale analysis. Organi,-ational Behav- 
ior and Hzcrmn Perfortmznce 16: Ill-128 
(1977). 
70. Sheridan. 
J. E. and Slocum, J. The direction of the causal 
relationship 
between job satisfaction 
and work performance. 
Or~ani~ariorrul Bckarhr n& Human Pcrfnrtnnncr i 3: 159 - 172 
(1974). 
7 I. Smith. C. A.. Organ. D. W. and Near. J. P. Organizational 
citizenship 
behavior: 
its nature and antecedents. 
Jmrtta~ of 
Applied Psychology 68:653-663 ( 1983). 
72. Taylor. J. A. A personality scale of manifest anxiety. Jourtmlof 
Ahnartnul Social Ps_~lzolog_~ 48: 285-290 ( 1953 1. 
73. Teas. 
R. K. Supervisory behavior. role stress and the job 
satisfaction 
of industrial 
salespeople. 
Jozrrnal of Murkefirzg 
Researciz 20:84-91 (1983). 
74. Thompson. J. D. Organi:arinns in Acrion. New York: McGraw- 
Hill. 1967. 
75. Walker, 0. C.. Churchill, G. A. and Ford, N. M. Motivation 
and performance in industrial seiling: present knowledge and 
needed research . Journal of Markehg 
Research 14: 156- 168 
4 1977). 
76. Wall. James A. and Adams, J. Stacey. Some variables affecting 
constituentsÆ evaluations of and behavior toward a boundary 
role occupant. 
Or~atzi:arional Bekovior mad H~tmn Pet-for- 
tmznce I I :390-408 ( 1974). 
77. Weed. Stanley E. and Mitchell. Terence R. the role of environ- 
mental and behavioral uncertainty as a mediator of situation- 
performance relationshlps. Academy of Munugetnen~ JmcrtnuI 
33:36-60 (1980). 
78. Wright. Sewall. Path coefficients and path regr:s\ ion;: alterna- 
tive or complementary conceptsÆ? Biottzehcs 
16: 189-202 t 1970). 

