ture of the manager's 
relationships with his or her direct superior, the boss, I used Liden & Maslyn's (1986) 
LMX-MDM scales. The LMX-MDM is drawn from the Leader Member Exchange 
(LMX) literature, a literature whose focus is the measurement and assessment of the 
dyadic relationships between managers and their subordinate employees. In order to 
61 
maintain clarity of the relationships and organization levels in this study, I follow 
Tangirala et al. (2007) and Venkataramani et al. (2010) and refer to the relationship 
between a manager and his or her boss as Leader Leader Exchange or LLX. The 
relationship between a manager and his or her subordinate measured along the same 
dimensions retains the label Leader Member Exchange (LMX). 
The LMX-MDM is a 12-item set of scales which is organized into four three-item 
factors or subscales. The four factors are: (a) Affect, the degree to which there is 
affection and friendship between the boss and the manager, (b) Loyalty, the extent to 
which the respondent believes that his or her partner in the relationship would support 
and defend him or her to others throughout the organization, (c) Contribution, the extent 
to which the manager would expend extra effort in order to deliver results to the boss, 
and (d) Respect, the extent to which the respondent looks favorably upon the target's job 
related skills and accomplishments. Although the LMX-MDM has been developed more 
recently than other more established LMX measures, it has two distinct advantages in this 
study. First, recent studies establish that the LMX-MDM has incremental explanatory 
power as an independent variable above other scales (Greguras & Ford, 2006). Second, 
the distinct dimensions of the LMX-MDM allow the researcher to differentiate two 
different interpretations of the relationship between a supervisor and his or her 
subordinate. On the one hand, the relationship may be thought of as one of social 
exchange (Sparrowe & Liden, 1997) in which the two parties engage in providing effort 
and favors on each other's behalf. This, to some degree, represents an instrumental 
flavor to the relationship. On the other hand, the supervisor/subordinate relationship may 
62 
be more affective in nature, rooted in mutual liking and trust (Graen & Uhl-bien, 1995). 
The specific items for the four factors are detailed in Appendix A. 
In the LMX literature, the evaluation of LMX is most often performed by the 
subordinate in the relationship. However, in a few instances (e.g. Sparrowe, Soetjipto, & 
Kraimer, 2006; Greguras & Ford, 2006), the superior in the dyadic relationship evaluates 
the relationship as well. For this study, I chose to have LLX assessed by the boss. There 
are two rationales for this decision. First, the boss perspective on LLX mirrors the in-
degree approach on horizontal networks, providing a view of the relationship from an 
external party. Second, as the manager is the focal player in this study, the boss 
assessment of LLX somewhat insulates the analyses from hidden variable problems and 
common source bias. To the 12 items in the LMX-MDM, I added two additional items 
designed to mirror the items in the peer network sociomatrices. I asked the boss to assess 
the degree to which (a) "you view the employee as a friend, someone you would socialize 
with outside of work," and (b) "you view the employee as a source of work or technical 
advice." Participants assessed all 14 items on a 5 point Likert scale where 
l=significantly disagree and 5 = significantly agree. 
Prior to engaging in the analyses for the study, I confirmed that the four factors of 
the LMX-MDM were distinct and reliable measures. I conducted a confirmatory factor 
analysis15 to confirm that the items were best represented by the four factors suggested by 
prior research. Table 5 displays the results of this CFA. The sample for these studies 
was all bosses or managers in Organizations A, B, and C who were in the sample for the 
15 All confirmatory factor analyses were conducted using MPlus, Version 6. 
63 
analyses for the study. In Table 5, model 1, or the "full model" captures each of the four 
factors as separate factors. Models 2-7 constrain the full model by collapsing specific 
pairs of factors to one. Model 8 models LMX-MDM as one factor. As reflected in Table 
5, the full model fit the data well %2 (48, N=66) = 103, (Comparative Fit Index = .96, 
Root Mean Square Error of Approximation = .086, Standardized Root Mean Square 
Residual = .041). I also confirmed that each of the four factors displayed sufficient 
internal reliability. Cronbach's alphas for the constructs ultimately used in the analysis 
are displayed on the diagonal of Table 8. 
As a final step, I evaluated the pairwise correlations among these four constructs. 
As reflected in the note on Table 5, there are modest to strong inter-correlations among 
these variables. Throughout this study, I constrain study variables to share no more than 
50% variance or a Pearson correlation of .707 or less. As displayed in the note on Table 
5, Affect and Loyalty have a pairwise correlation of .73, and Contribution and Respect 
have a pairwise correlation of .75. I therefore removed Loyalty and Respect from the 
analysis. The two LLX variables, then, are LLX-Affect and LLX-Contribution.16 Affect 
and Contribution remain moderately correlated, r=.64. While this correlation is still 
moderately high, I checked for multicollinearity using VIF tests and found none. 
TV. 5. b Intervening Variables: Network Benefits and Costs 
161 also captured two single item measures between manager and boss designed to mirror the friendship 
and advice network questions on the sociomatrices. These items were measured on the same 5 point Likert 
scales as the remainder of the LMX-MDM items. The friendship proxy (analogous to friendship in-degree 
centrality among peers) had a .68 correlation with the three item LLX-Affect scale. The advice proxy 
(analogous to advice in-degree centrality among peers) had a .75 correlation with the three item LLX-
Respect factor. 
64 
The theoretical model identifies two benefits of managers' external relationships 
(information/resource access and perceived manager status) and two potential costs 
(ascribed identity and manager accessibility). I used existing scales and items to measure 
the network benefits, but adapted and developed new scales to measure the two costs. I 
discuss the scales for the network benefits first below, follow that with a discussion of the 
network costs, and follow that with a confirmatory factor analysis across all four 
constructs. The items for all of these scales may be found in Appendix A. 
Resource and Information Access. At Time 1, subordinates completed a 6-item 
access to resources and information scale from Spreitzer (1996). Sample items include "I 
have access to the strategic information I need to do my job well" and "I have access to 
the resources I need to do my job well." Spreitzer's (1996) work suggests that these 6 
items represent two distinct 3-item factors, one representing information access and one 
representing resource access. I subjected the items to a confirmatory factor analysis, 
discussed below, and confirmed that they represent two distinct factors in my study as 
well. Cronbach's alphas for all individual/subordinate level constructs may be found on 
the diagonal of table 8. 
Perceived Manager Status. At Time 1, employees completed a \2-item perceived 
manager status scale adapted from Eisenberger et al. (2002). Sample items include "The 
organization holds my supervisor in high regard" and "My supervisor influences 
decisions made by upper management." I reduced the number of items in this scale to 6 
by (a) conducting an exploratory factor analysis and (b) identifying those items that had 
the most face validity with the theory constructed earlier, namely that subordinates 
65 
perceive their managers as having the ability to participate in decision making, the ability 
to influence superiors, and the autonomy to make their own decisions . I conducted an 
exploratory factor analysis using a sample of 107 study participants who would not be 
part of the subject pool for the core study. These 107 participants represent 65 front line 
employees in Organization D, the pilot site, and 42 employees in Organizations A, B, and 
C who were the only employees to participate for those given managers18. A promax 
oblique rotation yielded a two factor model with six times loading above .6 on the first 
factor. I used these six items, listed in Appendix A, for the perceived manager status 
scale. 
Ascribed Identity. Under social identity theory (SIT), people make assessments 
regarding the degree to which they and others seem like members of particular 
identifiable groups. In particular, members of a group make determinations as to whether 
they and others seem like in-group members or alternatively out-group members. 
Colloquially, members assess the degree to which an individual is "one of us" or "one of 
them." Individuals use other members' social identity markersùfor example, job 
function, demographics, attitudes, and behaviorsùto determine the degree to which they 
perceive them to be prototypicalùor membersùof the in-group, or, alternatively, 
prototypical members of salient out-groups. The degree of perceived membership in one 
group or another is an intervening variable that SIT suggests predicts a number of 
17 All exploratory factor analyses were conducted using Proc Factor in SAS v. 9.2. 
18 The core analyses for the main study in this dissertation use a multi-level modeling framework with 
subordinate employees nested within managers. In this framework, there must be at least two level-1 data 
points nested within each level-2 group (Gelman & Hill, 2007). These 42 individuals were the only 
subordinate employees to participate in the study for these managers making them unsuitable f
